<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-ROM23361-TFP-83-7LH">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S2145 IS: Patsy T. Mink and Louise M. Slaughter Gender Equity in Education Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code>
<congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>S. 2145</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber>
<action>
<action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S361">Ms. Hirono</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S313">Mr. Sanders</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S354">Ms. Baldwin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S341">Mr. Blumenthal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S275">Ms. Cantwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S221">Mrs. Feinstein</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S311">Ms. Klobuchar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S369">Mr. Markey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S322">Mr. Merkley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S364">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S353">Mr. Schatz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S394">Ms. Smith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S390">Mr. Van Hollen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S247">Mr. Wyden</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title>To support educational entities in fully implementing title IX and reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HB15129D9AEF247D79F424D502D825400">
<section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Patsy T. Mink and Louise M. Slaughter Gender Equity in Education Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4DC572C51447427DA1EE7CB7B3A16399"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="id2D6DFC27DED0485DB13B5C356A98B721"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>) and the implementing regulations of title IX prohibit sex discrimination in federally funded education programs and activities. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idfc5584f7bad14a5b82f34c5260b7c73e"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Although title IX requires that schools treat students equally with regard to athletic participation opportunities, athletic scholarships, and the benefits and services provided to athletic teams, female participation rates, especially for girls of color, lag far behind male participation rates. Nationally, for example, boys receive more than 1,000,000 more opportunities to play high school sports than girls. Furthermore, although girls comprise nearly 50 percent of high school students, schools provide them with only 43 percent of athletic opportunities, even though girls want to play in greater numbers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id60d1407e02924e109e6192927230161d"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A recent report from the Women’s Sports Foundation found that Black, Indigenous, and People of Color (BIPOC) women still lag behind White women in collegiate sports—14 percent compared to 30 percent, respectively. These disparities are also prevalent at the high school level, with fewer athletic opportunities available to students in heavily minority schools compared to heavily White schools. In a typical heavily minority school, there are only 25 athletic spots available for every 100 students, compared to 58 athletic spots for every 100 students in a typical heavily White school. Further broken down by gender, girls have 82 percent of the athletic opportunities that boys do in a heavily White school, compared to 67 percent for girls in a heavily minority school.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id9dd867a559354bd99e50ff2deeff273d"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Girl athletes have been found to have higher levels of self-esteem, as well as reduced risk for cardiovascular disease, diabetes, osteoporosis, and breast cancer, compared to girls who do not play sports. In addition, girl athletes are more likely to graduate from high school, score higher on standardized tests, and have higher grades than girls who do not play sports. Girls who play sports in high school go on to earn 7 percent higher annual wages than those who do not play sports, and are more likely to enter the labor force and pursue higher-skill, previously male-dominated positions. Generally, sports participation for women is associated with a lower prevalence of experiencing intimate partner violence, reinforcing that athletic access not only strengthens health, educational, and workplace outcomes, but also personal safety. According to a 2023 report from the Women’s Sports Foundation, girls who played sports during the first year of the COVID–19 pandemic fared significantly better than girls who did not, reporting higher levels of self-esteem, self-efficacy, and social support, and lower levels of loneliness and depression.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idd7a6119b22e1411eb697d21a0c4134b8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Although the availability of athletic scholarships facilitates access to higher education, many institutions of higher education fail to award proportional athletic financial aid to women, which can affect their long-term employment outcomes and economic security. According to the Department of Education’s Equity in Athletics Disclosure Act data from 2019 through 2020, men received $252,000,000 more in athletic scholarships than women.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id6bf43bcc94f84d31829e2332064036ee"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Although title IX ensures gender equity in career and technical education, women are severely underrepresented in fields nontraditional to their gender. According to the National Coalition for Women and Girls in Education, women make up more than 80 percent of workers with training or certification in historically women-dominated occupations that pay less than $30,000 per year, including child care, early childhood education, home care, and cosmetology. Women represent less than 40 percent of workers trained or certified in high-paying and historically male-dominated fields, including transportation, advanced manufacturing, and construction.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id11e0e46c17f44a089f01979f1c0f7766"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Although title IX promotes gender equity in the fields of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (in this section referred to as <quote>STEM</quote>) education, women are disproportionately lost at nearly every stage of the STEM pipeline. A recent report by the National Center for Education Statistics showed that women earned only 32 percent of all STEM degrees in 2017, and nearly <fraction>1/2</fraction> of these women were White. Women of color earned about 12 percent of STEM degrees in that same year. Furthermore, in STEM fields where women are particularly underrepresented, such as computing and engineering, women earned an even smaller percentage of degrees, including only 19 percent of computing bachelor’s degrees, and 21 percent of engineering bachelor’s degrees.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id658d9f9d6b224b1aadaff9d7d3e28340"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Although title IX prohibits sex discrimination in employment in federally funded education programs, according to the National Science Foundation, women only hold 34 percent of all tenured and tenure-track positions and 27 percent of full professor positions in STEM fields. Furthermore, Black and Latina women, together, hold only 4 percent of all tenured and tenure-track positions and barely over 2 percent of full professor positions in STEM fields. Asian-American women hold around 5 percent of all tenured and tenure-track positions, and less than 3 percent of full professor positions in STEM fields.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idd504c5516b3e43b587dcbf164cf7b92e"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Although title IX protects against sex-based harassment and violence, 56 percent of girls and 40 percent of boys in grades 7 through 12 experience sexual harassment each year, and 9 percent of girls and 7 percent of boys in high school experience physical dating violence each year. In addition, more than 60 percent of women and men in college experience sexual harassment each year, and 14 percent of women and 10 percent of men in college experience dating violence. Moreover, these statistics are often higher for marginalized students, including Black and Brown girls and women, lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer, and questioning (referred to in this section as <quote>LGBTQI+</quote>) students, pregnant and parenting students, and disabled students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id18296e0eb98d4aaab4fbe53e5184edc1"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to GLSEN, 87 percent of LGBTQI+ students have experienced harassment or assault based on a personal characteristic, and nearly 66 percent have experienced LGBTQI+-related verbal harassment at school based on sexual orientation. Research has shown that LGBTQI+ students who experience harassment at school are more likely to experience depression and anxiety, to engage in unhealthy and antisocial behaviors, and to have more unexcused absences from school.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id7a17adbb52e74c8e88df0baa16471884"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Although title IX prohibits discrimination on the basis of pregnancy or parenting status, the limited availability of accommodations, including lactation accommodations, excused absences for pregnancy-related medical conditions, and child care needs (including caring for a sick child), is a leading reason that parenting mothers drop out of high school. According to the National Women’s Law Center, only half of teenage mothers earn a high school diploma by the age of 22, compared to 89 percent of women who do not have a child during their teenage years, and one-third of young mothers will never get a diploma or a GED, further limiting continuing opportunities for education and employment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id3ef3c62f1df742c89ab64428d501fab4"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Although title IX protects against discrimination based on stereotypes of actual or perceived sex, many people carry implicit or unconscious biases that can unintentionally influence attitudes, beliefs, behaviors, and decision-making processes. Research has shown that unconscious biases can impact classroom environments, teaching methods, student evaluations, disciplinary practices, and career and counseling guidance, which can lead to discrimination against students based on race, color, national origin, and disability, particularly for students who are pursuing nontraditional fields.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="iddf1863075b4143cb8acf148c7520e1ca"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Nationally, the Feminist Majority Foundation estimates 100,000 title IX coordinators are needed to meet the needs of schools serving children in prekindergarten through grade 12, local educational agencies, and postsecondary institutions. However, in 2016, the Department of Education only identified 23,000 title IX coordinators nationwide. The Feminist Majority Foundation has found that schools serving children in prekindergarten through grade 12 rarely have their own title IX coordinators. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="ide01ee98f9f0d41dcb474b768c3e567f4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="id431DA75BECD843F781F9BA50443AF99B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>institution of higher education</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>school leader</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4da7fe31d0df4348b10f123592b9b25f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id9D15AC82B86C426B8D7B93D552FCAED0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office for Gender Equity established under section 5(a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idA66C8E027C4A43598E9595BA1F38FB23"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Educational entity</header><text>The term <term>educational entity</term> means any of the following entities that receive Federal funds:</text>
<subparagraph id="id23A0033874F04CB1A1AAE680433B0AFF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A State educational agency.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idAF9394A820474DBDBD342C9B935C587E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A local educational agency.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idFFE5D33D2E424094898761E3FB4EF090"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id8AE261E8D1C44E85BCCB590EB0781831"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An elementary school or secondary school.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idc6ab3b3f51bd49b6ae9be14854ce2187"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Another entity covered by title IX, such as a laboratory, library, or museum that provides education programs and activities. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida6102f2649f5464aacf65daa9598c864"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Evidence-based</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based</term> has the meaning given the term in clause (i) or (ii) of section 8101(21)(A) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801(21)(A)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id72c49dd8acc04384925431f3cdf19efd"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gender identity</header><text>The term <term>gender identity</term> means the gender-related identity, appearance, mannerisms, or other gender-related characteristics of an individual, regardless of the individual’s designated sex at birth.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idD9BB0D44BDA24CBFB1837050F2158431"><enum>(7)</enum><header>National gender equity infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>national gender equity infrastructure</term> means the horizontal and vertical network of title IX coordinators and title IX allies who work to advance gender equity and eliminate discrimination in the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id074d225213674df086c6c3da089e50b0"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id378e6f0ffc8340f9968e54567f8b902d"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Sex</header><text>The term <term>sex</term> includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="id34171f8dba1443ee836cfbe76030d937"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a sex stereotype;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id2c2bfa74d7234bb690960e02e75d64a4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>pregnancy, childbirth, or a related medical condition;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id501f829850df43b38319955139dda56e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>sexual orientation or gender identity; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id5a25d896d0d34884b5d80ca03d76cb41"><enum>(D)</enum><text>sex characteristics, including intersex traits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id8f7c138b55f0497db0d48e8a075c72a7"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Sexual orientation</header><text>The term <term>sexual orientation</term> means homosexuality, heterosexuality, or bisexuality.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida736dc4ce8074421b9030dad3a059ccd"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Title IX</header><text>The term <term>title IX</term> means title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idd40d99b19ed9412f82cbecc20cc92597"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Title IX ally</header><text>The term <term>title IX ally</term> means an individual who—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb65041133dc94113a913b0b8cd042dde"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is an employee at an educational entity (other than a title IX coordinator), a community stakeholder, or an equity expert; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3b5070402b6b4fc2ac4b47a2cf949f2f"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">helps to fully implement title IX. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="idf3e06f4e7f6d4a37baf6281bc41365b5"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Title IX coordinator</header><text>The term <term>title IX coordinator</term> means a responsible employee, as described in section 106.8(a) of title 34, Code of Federal Regulations, or successor regulations, designated to coordinate efforts under title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></section>
<section id="idb175609360694ac9affce439cf0ef93c"><enum>4.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are to—</text> <paragraph id="id689051c17b9c4d619592d4df1f06987c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advance gender equity in education in the United States;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idb95f219d70f7425aa9a44f6f3404fbc2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support educational entities so that such entities have the support to fully implement title IX;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idfa4ecc8703b84eb39b4360c40322f7a5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide title IX coordinators and title IX allies with training, technical assistance, and support to fully carry out their roles and responsibilities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id60d206dd0f6640738e87dff6c245f074"><enum>(4)</enum><text>increase general awareness about the rights and obligations of individuals and entities under title IX;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id3b03a25e685b4a9993140fa20dc7baf9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify, implement, and disseminate best practices for reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id18e30010eaea4143825eceec1413a6e3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>promote educational environments that are safe and free of sexual and sex-based bullying, harassment, and violence; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="ida709db504a244f3ba9bdc776834ad914"><enum>(7)</enum><text>promote equity in education for students and staff who face discrimination based on multiple and intersectional actual or perceived characteristics, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="idDFB747D3C8204292BCBF7D30D1878F24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>race;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1fa6b512240448a79865ec97a9a62bca"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idC77DFF2FEAB947919539C231E67316ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id2AAB131C127B4D4E93F62866A8F876A1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>national origin;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id74F2808347D3478E9F28A9BA2D41EC2F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>disability;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idF7D92A7CC0D34382983756E824098071"><enum>(F)</enum><text>religion;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id60FD00D730E74D48BC08313137D93FB4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>age; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id03D582B7ECE446EF8446734FACBF7F17"><enum>(H)</enum><text>sex; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id8a8e6e4aaa214bd899c050f416dfb110"><enum>(8)</enum><text>promote activities that strengthen the national gender equity infrastructure. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="id9ae122e2dabc4c01a5141eda7717d20a"><enum>5.</enum><header>Establishment of an Office for Gender Equity</header> <subsection id="id0872999073644a7b83f42639d8246949"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an Office for Gender Equity. The Director of the Office for Gender Equity shall be the Special Assistant for Gender Equity, as authorized under section 202(b)(3) of the Department of Education Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3412">20 U.S.C. 3412(b)(3)</external-xref>). The Director of the Office for Gender Equity shall report directly to the Secretary.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="idcc7a032776fd441f8ffb5a56301bcc6d"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Office for Gender Equity shall be responsible for the following:</text> <paragraph id="ide78c562fd4294f35a3a335f109e8e88a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Supporting educational entities in the full implementation of title IX.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id8bc66844ebe04100a7dc844287db8644"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Providing title IX coordinators and title IX allies with training, technical assistance, and support to fully carry out their roles and responsibilities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idbdc49370ff1c4fb4ab3052452bec8878"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providing grants to implement programs and activities that are focused on reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idface9909df204296a23836c34b309711"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Identifying and disseminating information and evidence-based best practices for reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id62cc58bcf94d4613b9e34607915cd662"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Maintaining an Office for Gender Equity resource center website to disseminate information and evidence-based best practices for achieving gender equity.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id6942b6723d9c47008a105bd6f626d087"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Performing any other activity consistent with achieving the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="idf1ff167a56e843d0a641ad5242814ba6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>To carry out the purposes of this Act, the Secretary shall coordinate with other relevant Federal offices and agencies, including—</text>
<paragraph id="ide507f2c5a6d6483ab96b1ae6b16dd895"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the White House Gender Policy Council;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idb688d9d0e7c4413f8c2bf124c4559da1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the White House Domestic Policy Council;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id015fb8482df047adb3bf61e5917b50ab"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Office for Civil Rights of the Department of Education;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idbb33e1ebfda34eb8b7e69fd0e58ebb3d"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Institute of Education Sciences; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id76f9cfd6cae54ca3a9f1c076335c69bc"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Women's Bureau of the Department of Labor;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id6308ab63d617403c92176383e7a7705d"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Office on Women's Health of the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id00d03bdb213149e9b47302f41c2afa0e"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Civil Rights Division of the Department of Justice;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id544b6d71b9c04328b767c95a313e4dec"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Office on Violence Against Women of the Department of Justice;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id1ca898586ead48af9f741ee318dc4892"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id7ded90de346242acb398dafc1599c835"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the Office of Safe and Healthy Students of the Department of Education; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idf19b0bdba69845c182ec75d2b73aa1b0"><enum>(11)</enum><text>other entities determined relevant for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="idf9edc39ada32419f92d58b0713700aac"><enum>6.</enum><header>Support for title IX coordinators and title IX allies</header> <subsection id="id1f0b6049873d42a1ba43b96691b07401"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall provide coordination, training, technical assistance, and support for title IX coordinators and title IX allies to ensure that educational entities are able to fully implement title IX and reduce and prevent sex discrimination in all areas of education.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="id0d56f1b31bc2474ebd514968564b383f"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Title IX coordinator training</header>
<paragraph id="id2d0050ba64c94f779a56b10806986251"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
<subparagraph id="id9c9dd0ce6a904fbe837d5ad1d112cd7e"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Title ix coordinator training</header><text>Not less than once a year, the Director shall conduct a training for all title IX coordinators, which shall address the different needs of elementary schools, secondary schools, local educational agencies, and institutions of higher education. The training may be conducted in partnership with a national organization with relevant expertise, and may be completed online or in person.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide246496fbd6040b5baee55f5f02c74b9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Availability to title IX allies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each training conducted under subparagraph (A) shall be made available to title IX allies to the maximum extent practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id1e7385a42ec848f5ad7c29332e4e5d78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of training</header><text>The training described in paragraph (1) shall include the following information:</text> <subparagraph id="id39b058921eab4a5abb0bd5c4a3cc942a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The role and responsibility of title IX coordinators.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idc85ca30b47b04d15b93bc0219461b562"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information and evidence-based best practices for increasing awareness about rights and obligations under title IX.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id3473638356dc4df9a6d87681ee8e781d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Information and evidence-based best practices for investigating and responding to claims of violations of title IX.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id0591aa3ac47e443d914ff4f2f10b2f9a"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Information and evidence-based best practices for identifying and preventing implicit and explicit sex discrimination in all areas of education, including—</text> <clause id="id08cc3da9cf1d4e9fb88c6abc43b6bff8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>recruitment and admissions;</text></clause>
<clause id="id06a79ba8088243628c058d7e802ab473"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>teaching practices, textbooks, and curricula;</text></clause> <clause id="ide5ea57e29eec4bce9d3b8c7768aa079f"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>campus safety and security;</text></clause>
<clause id="id7d5a3ee1d90343e7870422eee7767696"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>financial assistance;</text></clause> <clause id="id143d4f9b14724bc0b587d6d93634d2b3"><enum>(v)</enum><text>access to facilities, resources, and housing;</text></clause>
<clause id="ida7c54ee081514e94813dedbdf28ede51"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>access to course offerings;</text></clause> <clause id="idf5b3fd11040445b1811cc5f94decf4c1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>student health services and insurance benefits;</text></clause>
<clause id="id9e440c8f54004e08811858c41e06b87e"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>counseling and career guidance;</text></clause> <clause id="id98cd808c73d640ccbd29594c9df6ec73"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>athletics;</text></clause>
<clause id="idfb353884074347b38a27699570a9f537"><enum>(x)</enum><text>discipline policies;</text></clause> <clause id="id7517D574821A43B28F87C5DEFDE94705"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>employment; and</text></clause>
<clause id="id4F447E4C70724FAEA14C2EA1C60605E2"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>other areas that the Director determines are relevant for such purposes.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="idb7e23869dee9468baf7876cf3eafb36d"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application of Training</header> <subparagraph id="id27E4B38AEEB149938C65964D859DA7B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Director shall take steps to ensure that the trainings described in paragraph (1)—</text>
<clause id="idDAEC1276847847448FF24F5793EDDC4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are adapted, as necessary, to address issues of sex discrimination at all levels of education;</text></clause> <clause id="id73E499FDB0564F4C9C11761081DCFA15"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are updated with the latest information and evidence-based best practices; and</text></clause>
<clause id="id9E18365B5D5142749504D34C59C2D63D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>address recent trends in sex discrimination.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id8add16b0f6c64eff9958dad7d216b8af"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Attention to discrimination based on multiple characteristics</header><text>The Director shall take steps to ensure that such trainings include attention to students who face discrimination based on multiple actual or perceived characteristics, including—</text>
<clause id="id517292D65B6D4963BA65F48F92E59E5C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>race;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id15df84bb060a47c5a440e245808c3dd6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></clause>
<clause id="idD9483B5D766446C78CCF589D8CB3EEC4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></clause> <clause id="idB59B7F3E7A844FE584A9ADB583A9E5A5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>national origin;</text></clause>
<clause id="id016822CA92E14B03AB47C6C478212028"><enum>(v)</enum><text>disability;</text></clause> <clause id="id10048B0FACC2492FA4F8638C9498112C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>religion;</text></clause>
<clause id="idF59D5E3858584F43B7318AF3E2F7E583"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>age; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4F8C926A6E164FEFB4C16AB84CAB1B89"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>sex.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id23df602d718948aa9b7378155ee7eeb7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The Director shall—</text> <clause id="idAA80FCF0E1BF485693DE7EE01B4E1CB6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop and conduct pre- and post-training evaluations to assess the effectiveness of such trainings in improving the knowledge of the roles and responsibilities of title IX coordinators; and</text></clause>
<clause id="idD481B523039E41318EE9C027489BCF86"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>use such evaluations to update the title IX coordinator trainings annually and replicate effective models and practices for use by title IX coordinators and title IX allies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="id834d728f2e654c55bd1aa5ec03fdb782"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Handbook for conducting title IX compliance self-Evaluations</header><text>The Director shall develop a handbook for conducting self-evaluations of compliance with title IX in all areas of education, as described in subsection (b)(2)(D).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="id9cc7907a20cd42338256f50f2d0f582d"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assessment of support for title IX coordinators and title IX allies</header><text>The Director shall collect relevant data and statistics on all title IX coordinators, including demographic information for gender, race, and ethnicity, salary information, budgets, and primary roles, in order to make recommendations for improving title IX coordinator support. The assessment shall also describe how title IX coordinators work with title IX allies and others within the national gender equity infrastructure.</text></subsection> <subsection id="id661603e9433348aba003fa7de72821e2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The Director shall ensure that the workplace contact information of all title IX coordinators and any training materials or information developed under this section are made available on the Office for Gender Equity resource center website described in section 5(b)(5).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="idf52b64a5a27549dbb060ad72c4696aa0"><enum>7.</enum><header>Support for local implementation</header>
<subsection id="ide625892600c2493c858d734d64fb597b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header>
<paragraph id="idacc9425d5efc45ecbef07df651539257"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, is authorized to award grants to eligible entities to support such eligible entities in fully implementing title IX and reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id31F3146B7F734C01A45B64B9E98756BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="id4F4B304AEBE04462B01319F553FB642E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State educational agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id72FE3F22D41A4738832165EF2DC1A2D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a local educational agency;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id774089FC393846C7A5985A2E64D5C143"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an institution of higher education; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id0E40936E249C460E894A15A90C94B15B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a partnership consisting of—</text>
<clause id="id51DF38856DEA442CA71242377BBD2B4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an entity described in subparagraphs (A) through (C); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3BA29027E8D94EADB7F2E0916CE12F0F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a national organization with relevant expertise, or another entity that the Secretary determines has relevant expertise.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="id6537d34fb2a54a659fcb408f2546d06c"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use such funds to carry out programs and activities designed to fully implement title IX and prevent and reduce sex discrimination, including programs and activities that—</text> <paragraph id="idCF239535A8D64FD0AD9ADDD358076C90"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increase awareness of and counteract sex stereotypes, biases, and discrimination;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="iddd96f744f2b54788a5a0f1d632884a1c"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include trainings for students, teachers, principals, other school leaders, faculty, other personnel, and community stakeholders, including title IX allies, to learn about and use best practices for reducing and preventing sex discrimination in all areas of education;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idf602ce3e427f432d890bfc94a21c10a1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>increase access to school, campus, and community resources, facilities, and course offerings;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id06045e595e4c4262af51703305bf21af"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support title IX coordinators and title IX allies in performing outreach, advocacy, and education about title IX and reducing and preventing sex discrimination;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id828EF61877C9448EBFE5B7E8B973CDE9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>are aimed at identifying patterns or systemic problems in compliance with title IX;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id093126E962424AF285D72CB030190916"><enum>(6)</enum><text>strengthen prevention education and awareness programs regarding sexual and sex-based harassment and violence;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idA8D6949427A045A29882C5CA8B48EC84"><enum>(7)</enum><text>develop, conduct and analyze evidence-based campus climate and victimization surveys;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idC04AA89372964BAFB622E19A28C2A81C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>include institutional assessment activities to identify areas and causes of gender inequities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idE34030BD62444294AEF424824C67D35E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>make efforts to improve progress on gender equity indicators as described in subsection (c)(2)(A); </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id30f020b6edfb41bf85c27e067bf1c8fd"><enum>(10)</enum><text>make efforts to improve accuracy in measurement, data collection, and reporting of gender equity indicators as described in subsection (c)(2)(A); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id2bbbeb39c4914e0d9eb0ca25f09dbdb5" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>make efforts to strengthen the national gender equity infrastructure (which may include institutions of higher education, State educational agencies, local educational agencies, and individual schools), such as by hiring one or more dedicated employees to serve as title IX coordinators. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="id86d1fa49db7a43ada819ce7b523e08f5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header>
<paragraph id="idafaecd7516eb42009fbb1c9160cf03c0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id1390732304bc4f9f9e041a24e30f6214"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of application</header><text>Each application submitted by an eligible entity under this section shall include the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="idd25eda1450e8436fa91d04539bf876ec"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of locally defined and documented gender equity needs and priorities, which may include any of the following indicators:</text> <clause id="id132e69b2ceb84900b653f75f9e40cded"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Academic indicators, including performance on State assessments, and enrollment, admission, attrition, time to completion, and graduation rates.</text></clause>
<clause id="id7adfd940089e42e5820defd4b0db6f62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Civil rights data, including statistics on bullying, harassment, violence, discipline, and expulsion.</text></clause> <clause id="id3d6abe39fa80430b81c038f9b75eeabc"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Campus climate and victimization data.</text></clause>
<clause id="idd98035292c064483a1bffae23bf87c08"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Employment data.</text></clause> <clause id="idf4037890912d4a2ab1431cd36077bc83"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Athletics equity data. </text></clause>
<clause id="idd14379f49cd34664a9c7c76220013d17"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Attendance and absenteeism data.</text></clause> <clause id="idca5a98bb62b44edbb8575a3002bcb9d7"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Evidence of burden on title IX coordinators, including coordinator to student ratio and competing responsibilities.</text></clause>
<clause id="id52c050c609b647768e317befdbd78209"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Other documentation of need that the Secretary determines is relevant.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idbdcdf9d6fdce4b27b24863c59763e10b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the evidence that will serve as the basis for the activities that the eligible entity proposes to carry out using grant funds under this section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id5307EC845A0D407E84CFDC439B860FAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the activities that the eligible entity proposes to carry out using grant funds under this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idfebfc683edb54d619212a9d06b76fc68"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of how the proposed activities will be adapted, as necessary, to meet the needs of students who face discrimination based on actual or perceived multiple characteristics, including—</text>
<clause id="id0949AD51AC7B4953A19A02E08E50A6CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>race;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0656944448bc4058ba4c04804652750d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></clause>
<clause id="id31126EAD38A24F7C82C58C3D70561B16"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></clause> <clause id="idB0B03828D7644CCBB5AB0A5C3ABFD17B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>national origin;</text></clause>
<clause id="id6AF71959530C4CB4BC96408C2C26C5BF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>disability;</text></clause> <clause id="id82C9B3997D37420DBABEDD39169F93BA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>religion;</text></clause>
<clause id="id44B670F09BC94D84ACDA9BA889ED5AE1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>age; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0CC5F5D23F9045D6912CD86A8787D54D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>sex.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id635281f708584933b75c2afe68904b2e"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of how the proposed activities will help the eligible entity fully implement title IX.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="ida9d843a041314512bdec4ceff7657888"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A description of a plan for how the proposed activities under this section will continue with local support following completion of the grant period and termination of Federal funding.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id11c034b82e6e4084ad72b44f884edece"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A description of how the proposed activities are a significant component of a comprehensive plan for gender equity in education and full implementation of title IX.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="id5972572d9d664179b9d7982b94dcfcef"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as prohibiting persons of any sex from participating in any of the programs or activities funded under this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="id20957a5c2b854703a90506144b88be69"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Award basis</header>
<paragraph id="id7CFEE1E91C9B447186953B605A6EFF3E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Merit review</header><text>Grants shall be awarded under this section on a competitive basis.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id0441D414A3A44428B040C5BF8F661B5D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priorities</header> <subparagraph id="id1ED8D33C17984156800A8BE26E8CB965"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish criteria for determining which eligible entities shall have priority in receiving a grant under this section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id483ff0a746394270bda85f3a0eb12771"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Level of priority</header><text>The criteria described in subparagraph (A) may include a consideration of the extent to which the application demonstrates that the eligible entity—</text> <clause id="idd3d41482055942e0b43ca01bb3c5c457"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has demonstrated a high need for gender equity assistance based on indicators described in subsection (c)(2)(A) and a high commitment to addressing these issues;</text></clause>
<clause id="id3febb66ba72447708a2620d2a0b07ec8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will address the needs of students who face discrimination based on multiple actual or perceived characteristics, including—</text> <subclause id="id1447385DCA6B48B0A7D5BE37AC9C5516"><enum>(I)</enum><text>race;</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id018db9efb6c049e59bd6ea716e0e254e"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></subclause> <subclause id="id8F4F9FA68DDC4732AE2011A198880193"><enum>(III)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="id81858A4B137D494C8F115538FB993E25"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>national origin;</text></subclause> <subclause id="idC972720F1B1746F08A5BF7E654E9FAD4"><enum>(V)</enum><text>disability;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="id5CFB091CC802470288C8B6BF671DE538"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>religion;</text></subclause> <subclause id="id96890141A69E433B946177E65BE532A8"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>age; or</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idD0EE74EFF9F34071BCB7995ACB035B01"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>sex;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="idedd0df425c884fe0b3f73359d36c187c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>will address relevant issues of national significance through solutions that can be replicated;</text></clause>
<clause id="id6885e854093b4019bd930c395d176076"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>will implement an institutional change strategy with a long-term impact that will continue to be a central activity of the eligible entity upon termination of the grant; </text></clause> <clause id="id84e5d23544944de1af58639cec3d4860"><enum>(v)</enum><text>will serve a high percentage of low-income students;</text></clause>
<clause id="id5de0af650bc84258a6a41d89d5a277c2"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>will serve a high percentage of racially diverse students; </text></clause> <clause id="id200dd2600cae48c59f2fd10b7baa4645"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>will promote outreach to include others in their gender equity training and related activities during the grant period and after the grant ends; and</text></clause>
<clause id="id1e55fc12b02c419fbb51602e67605aad"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>will impact as many educational entities as possible to advance title IX implementation during and after the grant period. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id55ff0801908f48948f2db42c0bec2508"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>To the extent practicable, the Secretary shall ensure that grants awarded under this section, for each fiscal year, address—</text>
<clause id="idf0786fc032b443449d4a1277df83face"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all levels of education, including—</text> <subclause id="id282eaac40ad34d89a2c11f9ed60ba791"><enum>(I)</enum><text>elementary and secondary education;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="id485e4864069f453bae6a9a6769950786"><enum>(II)</enum><text>undergraduate and graduate education;</text></subclause> <subclause id="id0f43c6037d9d483c87edbe0cc1733250"><enum>(III)</enum><text>postdoctoral education and research;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="id4d259ec928ce488ea6cc766d0fbce32f"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>career and technical education; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="id1b38360889234f8ab9d8447d349dc5cc"><enum>(V)</enum><text>adult education;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="id0aad9e5acb7b4afea46dae4e5e00c0c9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>all regions of the United States; and</text></clause> <clause id="id7a1537818c6843eea1f8120dfe9e37f5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>urban, rural, and suburban educational entities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="id32e817302b344f5ab5c296780a044f13"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation and dissemination</header>
<paragraph id="id7e558f6f0cb04748b9b2a97da3468220"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluation</header>
<subparagraph id="id49ACF7EE24EC4AE1BD4CE41ED1330E76"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall conduct an evaluation regarding the extent to which the eligible entity made progress on the indicators under subsection (c)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id67A893BEA2F94B209F3CB234E52AE58A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>An eligible entity may work in partnership with the Institute of Education Sciences to conduct such evaluation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id0a594585b82445a3873d1dfabd5ff15d"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Use by secretary</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a grant award under this section, an eligible entity shall submit a report to the Secretary summarizing the results of such evaluation. The Secretary shall use those reports to build the research base on promising models for preventing and reducing sex discrimination across all areas and levels of education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="id30b1fe5b1d7d44cebda0113dbf2bdf9a"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate with the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences and other relevant Federal offices and agencies to—</text>
<subparagraph id="idB2D3E47C5744427A8D2C7CF258C8A5A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that the results of the activities carried out under this section are made readily available on the Office for Gender Equity resource center website; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idF401A2B108AA4F5E861349556A0FDC0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>widely disseminate the results described in subparagraph (A) to relevant Federal offices and agencies, educational entities, and the general public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="ida782d5c8630848c78187fac6c59682e1"><enum>8.</enum><header>Research and development</header>
<subsection id="id179ee0a28cdf4bf7a46ed83688eeb6a2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate with the Special Assistant for Gender Equity, the Assistant Secretary of the Office for Civil Rights of the Department, the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences, other relevant Federal offices and agencies, and relevant non-Federal entities to investigate, identify, and disseminate best practices to fully implement title IX and reduce and prevent sex discrimination in all areas of education, including—</text> <paragraph id="id43724b1ee96c4450be8fcfc8165febcc"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the reduction and prevention of sex stereotyping, bias, and discrimination in curricula, textbooks, software, and other educational materials;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id74207d7d54fe45339de0a736c0da88cd"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the development of policies and programs to—</text> <subparagraph id="idefce723341e94c8eb2b085aa50db9439"><enum>(A)</enum><text>address and prevent sexual and sex-based harassment and violence;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id8dff3b9d333c4e45bada11e949c87fe0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that schools and campuses are free from threats to the safety of students, teachers, faculty, and personnel; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id452be67d34b24c469be29f6d2cc9e0d1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensure athletic programs are equitable;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idb9c504d8225e4677855992f9998b0796"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the development and evaluation of—</text> <subparagraph id="id68F49A28316040F2A24A25B4716ED047"><enum>(A)</enum><text>counseling and career guidance training; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id3534305848C440A999803CE663FD4593"><enum>(B)</enum><text>programs to reduce and prevent sex stereotyping, bias, and discrimination;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="idbc23550fdff34ace9782c65aa6ebc0f3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>best practices for mitigating implicit bias in teaching, discipline, and all areas of education;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id738c51491c90450bb8495a95ffde246c"><enum>(5)</enum><text>best practices for addressing the needs of students who face discrimination based on multiple actual or perceived characteristics, including—</text> <subparagraph id="id34BB88D7E6A54622B7B0FB4E842B768B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>race;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbf9d0b9d776e4297a42ffa89149c9bc7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id6EDF8C15C1BC448CA3837FD01C859BA2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id7DA2B4C928E740D9BD8987D9CBFE2B1B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>national origin;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id8F6273EE30BA48669731912B15097835"><enum>(E)</enum><text>disability;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idA4F1472A111E4D8F9EF36152A56A4BC5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>religion;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id597912CDC5F3424C82F6AA2C7B27523D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>age; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idA7BC6BD9402F4239BE88EE0CE4FF5897"><enum>(H)</enum><text>sex; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="id385eab63ff8f4d09a0ffc4f1da10ed5f"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other activities that the Secretary determines are consistent with the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="id257c39dbb6af47ff862d965074fce7ab"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The best practices described under subsection (a) shall be published on the Office for Gender Equity resource center website, as described in section 5(b)(5), and the What Works Clearinghouse website of the Institute of Education Sciences.</text></subsection></section> <section id="idaf1c0c8951674a50937ddaf889a8a253"><enum>9.</enum><header>Report; dissemination</header> <subsection id="id0522f39d48564a62bc37c3ee55d72a2c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary shall publish a report on the steps the Department of Education has taken to—</text>
<paragraph id="id3992ba1a08bc4aec8f8359e155f3745f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support educational entities in fully implementing title IX and reducing and preventing sex discrimination;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="idf61cfd77205c4ad6987e6789a20d8ead"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide coordination, training, and resources for title IX coordinators and title IX allies to fully carry out their roles and responsibilities; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id690a4e41c55249b7bb2c4172a786dcb0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promote equity in education for students who face discrimination based on multiple actual or perceived characteristics, including—</text> <subparagraph id="idE0AF6F6D8B2A401387801BE2909CD686"><enum>(A)</enum><text>race;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide331848347cc40b0a4839990e3a76703"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">color;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id1B8BBC165C5A456EAF88CDCC76858C0B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id256665D28AE54EB791A1E9DDE5AE2A3C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>national origin;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id01500F81ED9E4DCE9EA3D10AE50DE956"><enum>(E)</enum><text>disability;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idE80E293B2C6A4E31A37AE3D78EB72E43"><enum>(F)</enum><text>religion;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id1E850A2B160D410AAE24C6B032ADED3D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>age; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0452827A481F4881B5D9F9447CEDB5B1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>sex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="id4fb1cf82488d47cdbef3e2b4251e097e"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate with the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences and the heads of relevant Federal agencies to ensure that the results of trainings, activities, evaluations, and research developments under this Act are made readily available on the Office for Gender Equity resource center website and disseminated widely to other relevant Federal agencies and offices, educational entities, and the general public.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="id227F8CB765A742BEAA993624AEF43024"><enum>10.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed—</text> <paragraph id="id189640E5479944D596891E235EC06ACA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as modifying any provision of title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="idA3E35CF50938458FA4630D39C9951183"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as affecting the enforcement of such title by the Department of Education, the Department of Justice, or any other Federal agency.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="id60b11f02fab54893a9ced484830aec3f"><enum>11.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> <subsection id="id3e580fbaa9524efcba13d69ae9dfc763"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $160,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="id095d1211b091444d81f924395d851ca3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use</header><text>From amounts made available to carry out this Act for each fiscal year, the Secretary shall use not less than $140,000,000 of such amounts to award grants under section 7.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

