<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MCC23077-FNS-0R-K36"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S425 IS: Secure and Protect Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 425</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S293">Mr. Graham</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 to protect alien minors and to amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to end abuse of the asylum system and establish refugee application and processing centers outside the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" changed="not-changed" id="idde3c6c9b-ba7f-480a-8e3e-597c8214046a"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Secure and Protect Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section changed="not-changed" id="id6c08b578-edd3-4d51-957b-ab515c8d10a3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protection of minors</header><subsection id="idda50c1fb-7b57-4cff-996f-339826e71731" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Promoting family unity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 235 of the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1232">8 U.S.C. 1232</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="ide493bcd2-246c-41b2-9adb-b1e0965a0cdd"><subsection id="idd1cb90d0-520e-442a-abaa-2212e85f278a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Promoting family unity</header><paragraph id="id32d0c7ff-0504-43bb-afa5-34af9cdc157b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Detention of alien minors</header><subparagraph id="idfca0d250-fb63-4751-8cbd-948644fe3061" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, the Secretary of Homeland Security may detain any alien minor (other than an unaccompanied alien child) who is inadmissible to the United States under section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>) or removable from the United States under section 237(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)</external-xref>) pending the completion of removal proceedings, regardless of whether the alien minor was previously an unaccompanied alien child.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4927670d-3899-417c-847e-63845b0fb3c5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority removal cases</header><text>The Attorney General shall—</text><clause id="idc09f4156-e295-46a9-aeab-67a8ce2eab77" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prioritize the removal proceedings of an alien minor, or a family unit that includes an alien minor, detained under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="id03e92ffc-fa6a-4c25-9fda-e463bb7363f5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>set a case completion goal of not more than 100 days for such proceedings.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id24427800-a5f8-4573-a7a5-f3b90e36fd79" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Detention and release decisions</header><text>The decision to detain or release an alien minor described in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="id208e2091-f103-4263-8492-18ba22481bf9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be governed solely by sections 212(d)(5), 217, 235, 236, and 241 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)(5)</external-xref>, 1187, 1225, 1226, and 1231) and implementing regulations or policies; and</text></clause><clause id="id84d86e49-4c29-4019-95a9-cb3d2856cf3a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be governed by standards, requirements, restrictions, or procedures contained in a judicial decree or settlement relating to the authority to detain or release alien minors.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id70ebbdd5-a079-4c63-a5fc-e6d70a34b123" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions of detention</header><subparagraph id="idfee0fc24-a869-4176-8684-b74dbf6b7c17" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall determine, in the sole discretion of the Secretary, the conditions of detention applicable to an alien minor described in paragraph (1)(A) regardless of whether the alien minor was previously an unaccompanied alien child.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id728ce9aa-1fe2-4e84-8c2d-d87abc8ba964" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No judicial review</header><text>A determination under subparagraph (A) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida2e7fad8-e977-475c-8e1c-91f88809f20e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section—</text><subparagraph id="idc0363411-3928-4759-9249-218ffe126df0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>affects the eligibility for bond or parole of an alien; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id80092ce7-bf8a-48fe-9278-f54ab1934754" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>limits the authority of a court to hear a claim arising under the Constitution of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf873c2cf-4fec-4a94-979d-cdd3cac806f7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Preemption of State licensing requirements</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, a State may not require an immigration detention facility used to detain families consisting of one or more children who have not attained 18 years of age and the parents or legal guardians of such children, that is located in the State, to be licensed by the State or any political subdivision thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4A6E342288944C73A254F7A559F549CA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Conditions of custody</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall ensure that each—</text><subparagraph id="id87de2c57ee424c77a58d3065dea7e8df" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>family residential facility is secure and safe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4C996F5917A74D1DAA8200EB718E5851" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>alien child and accompanying parent at a family residential facility has—</text><clause id="idE2255F8E8872443F9A485D9D1ABBF804" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>suitable living accommodations;</text></clause><clause id="idFB7A9442A6F84C4BAE0181AD9E769E26" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access to drinking water and food;</text></clause><clause id="id51B2286C29C34DA18451B3C5275DE4A5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>timely access to medical assistance, including mental health assistance; and</text></clause><clause id="id561CA971D1C94DD98E9B0CB904213183" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>access to any other service necessary for the adequate care of a minor child.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide8010d47-474a-4f14-856d-0421f451c1ff" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0b57a96e-0681-4fb0-b8c1-c3cad73f97e7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Applicability of consent decrees, settlements, and judicial determinations</header><paragraph id="idc77803a61be14a9eb31ad259280ed0f1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Flores settlement agreement inapplicable</header><text>Any conduct or activity that was, before the date of the enactment of this subsection, subject to any restriction or obligation imposed by the stipulated settlement agreement filed on January 17, 1997, in the United States District Court for the Central District of California in Flores v. Reno, CV 85–4544–RJK, (commonly known as the <quote>Flores settlement agreement</quote>), or imposed by any amendment of that agreement or judicial determination based on that agreement—</text><subparagraph id="id2D51CFF0B2B84E9A8F66B25B6FFB8346" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be subject to the restrictions and obligations under subsection (j) or imposed under any other provision of this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCA04A4A220CC4A6CAD0EC1A0283B0497" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be subject to the restrictions and the obligations imposed by such settlement agreement or judicial determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id1f1f7f6ccf4241afa993b93e97c79dc3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other settlement agreements or consent decrees</header><text>In any civil action with respect to the conditions of detention of alien children, the court shall not enter or approve a settlement agreement or consent decree unless it complies with the limitations set forth in subsection (j).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id5a34ce85-3e0d-4836-9a87-e1ff6afd9cb9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Safe and prompt return of unaccompanied alien children</header><text>Section 235(a) of the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1232">8 U.S.C. 1232(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id9e677892-b844-42cb-8db8-4668d0f92a88" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="id27be1e8d-8f22-457e-948f-ce5f26940f68" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending the paragraph heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Rules for repatriating unaccompanied alien children</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8c5055e6-8bf9-4825-a55d-b02b956d0230" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>who is a national or habitual resident of a country that is contiguous with the United States shall be treated in accordance with subparagraph (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>shall be treated in accordance with this paragraph or subsection (b), as applicable</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9891d4f8-a40f-48b9-81f6-f48027ff3f8c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide84c0308-8602-4755-a996-4e89585dbfa4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i) and (ii) as subclauses (I) and (II), and moving the subclauses two ems to the right;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id17993c35-2379-4a70-aba2-7f9ff6e2981e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (I), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>An immigration officer</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="id30349007-af42-4255-a541-93377d1675b5"><clause id="idc8bf12c8-f504-457a-afc6-2c24022417c6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An immigration officer</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3da88783-0c33-46a4-a857-5d4409ad88b9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idb998b8d2-936f-4f0c-ab08-6fd82acd6ebe"><clause id="id08991c4b-7c14-481f-80d0-5615e5027e79" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Children unable to make decisions with respect to withdrawal of applications for admission</header><text>If at the time of initial apprehension, an immigration officer determines, in the sole and unreviewable discretion of the immigration officer, that an unaccompanied alien child is not able to make an independent decision with respect to the withdrawal of his or her application for admission to the United States, the immigration officer shall refer the unaccompanied alien child for removal proceedings under section 240 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>).</text></clause><clause id="id0dbec76d-c36b-4218-978f-a2eea92d8410" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Children able to make decisions with respect to withdrawal of applications for admission</header><subclause id="idd6c8f280-c967-4fe2-8e9b-18ed0b927743" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as described in subclause (III)(aa), notwithstanding any other provision of law that requires removal proceedings under section 240 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>), including subparagraph (D) and section 235 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225</external-xref>), in the case of an unaccompanied alien child who is able to make an independent decision with respect to the withdrawal of his or her application for admission to the United States, as determined by an immigration officer at the time of initial apprehension, and does not wish to withdraw such application, the immigration officer shall—</text><item id="idd313d817-2a6e-4c3f-9ffd-2b17aefbcf54" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>make a record of any finding of inadmissibility or deportability, which shall be the basis of a repatriation order, which shall be carried out and the child shall be returned to his or her country of nationality or last habitual residence, unless the child is referred—</text><subitem id="id9C8A53BEE98D465F9665A226E84BC6A5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>for removal proceedings pursuant to subclause (III)(aa); or</text></subitem><subitem id="id1A71BF52B7714D2DA9FA46060D404442" changed="not-changed"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>to an immigration judge for a determination pursuant to subclause (III)(bb); and</text></subitem></item><item id="id5e64cccf-21e6-403c-a522-0cce9c8eabb5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>refer the unaccompanied alien child for an interview under subclause (II) to determine whether it is more likely than not that the unaccompanied alien child—</text><subitem id="idcd8b2f7a-34e7-4adc-b9df-54d9d7d420d2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>will be subjected to trafficking on return to his or her country of nationality or last habitual residence; and</text></subitem><subitem id="id1951e1da-1fdd-4006-abd6-8327554573cc" changed="not-changed"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>would be granted asylum under section 208 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158</external-xref>), withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(b)(3)</external-xref>), or protection under the regulations issued pursuant to the legislation implementing the Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, done at New York, December 10, 1984 (referred to in this clause as the <quote>Convention Against Torture</quote>).</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="id7f568da6-0ee5-403d-901a-3e04d1a786bd" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Interview</header><item id="idd6fa5df5-d663-416d-94dd-7ae1193df9bb" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An interview under subclause (I)(bb) shall be conducted by an immigration officer with specialized training relating to—</text><subitem id="id42f15260-893b-49ab-b9dd-57f112c18f6e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>applicable law;</text></subitem><subitem id="id759da5ab-c017-44be-9ed9-bd045b773b9d" changed="not-changed"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>interviewing children; and</text></subitem><subitem id="id5c14ccd5-c53b-4630-a011-5440317b2e6b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>child trafficking.</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="idb6aba9ba-0077-41c7-af85-3af6e3c37714" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Determinations based on interview</header><item id="id6c9c7f1c-bcea-464b-af2b-f4e94d8787cf" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Removal proceedings</header><text>An unaccompanied alien child described in subclause (I) shall be referred for removal proceedings under section 240 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>) if, based on an interview under item (bb) of that subclause, the immigration officer makes a determination that it is more likely than not that the unaccompanied alien child will be trafficked on return to his or her country of nationality or last habitual residence.</text></item><item id="idfb18c866-f5d1-4f24-ae35-4427de423d8a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Asylum only determinations</header><subitem id="iddfded313-2708-43c7-b1c2-757f5bc2fc8e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(AA)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, based on an interview under subclause (I)(bb), the immigration officer makes a determination that it is more likely than not that the claim of an unaccompanied alien child for asylum under section 208 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158</external-xref>), withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(b)(3)</external-xref>), or protection under the Convention Against Torture will be granted, the unaccompanied alien child shall be referred to an immigration judge solely for a determination with respect to whether the unaccompanied alien child is eligible for asylum under section 208 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158</external-xref>), withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(b)(3)</external-xref>), or protection under the regulations issued pursuant to the legislation implementing the Convention Against Torture and, if otherwise eligible for asylum, whether asylum shall be granted in the exercise of discretion.</text></subitem><subitem id="id3ca6d351-0a5b-4da7-95ce-cc85b5180a28" changed="not-changed"><enum>(BB)</enum><header>Repatriation</header><text>An unaccompanied alien child referred to an immigration judge under subitem (AA) shall be returned to his or her country of nationality or last habitual residence if the immigration judge finds that the unaccompanied alien child is not entitled to asylum, withholding of removal, or protection under the regulations issued pursuant to the legislation implementing the Convention Against Torture.</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="id69e6c729-bfee-43fa-8b67-885715c8d130" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Discretion of immigration officer; no judicial review</header><text>A decision of an immigration officer under this clause, and the issuance of a repatriation order, shall be in the sole, unreviewable discretion of the immigration officer.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id46EDE26EA50C4638ACC74B895827EC41" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Detention during proceedings</header><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id88fb4bbc-4097-4918-95af-16038e3bb604" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subclauses (II) and (III), notwithstanding any other provision of law, settlement agreement, or consent decree, an unaccompanied alien child shall not be released from the custody of the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Director of the Office of Refugee Resettlement during the pendency of the immigration or removal proceedings of the unaccompanied alien child.</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idC7CB31ABD16E4361BD528B268D4E97C6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Release to sponsor</header><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1920F09688DA4A2D8028841000C7D81E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in item (bb), the Director of the Office of Refugee Resettlement may, in the sole, unreviewable discretion of the Director, release an unaccompanied alien child to a sponsor who is a verified parent or legal guardian or, in the case of an unaccompanied alien child who does not have a verified parent or legal guardian in the United States, a close relative, a distant relative, or an unrelated adult.</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idD1E26845298E4B12BAE206D4E516C57A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Director of the Office of Refugee Resettlement shall not under any circumstance release an unaccompanied alien child to a sponsor or a member of the sponsor's household who has committed an offense described in section 236(c)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226(c)(1)</external-xref>), is detained while in removal proceedings under section 240 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>), has assisted or facilitated the smuggling or trafficking of a child, or would otherwise pose a threat to the well-being of the unaccompanied alien child.</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id251671915C55423482AD8FFC73EFE3CE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Provision of information to Secretary of Homeland Security</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide to the Secretary of Homeland Security information relating to the sponsor, potential sponsor, and each member of the household of the sponsor or potential sponsor, of each unaccompanied alien child.</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id05DFE6D91E474D8A863EA45775FC8F82" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Programs for unaccompanied alien children without sponsors</header><text>In the case of an unaccompanied alien child who cannot be placed with a sponsor under item (aa), the Director of the Office of Refugee Resettlement may release the child to a program for unaccompanied alien minors, such as a program under section 412(d) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1522">8 U.S.C. 1522(d)</external-xref>).</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9553c71b-dd0d-4f14-8bc0-b981ae76c308" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><clause id="ide0e5f8d2-0f21-43b2-8b99-d1b989934c77" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by amending the subparagraph heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Agreements with foreign countries.—</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="idce19738b-dcf3-4806-afc3-3f0983373400" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>countries contiguous to the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>Canada, El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, Mexico, and any other foreign country the Secretary considers appropriate</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2bc7c03c-be6a-4586-8d97-51646f001282" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id01977853-9197-4fa1-a544-ae34e056e89e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) and (5) as paragraphs (3) and (4), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc125d229-3e28-4ac1-b8b0-f942cfe4030a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(D), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>from a contiguous country</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd8e941d6-2c25-4390-9ef0-912a46dfbcb3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Protecting integrity of special immigrant juvenile visa program</header><text>Section 101(a)(27)(J) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(27)(J)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id24bcc05e-97cb-465d-98c5-9b0fd2eb831f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>, and whose</quote> and all that follows through <quote>State law</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5ec98d36-ea5c-46c3-afb5-6d298b95b77e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (iii)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc45e2728-88d6-47f9-9964-6f828f7af8d6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subclause (I), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id84787a63-e912-4bfc-9089-4ac3381baaf6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="id09a75be0-35ab-4d6e-ba02-6ea837616cc4"><subclause id="ide58d871d-b757-4d48-99ce-679e16c4bd63" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an alien may not be granted special immigrant juvenile status under this subparagraph if the juvenile court determines that the alien may be returned to the legal custody of any parent of the alien; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idb9233598-9b0b-47b3-b3b0-95dae666e602" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id0b1d0fcc-23c6-41f5-85c8-a8dd09564e0d" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in assessing whether an alien is entitled to special immigrant juvenile classification under this subparagraph, the Secretary of Homeland Security may, in the discretion of the Secretary, determine whether—</text><subitem changed="not-changed" id="id29C9425B981B4820B4D0EC8124E486C7" indent="up1"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>an order of dependency or custody issued for purposes of clause (i) was issued during juvenile court abuse and neglect proceedings for the purpose of providing permanency to an alien the parents of whom have been found to be unfit; and</text></subitem><subitem changed="not-changed" id="id14BA6D978ED04F33A7D57E67A8379547" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>such order was issued by a court of appropriate jurisdiction; and</text></subitem></item><item changed="not-changed" id="id8eb5d71c-7547-4c83-8fc2-efe699435a88" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of law, no court shall have jurisdiction to review a determination made by the Secretary of Homeland Security under this subclause;</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0371C1900B654E34B09F302050E352E6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Parole reform</header><paragraph id="id5B707A85C25346E4A3296747AC5B945E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 212(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" changed="not-changed" id="HC15A399966FF4A358E43599F1F1D1A71"><paragraph id="H0DFE4948816047A98935DF710C17012D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Humanitarian and significant public benefit parole</header><subparagraph id="H35229BC65738477B87CB26896C07572B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the provisions of this paragraph and section 214(f)(2), the Secretary of Homeland Security, in the sole discretion of the Secretary of Homeland Security, may, on an individual case-by-case basis and not according to eligibility criteria describing an entire class of potential parole recipients, parole an alien into the United States temporarily, under such conditions as the Secretary of Homeland Security may prescribe, only—</text><clause id="H03534AC61DAC45EBBF27ED461579E81B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for an urgent humanitarian reason (as described under subparagraph (B)); or</text></clause><clause id="H0E168493C260449493A8C06B2039EC30" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for a reason deemed strictly for the significant public benefit (as described under subparagraph (C)).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44D33C5BB3084DC4B1FCD78BD5EC6A67" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Humanitarian parole</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may parole an alien based on an urgent humanitarian reason described in this subparagraph only if—</text><clause id="HA67D9E8E2BEA461EA62C238E5B7CDC86" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the alien has a medical emergency and the alien cannot obtain necessary treatment in the foreign state in which the alien is residing or the medical emergency is life-threatening and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause><clause id="id8FBF3A1369D144FF90054F5E82DBE95D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien is the legal guardian or otherwise has legal authority to make medical decisions on behalf of an alien described in clause (i);</text></clause><clause id="H40F333BB757E48609FFA491B031D9CF4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alien is needed in the United States in order to donate an organ or other tissue for transplant into an immediate family member and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause><clause id="H659F8EFFB1C0461E92747CE77B0A00F8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the alien has an immediate family member in the United States whose death is imminent and the alien could not arrive in the United States in time to see such family member alive if the alien were to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF2870FCEAEDE486CAB0DC4DDCF44100B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the alien is a lawful applicant for adjustment of status under section 245; or</text></clause><clause id="H0F8475E4CE3240359F9CF1E62C9C9F7F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien was lawfully granted status under section 208 or lawfully admitted under section 207.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A962775414B42AABB8C571A11159B31" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Significant public benefit parole</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may parole an alien based on a reason deemed strictly for the significant public benefit described in this subparagraph only if—</text><clause id="idab12376ce4f34cc488e5a1a974d7ce04" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the presence of the alien is necessary in a matter such as a criminal investigation or prosecution, espionage activity, or other similar law enforcement or intelligence-related activity;</text></clause><clause id="id99e4fb048a1b48919d3308a2f2e63b0c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the presence of the alien is necessary in a civil matter concerning the termination of parental rights;</text></clause><clause id="ide2f5b628d3be4761859d8e7038e7bc83" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alien has previously assisted the United States Government in a matter described in clause (i) and the life of the alien would be threatened if the alien were not permitted to enter the United States;</text></clause><clause id="id3e5122fb084240f89173e9cd2d9c1a5d" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of an alien detained under section 235, it is necessary to release from detention and grant parole to the alien due to a safety concern or for the preservation of life and property, including in the case of—</text><subclause id="id3699d25f77ea4cb691851d49e7a0e6dc" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>lack of adequate bed space in a detention facility; or</text></subclause><subclause id="id96e9413bd6fc43c18522de5f5f15f9e3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an alien who has a serious medical condition such that continued detention would be life-threatening or would risk serious bodily injury, disfigurement, or permanent disability; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idc8d823d9c2db4b1a9d577c0ef198e45e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in the case of an alien returned to a foreign territory contiguous to the United States pursuant to section 235(b)(2)(C), it is necessary to parole the alien into the United States for an immigration proceeding.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA2FF2D3C58A4B2F86E19198434FA55C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation on the use of parole authority</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not use the parole authority under this paragraph—</text><clause id="id4013B1D819CF4BD6AD74544A23BF2CB2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to circumvent immigration policy established by law;</text></clause><clause id="id9C082FE7E58442CFB9B17D8EF7734443" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to admit classes of aliens who do not qualify for admission under established legal immigration categories; or</text></clause><clause id="id524E74846F27454CA037DBF0DB7ED302" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to supplement established immigration categories without an Act of Congress.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE27824043F1A4A1D8D8C4B4198A9BC24" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Parole not an admission</header><text>Parole of an alien under this paragraph shall not be considered an admission of the alien into the United States. When the purposes of the parole of an alien have been served, or such parole is revoked, as determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security, the alien shall immediately return or be returned to the custody from which the alien was paroled and the alien shall be considered for admission to the United States on the same basis as other similarly situated applicants for admission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79E4552CBB85435EB133842A41A642C0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit a report to the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives describing the number and categories of aliens paroled into the United States under this paragraph. Each such report shall contain information and data concerning the number and categories of aliens paroled, the duration of parole, and the current status of aliens paroled during the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC96491F4C7049789A3B37C1DCEC2ACF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by paragraph (1) shall take effect on the first day of the first month beginning more than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idfe8b69f0-f8cd-4a5e-af62-0fd186d165df"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ending abuse of asylum system</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id97457227CB7F4D75B5D35CB5491EA202" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Standards To deter fraud and advance meritorious asylum claims</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 235(b)(1)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id2D3D87E7704B4C0CBC3D3BEB069B4116" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending clause (v) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="id6E51605C4A524834AA5804BBF7EDFCE9"><clause id="id088911246E87433EBBD87344389724ED" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Credible fear of persecution</header><subclause id="idCE2A066DA46D462C825962224C49574C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>credible fear of persecution</term> means that it is more likely than not that the alien would be able to establish eligibility for asylum under section 208—</text><item id="idF1CA9A1D1D284A4095541FB662B8F5A2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>taking into account such facts as are known to the officer; and</text></item><item id="idEFDA61DC445E42109C6AE4D97639FBA5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only if the officer has determined, under subsection (b)(1)(B)(iii) of such section, that it is more likely than not that the statements made by the alien or on behalf of the alien are true.</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idBE428A76C5904A4284D9AC13FCC9E9AF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Bars to asylum</header><text>An alien shall not be determined to have a credible fear of persecution if the alien is prohibited from applying for or receiving asylum, including an alien subject to a limitation or condition under subsection (a)(2) or (b)(2) (including a regulation promulgated under such subsection) of section 208.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="id4A3614FA7EB74F5EB26CC43DABEB1C7E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="id922A25C7261A498EB9A7FB1F4C078896"><clause id="id131773FA3F7049C184AE4A4010DDD2BF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Eligibility for relief</header><subclause id="id0FD0A1897F344B60B9DE2D0437D0C494" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Credible fear review by immigration judge</header><text>An alien determined to have a credible fear of persecution shall be referred to an immigration judge for review of such determination, which shall be limited to a determination whether the alien—</text><item id="id0BBF97D3057D47DFA50545C7AF5C0749" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is eligible for asylum under section 208, withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3), or protection under the Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, done at New York, December 10, 1984 (referred to in this clause as the <quote>Convention Against Torture)</quote>; and</text></item><item id="idA7E1D22E928B41BFA35BE3458D0B45D2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>merits a grant of asylum in the exercise of discretion.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="id2BC6A237CEEA4D878BBF1117E87FD866" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Aliens with reasonable fear of persecution</header><item id="idC21E18016DAA4CBFB8BE777296D898AC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in item (bb), if an alien referred under subparagraph (A)(ii) is determined to have a reasonable fear of persecution or torture, the alien shall be eligible only for consideration of an application for withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3) or protection under the Convention Against Torture.</text></item><item id="id62FE933976154991ACFACAA5204C323B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An alien shall not be eligible for consideration of an application for relief under item (aa) if the failure of the alien to establish a credible fear of persecution precludes the alien from eligibility for such relief.</text></item><item commented="no" id="id9B2FFD32B1494198A8E3CD18337F3FF8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An alien whose application for relief is adjudicated under item (aa) shall not be eligible for any other form of relief or protection from removal.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="id1B8545B2C85F4421A587D6F7D7528BEC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Ineligibility for removal proceedings</header><text>An alien referred under subparagraph (A)(ii) shall not be eligible for a hearing under section 240.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id990FA9B14FDE43579627FB48E8AF48A2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications for asylum</header><text>Section 208 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id9BACAC8516E64BF4BD1127224CEA3FDB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="id36B3C8A7B8084ADD87CF557DABF2E6AF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idC83AC71CBA3C43BCA67851958092D424"><paragraph id="id31114907AC044CFD85E3D88FB1989FF6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Only an alien who has entered the United States through a designated port of entry may apply for asylum under this section or section 235(b), as applicable.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1C1BEAA1B40642A280B7369DC4AC8B30" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="id63B8627D8C94452AA7234EB90C8C5117" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>, pursuant to a bilateral or multilateral agreement,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="id120B24E0216D4585B62ACB165A6BB502" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>Subparagraphs (A) and (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>Subparagraph (A)</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id620A3CD8D7884DD9A79733E7AB2832A4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(3), by striking subparagraph (C).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7935231725E7489DA0BC8CDB6B87D8EC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority for certain aliens To apply for asylum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idA863E2751E0541309968DD7B359011E0"><subparagraph id="id6F8E857B5C144EF9B2148EEA362644D5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Ineligibility for asylum</header><clause id="id5B916A91D11B466C8319F3B803BB942A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including paragraph (1), except as provided in clause (ii), an alien is ineligible for asylum if the alien—</text><subclause id="idCE22575C7E1C47EBAFD9209FBC23018C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has been convicted of a felony;</text></subclause><subclause id="id819BE0E2823A472C96153D6566D677D0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is inadmissible under section 212(a) (except paragraphs (4), (5), and (7));</text></subclause><subclause id="id7391CE3AAD8E4D6BA0BC3A0C633C623A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has been previously removed from the United States; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idADE19CCCE43D49938249783D28389FC8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>is a national or habitual resident of—</text><item id="idACF149CC643F49378ABF5D5FE6694169" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a country in Central America that has a refugee application and processing center; or</text></item><item id="id6502605332F84306B945E706FD04BE61" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a country contiguous to such a country (other than Mexico).</text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id63386EB98BB1403EAB3C0C433CE8888D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Notwithstanding clause (i), paragraph (1) shall not apply to any alien who is present in the United States on the date of the enactment of this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section changed="not-changed" id="ide08bb4d3-8c01-48d5-babe-2891339a7eac"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of refugee application and processing centers</header><subsection id="id98d92fdc-6c7b-4a77-90f4-068d8c9c3da9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idc903eb54-c611-4843-917f-0d60e4c21742"><paragraph id="id6e18daac-aa02-4a89-9dd7-bf700ce6c8e6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(53)</enum><text>The term <term>refugee application and processing center</term>—</text><subparagraph id="id6697811a-1537-4bd2-93d7-5c55b1ba9fbd" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a facility designated under section 207(g) by the Secretary of State to accept and process applications for refugee admissions to the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id59ae540e-407b-4f51-8d33-5c2f46a447db" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include a United States embassy, consulate, or other diplomatic facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id1e806c71-805b-458c-8bd4-82385887ea94" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Section 207 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="id49dcfb4f-f67c-41d6-857c-fe74ccc4a755"><subsection id="id04fbca66-a926-45b2-a24a-93c1e5f8359b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Refugee application and processing centers</header><paragraph id="idc282cab3-ef01-43da-819e-221cf563571e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Not later than 240 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall designate refugee application and processing centers outside the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2ac8a254-2df2-4f40-9f38-f2dae939b194" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Locations</header><text>The Secretary of State shall establish—</text><subparagraph id="idf58b1c05-e7a7-48fb-b0d9-63e2ace241ac" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not fewer than 1 refugee application and processing center in Mexico; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4ac3c80e-6d5f-42e5-bdd6-a9b1556cf034" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not fewer than 3 refugee application and processing centers in Central America at locations selected by the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf2a1d51e-6983-4336-8148-653eef946e57" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties of Secretary of State</header><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall ensure that any alien who is a national or habitual resident of a country in which a refugee application and processing center is located, or a country contiguous to such a country, may apply for refugee status at a refugee application and processing center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0435152b-4009-4218-b296-c06d5aa26ff1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Adjudication by refugee officers</header><text>An application for refugee status submitted to a refugee application and processing center shall be adjudicated by a refugee officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9226de8a-be85-40a8-8c5d-17a0403d797b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary of State shall ensure that refugee application and processing centers accord priority to applications submitted—</text><subparagraph id="id02411960-76a5-4fa6-bc0b-7b90f71181c9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by aliens who have been referred by an authorized nongovernmental organization, as determined by the Secretary of State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb0182745-3b1e-4567-b74f-0abcac55f0e3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date on which such referral is made; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida6da68a9-f450-419a-9971-b9257d84e1cc" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in accordance with the requirements and procedures established by the Secretary of State under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id157bd2d9-13fd-403c-850b-4dc2b291206f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Application fees</header><subparagraph id="id3b7a8a7a-81aa-4f1f-9053-144bf0659ca1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall charge, collect, and account for fees prescribed by each such Secretary pursuant to subsections (m) and (n) of section 286 and section 9701 of title 31, United States Code, for the purpose of receiving, docketing, processing, and adjudicating an application under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb5ca6a3e-024d-4c64-a386-62fe88324c51" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Basis for fees</header><text>The fees prescribed under subparagraph (A) shall be based on a consideration of the amount necessary to deter frivolous applications and the cost for processing the application, including the implementation of program integrity and anti-fraud measures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id4517C390AEBB40739CC4CE93E14C2CE9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall cease to be effective beginning on the date that is three years and 240 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="ida1d9be49-4207-48fc-a510-55aeb359e0cf"><enum>5.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 553(b) of title 5, United States Code, not later than 210 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Attorney General shall, jointly or separately, publish in the Federal Register interim final rules to implement the amendments made by section 3(c) and section 4.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed" id="idca1e5756-9236-46d5-8ae8-9b9543af5e40"><enum>6.</enum><header>Hiring authority</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb1efc79f-b8dc-429c-80ae-a085ad319abf" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Immigration judges</header><text>The Attorney General shall increase—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida4cb4ece-10e9-449e-8e14-c74cc7be9f87" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of immigration judges by not fewer than an additional 500 judges, as compared to the number of immigration judges as of the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8a54a188-9c94-4b1c-bff7-5c61eade431f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the corresponding number of support staff, as necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide2c292f2-70fc-4960-9706-cacae528fe92" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Immigration and Customs Enforcement attorneys</header><text>The Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement shall increase the number of attorneys and staff employed by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement by the number that is consistent with the workload staffing model to support the increase in immigration judges.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc2280991e1504f59ac49063440c9c1b8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for—</text><paragraph id="idEC917CCF78024238A3A0F648634352E5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the hiring of immigration judges, support staff, and U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement attorneys under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id30E474CC3FA84F0EB5AC0961D84F60EB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the lease, purchase, or construction of facilities or equipment (including video teleconferencing equipment and equipment for electronic filing of immigration cases), and the transfer of federally owned temporary housing units to serve as facilities, for—</text><subparagraph id="idf8016a98f6364efcb3e8d8fc5ce80638" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the increased number of immigration judges, attorneys, and support staff under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id086a40e856a1471fae5c0a0909b3e5ba" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conducting immigration court proceedings in close proximity to the locations at which aliens are apprehended and detained.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

