<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-type="olc" bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-KEN23293-995-WX-54D" key="H">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1785 IS: Stop Fentanyl Overdoses Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code>
<congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>S. 1785</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber>
<action>
<action-date date="20230531" legis-day="20230530">May 31 (legislative day, May 30), 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S369">Mr. Markey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S366">Ms. Warren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S370">Mr. Booker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S277">Mr. Carper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S247">Mr. Wyden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S422">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S306">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S322">Mr. Merkley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S341">Mr. Blumenthal</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S359">Mr. Heinrich</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title>To establish programs to address addiction and overdoses caused by illicit fentanyl and other opioids, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body style="OLC" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H84B8D4D83D4045E0BD2AFC26B95A8A22">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H8CBCFBAB922F46ECAFCEB5719BE6E61A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
<subsection id="H8A34465267BD4370A62D6A5C9738C0B2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Fentanyl Overdoses Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H912A9A74B286453DADEF5E50DFA564A8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
<toc>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H8CBCFBAB922F46ECAFCEB5719BE6E61A">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HBDC25064A53D4F9F97BBA256E342733D">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="title" idref="H75AA17AA2D2245D485898891F987B218">TITLE I—Fentanyl</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H0963A3A80E694EBFA9FF225F96372A32">Sec. 101. Enhanced fentanyl surveillance.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF10248F13E124AF7AB0CEB830900E320">Sec. 102. Collection of overdose data.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HC07E4AC07540451BBEFBA9462158E3BD">Sec. 103. Public health support for law enforcement.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HFB9B40ACB01445E192DB93CC59FE7683">Sec. 104. Fentanyl detection.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H1C1D62F1A40447D9AD996ABA753EE913">Sec. 105. Grants to improve public health surveillance in forensic laboratories.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="title" idref="H4CC3780285F949E99B95C06ECEF119E4">TITLE II—Stemming the Supply of Fentanyl</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H9665C4CB07244636AC963F055345C764">Sec. 201. Report on countries that produce synthetic drugs.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H21E6ADB791CF4673ADE013418B35684B">Sec. 202. GAO report on international mail and cargo screening.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="title" idref="HAD54439D51DE40128A76C80D513EA294">TITLE III—Overdose prevention and substance use disorder treatment programs</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H1BC4C9DEA9C240978BB202279DD09FC6">Sec. 301. Opioid treatment education.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H59F5DBC80CEE40D09AC0F2C169E2AC8D">Sec. 302. GAO study on naloxone access.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HFCBB99E78AC741B3B45E667C0916FA29">Sec. 303. Increasing access to medication for opioid overdose reversal; exemption from requirements of the Drug Supply Chain Security Act.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HA61A38B6BA0E47CAA05E3DDB26A0087A">Sec. 304. Grant program on harms of drug misuse.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF696D5557E014ABC821AA224530EA153">Sec. 305. Good Samaritan immunity.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H914258B822544A6888102F2024531CEB">Sec. 306. Report on overdose prevention centers.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H13E34531798D4DD9A465A6B5E59E95C5">Sec. 307. Prisons and substance use disorder treatment.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section>
<section id="HBDC25064A53D4F9F97BBA256E342733D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H1A14E3AB73164ED2B6C693EA5216106E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fentanyl-related substance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fentanyl-related substance</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1308.11(h)(30)(i) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H91F577802497451E944283E30A8266B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></section> <title id="H75AA17AA2D2245D485898891F987B218"><enum>I</enum><header>Fentanyl</header> <section id="H0963A3A80E694EBFA9FF225F96372A32"><enum>101.</enum><header>Enhanced fentanyl surveillance</header> <subsection id="H2AB01D72E4954473A544555206623F46"><enum>(a)</enum><header>CDC surveillance program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part J of title III of the Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 392A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280b-1">42 U.S.C. 280b–1</external-xref>) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H56A2FBD4FBAE4D949A1872CD5F771D96">
<section id="H0C5A0995F1634CAD8B9E9FB06994D3B8"><enum>392B.</enum><header>Enhanced fentanyl surveillance</header>
<subsection id="HE6C038497B344276BB618EFE8C8C6790"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>fentanyl-related substance</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1308.11(h)(30)(i) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations). </text></subsection> <subsection id="H7E65E04EA5774D79AEF711728ACC74D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data collection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall enhance the Overdose Data to Action program and other drug surveillance programs of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention by—</text>
<paragraph id="HDCE8EB55F5E046B48CF82F0C43B8F8D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encouraging States, political subdivisions of States, and territories to participate in such programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14CAB67F3FA645CCB9B25B241ECBE71F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing and accelerating the collection of data on fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, other synthetic opioids, and new emerging drugs of abuse (including harmful adulterants of fentanyl, such as xylazine), including the collection of related overdose data from medical examiners and drug treatment admissions and information regarding drug seizures; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H27EA6A947B3A4064B5EEDD744EFACE02"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilizing available and emerging information on fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, other synthetic opioids, and new emerging drugs of abuse, including information from—</text> <subparagraph id="H60ED0A2A49804E468CCB028E1C18D620"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the High Intensity Drug Trafficking Areas program under section 707 of the Office of National Drug Control Policy Reauthorization Act of 1998; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H15B9EE0CBA4F4E478C8B2C7AAC51AE73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the National Drug Early Warning System;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB69432933FD4D919E638FC6385D4A15"><enum>(C)</enum><text>State and local public health authorities;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8C68AD4094884188BA6CA0AA6EE63500"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Federal, State, and local public health laboratories; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFA0E5DE3B4040CFB5E1B497C76ED60B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>drug seizures by Federal, State, and local law enforcement agencies, including information from the National Seizure System and the National Forensic Laboratory Information System of the Drug Enforcement Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7D1093098C954310B0B35F4F2C933C63" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall publicly disseminate data collected under this section. </text></subsection> <subsection id="id4DB6B060D5C4438CA0515F919F15505C" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as are necessary.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H0926A9FAFDA34DE38CCB4638F1CB4AF1" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Law enforcement reporting</header><text>Each Federal law enforcement agency shall report information on all drug seizures by that agency to the Drug Enforcement Administration for inclusion in the National Seizure System.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7F3262D304A3401E8F0F7865D5898DDF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H6844DFA4EC07471E8C15F00C7B69E1BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>publish a report analyzing how Federal agencies can improve their collection, reporting, sharing, and analytic use of drug seizure data across Federal agencies and with States and local governments; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF48813F477294B15AFA151F001943C01"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include in such report an analysis of how well available data on drug seizures can measure progress toward reducing drug trafficking into and within the United States, as outlined in strategies such as the National Drug Control Strategy of the Office of National Drug Control Policy.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="HF10248F13E124AF7AB0CEB830900E320"><enum>102.</enum><header>Collection of overdose data</header>
<subsection commented="no" id="H6F9C073EFBB2484D983142D0C646633F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall commence a study on how to most efficiently track overdoses by type of drug, including fentanyl.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HDD081BE41E4140368CC9C1331681612A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HBFA4DF0B5F0E4BBD9063B08D0147F30E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon completion of the study under subsection (a), and taking into consideration the results of such study, the Secretary shall award grants to States to facilitate the collection of data with respect to fentanyl-involved overdoses.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H56141EAFCC374BECB5F87FB16A6FF14E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>As a condition on receipt of a grant under this subsection, an applicant shall agree to share the data collected pursuant to the grant with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H5F1D9468C73C420F85D8A3E3945AEC40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give preference to applicants whose grant proposals demonstrate the greatest need for collecting timely and accurate data on overdoses.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HC07E4AC07540451BBEFBA9462158E3BD"><enum>103.</enum><header>Public health support for law enforcement</header>
<subsection id="H646C66FE2FBD4F70B26CDCE00F5234C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Support for fentanyl detection and handling</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Attorney General, shall carry out a program to provide to Federal, State, and local law enforcement agencies training on accurate information about fentanyl and how to detect and handle fentanyl.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAB0DCBA6024F4EC2922F3F94BB417009"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Evidence-Based</header><text>The program under subsection (a) shall comply with evidence-based guidelines, including the <quote>Fentanyl Safety Recommendations for First Responders</quote> (or any successor guidelines) of the Office of National Drug Control Policy.</text></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="HFB9B40ACB01445E192DB93CC59FE7683"><enum>104.</enum><header>Fentanyl detection</header>
<subsection commented="no" id="H25C2D9E52EE443E59A08CA2A19DA4408"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Testing of contaminants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, and in coordination with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall continue to improve efforts to enhance screening and identification of contaminants in drugs to prevent overdoses.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HE348FA438FFF4E10AC75474A6B58A232"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Research into technologies</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H95AB96F765024732B6979279ECEA0309"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of chemical screening device</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>chemical screening device</term> means an infrared spectrophotometer, mass spectrometer, nuclear magnetic resonance spectrometer, Raman spectrophotometer, ion mobility spectrometer, or any other device or other technology that is able to determine the presence of, or identify, one or more contaminants in drugs.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H95F51824A43D47E8996EC3D3D573071F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct or support research for the development or improvement of portable and affordable technologies relating to testing drugs for fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances, including chemical screening device methods.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HA52A61525A49471B85377FCE87FE9827"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection such sums as are necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="H1C1D62F1A40447D9AD996ABA753EE913"><enum>105.</enum><header>Grants to improve public health surveillance in forensic laboratories</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H5200091751604751BFB2BF5C57DDAFAC" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"> <part commented="no" id="HDA94FDF6B10E4EEA825CC3B7C95F4D82"><enum>PP</enum><header>Confronting the use of heroin, fentanyl, and associated synthetic drugs</header> <section commented="no" id="H224523DFDC2742BCB0AAD2C498BDA7E9"><enum>3061.</enum><header>Authority to make grants to address public safety through improved forensic laboratory data</header> <subsection commented="no" id="H16596E6399F74572B43E69F3CAC6997A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to assist States and units of local government in—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H231037314C90436296187BB7E8151247"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carrying out programs to improve surveillance of heroin, fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, and associated synthetic drugs to enhance public health; </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H6306F08B56744C8BB7969CE88C98606A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improving the ability of States, Tribes, and units of local government to carry out such programs; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HCDC680B758A24E1BAB9CF51608004CA7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carrying out the activities as described in section 101 of the <short-title>STOP Fentanyl Act of 2023</short-title>. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H527743A0BD4E4983B5142CA3E086B3CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance, may make grants to States and units of local government to improve surveillance of heroin, fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, and associated synthetic drugs to enhance public health.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H7D28A969C1634C38B0F3045D30EC7A09"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant projects To improve surveillance of seized heroin, fentanyl, and associated synthetic drugs</header><text>Grants made under subsection (b) shall be used for programs, projects, and other activities to—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H875B7F6BB5824C118044E7411DC3AE91"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reimburse State, local, or forensic science laboratories to help address backlogs of untested samples of heroin, fentanyl, and associated synthetic drugs;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H8EEFAD5C55244C909C6A6B5BC7237A5C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reimburse State, local, or other forensic science laboratories for procuring equipment, technology, or other support systems if the applicant for the grant demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Attorney General that expenditures for such purposes would result in improved efficiency of laboratory testing and help prevent future backlogs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H6916F021E0D34A54AEF6A9453DE8E4A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reimburse State, local, or other forensic science laboratories for improved, real time data exchange with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention on fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, and other associated synthetic drugs present in the local communities; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HDBADC7F4B39041B1913D445CCFA8A19B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support State, tribal, and local health department services deployed to address the use of heroin, fentanyl, and associated synthetic drugs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H3A7B1C8C9E804900B14B1982666DDFB4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Not less than 60 percent of the amounts made available to carry out this section shall be awarded for the purposes under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (c).</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H1A13FB7DA20A425EA23FF2CCB686F8CE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as are necessary.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H5EF9BF3BF8594038AA060546B093EF59"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Allocation</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H9FE6B639C62941D18603D350899169FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Population allocation</header><text>Seventy-five percent of the amount made available to carry out this section in a fiscal year shall be allocated to each State that meets the requirements of section 2802 so that each State shall receive an amount that bears the same ratio to the 75 percent of the total amount made available to carry out this section for that fiscal year as the population of the State bears to the population of all States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H32B52AFF8443414F826DECD64D2E5D43"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Discretionary allocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Twenty-five percent of the amount made available to carry out this section in a fiscal year shall be allocated pursuant to the discretion of the Attorney General for competitive grants to States or units of local government with high rates of primary treatment admissions for polysubstance use, including heroin and other opioids, for use by State or local law enforcement agencies.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HBA395A1D1F9F4A959223578136B5DB56"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Minimum requirement</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraphs (1) and (2), each State shall receive not less than 0.6 percent of the amount made available to carry out this section in each fiscal year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H6866802D147D437A960AB11EFF582879"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certain territories</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE450CD38601547A4BEBEB24CE407F35A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of the allocation under this section, American Samoa and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands shall be considered as 1 State.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H335518AC362643A490D759FB976D0D01" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Allocation amongst certain territories</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), 67 percent of the amount allocated shall be allocated to American Samoa and 33 percent shall be allocated to the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title>
<title id="H4CC3780285F949E99B95C06ECEF119E4"><enum>II</enum><header>Stemming the Supply of Fentanyl</header>
<section id="H9665C4CB07244636AC963F055345C764"><enum>201.</enum><header>Report on countries that produce synthetic drugs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report— </text> <paragraph id="H4041BB49430E44F3B67437C67CA1C064"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifying the countries the Secretary determines are the principal producers of synthetic drugs trafficked into the United States;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H985C0AEA65924192A37682B14E4FE807"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assessing how and why those countries are producing such drugs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H771237F38F8B4474A0F385AD122CB559"><enum>(3)</enum><text>describing measures the Secretary plans to take to reduce the flow of such drugs into the United States.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H21E6ADB791CF4673ADE013418B35684B"><enum>202.</enum><header>GAO report on international mail and cargo screening</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report reviewing the impact of the High Intensity Drug Trafficking Areas program on illicit fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances imported through international mail and cargo, including discussion of the following:</text> <paragraph id="id494cfe4502d8410fa9c569f47dd9e3f6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The volume of fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances being imported into the United States by means of international mail and cargo.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6A713118F10A4E0E850F7B25AD51CAEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The potential impact of increased screening for illicit fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances on—</text> <subparagraph id="HC411B2D8CC1845ABBE2F8BB4CD9863C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deterring drug trafficking in the United States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBCBA5E3CC09A43E2BD1F22C70DD81DF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">interdicting fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances that were manufactured outside of the United States and intended, or attempted, to be imported into the United States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H244955FC7A044089A5654EFF0F29EEF8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of Federal criminal prosecutions based on the manufacture, distribution, or possession of fentanyl or fentanyl-related substances, disaggregated by demographic data, including sex, race, and ethnicity, of the offender;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDA0EDCD013054708BBE0016568B453C2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the charges brought in such prosecutions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBCC1DC5AD5BD459ABE46444413672944"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the impacts of prosecutions on reducing demand and availability to users; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8E81E3AFE9034BBAB562B8B657D1C07B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the development of new fentanyl-related substances.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD9F808858124985878E952EBC604E7D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The need for noninvasive technology in screening for fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances, taking into account the findings pursuant to paragraphs (1) and (2). </text></paragraph></section></title>
<title id="HAD54439D51DE40128A76C80D513EA294"><enum>III</enum><header>Overdose prevention and substance use disorder treatment programs</header>
<section id="H1BC4C9DEA9C240978BB202279DD09FC6"><enum>301.</enum><header>Opioid treatment education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290dd">42 U.S.C. 290dd et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB9CF17C04424EE394C4CDA6C7CF99F7"> <section id="HECA4D949E83444C085462323FECDFB88"><enum>553.</enum><header>Opioid treatment education</header> <subsection id="HAC529E7DBCDE42FABDC7CF5CC9FE65F5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to States and local governmental entities to provide education to stakeholders, including health care providers, criminal justice professionals, and substance use disorder treatment personnel, on the current state of research on treatment for opioid use disorder, including—</text>
<paragraph id="HCBD65003963A491A936FF88C0E9903CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the use of opioid agonists or partial agonists; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H680ABB259DFF4648AE909F8D25693711"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the potential benefits of the use of opioid agonists or partial agonists for affected individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9CA5B817EAFC44F4A118E71F8B869A7E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>STOP Fentanyl Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that includes the following data on the education programs funded pursuant to grants under subsection (a):</text> <paragraph id="H748DE0C2F0D74D89B1430C5C2117856A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of people reached by educational materials funded pursuant to grants under subsection (a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFBE1EF99B51E4A819286370E0B32EE6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The geographic areas where people received such educational materials.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A5C7E799E524B77992288C52CA52213"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The remaining populations and areas targeted for awareness of such educational materials, including the characteristics of such populations and areas, such as the type of stakeholder.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H337B856BCD534F06B40565A6E75F68BA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The outcomes of education provided pursuant to grants under subsection (a), as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF0DDFB36B2B94420AE516C98C85AEB72"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as are necessary.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H59F5DBC80CEE40D09AC0F2C169E2AC8D"><enum>302.</enum><header>GAO study on naloxone access</header>
<subsection id="ida4418eba948d4a93856d1ad1b867aaf5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on actions that may be taken to ensure appropriate access and affordability of naloxone for individuals seeking to purchase naloxone. Such study shall address what is known about—</text> <paragraph id="id83b2730755c34315832f35ebf229a4dc"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coverage of naloxone (in any available form), including whether naloxone can be covered as an over-the-counter drug under a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage (as such terms are defined in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>)) or for individuals entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>), or receiving medical assistance under a State plan under title XIX of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) or a waiver of such plan;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id46ae4fbe2d5c42eab4f483ba1b369080"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the out-of-pocket cost to consumers purchasing naloxone—</text> <subparagraph id="idfe15b202271f47ad932ad9d78aec329d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with a prescription, with and without coverage under any such plan or coverage; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id6b89715889ec47a5b632df6cd89a190a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>over-the-counter, with and without coverage under any such plan or coverage; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id68021b004e4541ddb1dacc5e7de5050d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>via standing order; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id9fe5b122f44a428a97d65f683a52fedc"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other factors impacting coverage, including barriers in covering naloxone as an over-the-counter drug, the relative net costs of naloxone when purchased over-the-counter without insurance coverage compared to when purchased with a prescription and covered under a group health plan or health insurance coverage, and the availability of naloxone purchased and distributed through public health entities.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="ided4621da706e4714a4df113ee0df8717"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report that contains the findings of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HFCBB99E78AC741B3B45E667C0916FA29"><enum>303.</enum><header>Increasing access to medication for opioid overdose reversal; exemption from requirements of the Drug Supply Chain Security Act</header>
<subsection id="H8AA67BABEC534F7597ED231CFE0FD17F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transactions</header><text>Section 581(24)(B) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360eee">21 U.S.C. 360eee(24)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H6717256418634A0D9014DA83F8670209"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (xvii) and (xviii) as clauses (xviii) and (xix), respectively; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF3486D1088924A9DB448AE1A60DE67A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (xvi) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H688E45CA1E154F23895042209A63E5FA"> <clause id="H5B18D88B3F094C1F8F0BA1D4833833E2"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>the distribution of an opioid antagonist indicated for emergency treatment of opioid overdose, such as naloxone, by or to an overdose prevention, syringe services program, or other harm reduction service;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2170E1480B994494B49EF858BCC9A86C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Wholesale distribution</header><text>Section 503(e)(4) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/353">21 U.S.C. 353(e)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H7EC12F8B42E6452C8F42AC798626C4D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (R) and (S) as subparagraphs (S) and (T), respectively; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB1B8E4697272432D985D702F9BD04A65"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (Q) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H61948FFF6C0947EFB707106880425B8E"> <subparagraph id="H0DD9B2EA12BA44E688E4742C51D7AB18"><enum>(R)</enum><text>the distribution of an opioid antagonist indicated for emergency treatment of opioid overdose, such as naloxone, by or to an overdose prevention, syringe services program, or other harm reduction service;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HA61A38B6BA0E47CAA05E3DDB26A0087A"><enum>304.</enum><header>Grant program on harms of drug misuse</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290dd">42 U.S.C. 290dd et seq.</external-xref>) (as amended by section 301) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18B528BE6A1C4AFAA3266F150141FD4F"> <section id="H5982561E709B4992A0664797E8536414"><enum>554.</enum><header>Grant program on harms of drug misuse</header> <subsection id="H6E24CD0CF4A141A6A03931EAE3A7C3B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary, in consultation with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall award grants to States and political subdivisions of States to support the delivery of overdose prevention services, including distribution of opioid reversal agents approved by the Food and Drug Administration, such as naloxone, fentanyl strips, and other harm reduction services that address the harms of drug misuse, including by—</text>
<paragraph id="H4993DDF6CEF3460DA34BB4C4E4AF630C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>connecting individuals at risk for, or with, a substance use disorder to overdose education, counseling, and health education; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3537779F222D4B7B8FED93036F4B5B46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>encouraging such individuals to take steps to reduce the harms associated with substance misuse.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF5ABEBC08F414403816666336C78ADAC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Assistant Secretary shall prioritize grants to applicants that are—</text> <paragraph id="H3C66401A93FD42DB9750C30F1C30FEBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organizations providing culturally competent care in terms of considerations based on race, language, ethnicity, gender, sexuality, or disability; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCFD8788F387049ECB1C405319A65DA43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>proposing to serve areas with—</text> <subparagraph id="H9ECDA0FF6B2C4412BF3D6AC95C13B0E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a higher proportion of the population who meet criteria for dependence on, or abuse of, illicit drugs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7B4AF5564B9B4B5AA7A51E37F13740E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a higher drug overdose death rate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9B4A3E7C2439427CBD85B73E21A246D9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a greater behavioral health and substance use disorder workforce need.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H377CF8EA2F754BC89B0B583A5288DA9C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special considerations</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section shall—</text> <paragraph id="H618748A354DE4938B8E6801EB1383DF4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that not less than 60 percent of the grant funds are used for harm reduction programs; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H07251D4654654C12B4293BB7C2C0F07D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prioritize the delivery of opioid antagonists to—</text> <subparagraph id="HBA14C4013BD344FE8A097EBCEDBDE27D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">people who use opioids or illicit drugs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2A88C5128CA84E3C925DE52508CD85BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>families of such people;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74746923889C443088321CAD069DC59E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>first responders, such as law enforcement personnel and nonemergency services, such as firefighters and park rangers; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0E3A64CB71FD41BEBE98492BFB93ECB4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>community service providers, such as library, school, and public transportation personnel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9C7A288939204851BD2A4DF4D1F3ECAC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of grant awards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under this section may use grant funds for the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HC1A091DFC0C247D3ABAE8DBECB6CB7ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Adapting, maintaining, and expanding essential services provided by harm reduction service organizations to address the risks of drug overdose and contraction of infectious disease.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2C1ECC97C4204DD4B1B81C330563E561"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Maintaining or hiring staff.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H36850884F47540118B9ADA8B2F671D8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Supporting program operational costs, including staff, rent, and vehicle purchase or maintenance.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B14DD8400534765AD7D6D3F068CA2C4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Program supplies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H69C05E98BD3A438FADF20B79002653CE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Support and case management services.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H081AEB35447346F6A58AD929A0261C06"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as are necessary.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="HF696D5557E014ABC821AA224530EA153"><enum>305.</enum><header>Good Samaritan immunity</header>
<subsection id="HA390E8B82AE044A6855F1C59E1D72238"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part B of title II of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/238">42 U.S.C. 238 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB98E72021E74463596F45435CEC21423"> <section id="HF9CF43BA0188416E98C8986EBCF0C649"><enum>249.</enum><header>Good Samaritan immunity</header> <subsection id="H4269908B30BC4D9E9597CA48D60F2801"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on civil liability for individuals who administer opioid overdose reversal drugs</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB137523BAD324685811DE0D4B7FBEBD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, except as provided in paragraph (2), no individual shall be liable in any Federal or State proceeding for harm caused by the emergency administration of an opioid overdose reversal drug to an individual who has or reasonably appears to have suffered an overdose from heroin or another opioid, if the individual administers the opioid overdose reversal drug in good faith. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC8B733EE1FA944478804EF4E60998B46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to an individual if the harm was caused by the gross negligence or reckless misconduct of the individual who administers the drug.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC4BF8D332E414823AF86226281C7161D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definition of opioid overdose reversal drug</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>opioid overdose reversal drug</term> means a drug approved under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act that is indicated for the partial or complete reversal of the pharmacological effects of an opioid overdose in the human body. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HEA914D397FBB4F4FB3AC360393171C86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Immunity from liability</header>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HB481078AB34048D082F8890E620A09A9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Immunity</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id66d5ca94b53a43a782394cd9d6fbcfb3"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>An individual described in subparagraph (B) shall not be cited, arrested, prosecuted, criminally liable, or subject to any sanction for a violation of a condition of supervised release under section 404 of the Controlled Substances Act for the possession or use of a controlled substance, or under any other provision of Federal law regulating the misuse of prescription drugs, as a result of seeking medical assistance as described in clause (i), (ii), or (iii) of subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf218bdeb9f9145afab16d1d213d467e9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Individual described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual referred to in subparagraph (A) is an individual who, in good faith and in a timely manner—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4ecbf10a62cb4a8f80b14da9cd5e6465"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seeks medical assistance for another individual who is experiencing a drug overdose;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5f556a7c58c84f1eb1f32aa53ff1132b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seeks medical assistance for himself or herself for a drug overdose; or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2cc9d876726e45ecb703d06cdc869566"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is the subject of a request for medical assistance for another individual who is experiencing a drug overdose. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H488266B3BBD041FFBC44A687D23097C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection preempts the laws of a State or any political subdivision of a State to the extent that such laws are inconsistent with this subsection, unless such laws provide greater protection from liability.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE4F91C01BF5F4306934A6698D51C1B65"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H76B81137FFF248BB9BDA6BAE7BEC3D22"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Controlled substance</header><text>The term <term>controlled substance</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HB00C9D745A4F44329C7673BE6CBC1D57"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Drug overdose</header><text>The term <term>drug overdose</term> means an acute condition resulting from or believed to be resulting from the use of a controlled substance, which an individual, who is not a health care professional, would reasonably believe requires medical assistance.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H86E7AE4816854C03856A3FEFF44FD6A5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prescription drug</header><text>The term <term>prescription drug</term> means a drug subject to section 503(b)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H48A0660EBA5144E6933D6ED19104765C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Seeks medical assistance; seeking medical assistance</header><text>The terms <term>seeks medical assistance</term> and <term>seeking such medical assistance</term> include—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H348C92B265A448BE8DD3D74F95DE85A2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reporting a drug or alcohol overdose or other medical emergency to a law enforcement authority, the 9–1–1 system, a poison control center, or a medical provider;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="HC532A9A17E8D425EAAB3F9DC0C502571"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assisting another individual who is making a report described in clause (i); or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H7C1A61D497934AECA3981BBDB28C6755"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>providing care by administering a drug to someone who is experiencing a drug or alcohol overdose or other medical emergency while awaiting the arrival of medical assistance.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HF80A76BF5D02417CA1E9EA28A66E64AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public awareness campaign</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in coordination with the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, shall carry out a campaign to increase public awareness of the limitations on civil and criminal liability established by section 249 of the Public Health Service Act (as added by subsection (a)).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H914258B822544A6888102F2024531CEB"><enum>306.</enum><header>Report on overdose prevention centers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine under which the National Academies shall—</text>
<paragraph id="id02f332764ebe4f2d990c8814b9421d68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of the agreement, submit to Congress a report on overdose prevention centers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id814a580f9ae14d1296c60151bdc23373"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include in the report required under paragraph (1)—</text>
<subparagraph id="idddbec244e34347e6a8ae20f1d36849ef"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identification of barriers to operating overdose prevention centers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id0e33e731fb28496182012afebd2ad68b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a compilation of the data available to measure effectiveness of overdose prevention centers on preventing and reducing regional rates of overdose deaths, and practices utilized at overdose prevention centers to improve access to medication for opioid use disorder and recovery services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idfb31e5f1e546472498b2ef94f2b88209"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identification of best practices at overdose prevention centers to promote individual and public health, provide resources to individuals and families, improve access to substance use disorder and behavioral health services, and reduce stigma;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="idf2b03ba206f744fda97cd326abad85c8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations for developing integrated care settings inclusive of overdose prevention sites and incorporating overdose prevention sites into referral networks; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idf1be8fb56fdc4928a0ac958b6271fc35"><enum>(E)</enum><text>recommended approaches to overdose prevention services that may serve as effective strategies for recovery for people using fentanyl, fentanyl-related substances, other synthetic opioids, and new emerging drugs of abuse (including harmful adulterants of fentanyl, such as xylazine).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section commented="no" id="H13E34531798D4DD9A465A6B5E59E95C5"><enum>307.</enum><header>Prisons and substance use disorder treatment</header> <subsection commented="no" id="HB9E033D684604AFD85FEFE7429FD8BF1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prisons and medication-Assisted treatment</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HAD9EFE601E29480BB536437BE6A8F590"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Bureau of Prisons, in collaboration with the Director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy, shall establish a program to offer—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H90F87B75DBBD4C1299552550CA45C444"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">all drugs that are approved by the Food and Drug Administration for treatment of a substance use disorder;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfd34c098ef8847a38c58609d409f6ac9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">counseling and other psychosocial treatments for the treatment of substance use disorder; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H198D20186A074DC8BA8BCCE9B84CE8FC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based withdrawal management services to individuals in the custody of the Bureau of Prisons to provide a comprehensive treatment approach substance use disorders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H5F2D061588CE4281AD4FB5BB14A7631A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection such sums as are necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB58F79AF40364213964AA2781F7A2949"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Residential substance abuse treatment for State prisoners</header><text>Section 1904(d) of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10424">34 U.S.C. 10424(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H9FC3FFD8B0CC4796AF571B8F82747807"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>means</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0CFBE15F6BAC443CB5D0E55EC0EE1970">
<paragraph commented="no" id="H33FDBBCCFEDA44E3B60B1A2F85C4328A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HE97CC28FF4564F41A662A072AAA925DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H80848D76FA364721B5BDB9C1A8A26031"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C7DECD4CB6546FBB75BEBE11DFCD2D5"> <paragraph commented="no" id="HDD3B4B8E7A9D490B8341F49CFE76B124"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any such course of comprehensive individual and group substance abuse treatment services using medication-assisted treatment for opioid use disorder (including the use of any drug approved or licensed by the Food and Drug Administration for such treatment).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></title>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


