<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-type="olc" bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-EHF23512-HL9-77-TC7"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S2007 IS: Improving Corporate Governance Through Diversity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 2007</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S306">Mr. Menendez</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S385">Ms. Cortez Masto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S361">Ms. Hirono</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S394">Ms. Smith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S366">Ms. Warren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S370">Mr. Booker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S415">Mr. Warnock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S307">Mr. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S390">Mr. Van Hollen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S413">Mr. Padilla</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to require the submission by issuers of data relating to diversity, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body style="OLC" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HEB1BDE5C5A9444CAB34587370ECF7A8D"><section section-type="section-one" id="HECBCD16C219F4E1C8A57968BEC102AF2"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Corporate Governance Through Diversity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H23E6FE281DFA44D3A39CE735714E9FCD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Submission of data relating to diversity by issuers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1539BCFFAE2447AEA718E411BD82B01C"><subsection id="H192A42FE538A4C81B64E3FAE04D2E859"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Submission of data relating to diversity</header><paragraph id="H9E68437DA76840CEB98BCA2804C9FAB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H328AC092ABB7413DB1880A0C2043ADEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>executive officer</term> has the meaning given the term in section 230.501(f) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA073098A484458A9689B6DB7EAB546A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>veteran</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C98CD2693C040A7AF308924ADC3FA17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission of disclosure</header><text>Each issuer required to file an annual report under subsection (a) shall disclose in any proxy statement and any information statement relating to the election of directors filed with the Commission the following:</text><subparagraph id="HC8F780142876414D8E2CA6F0B468A14B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Data, based on voluntary self-identification, on the racial, ethnic, and gender composition of—</text><clause id="H5778BEC948A94C86B167751C09B215DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the board of directors of the issuer;</text></clause><clause id="HDA980112B28248429C0846EB8EA31CA4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nominees for the board of directors of the issuer; and</text></clause><clause id="HD98165745B12476E920CB865C15CBE82"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the executive officers of the issuer.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE2166EF2D4D4488816523BD9F165E86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The status of any member of the board of directors of the issuer, any nominee for the board of directors of the issuer, or any executive officer of the issuer, based on voluntary self-identification, as a veteran.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50634D58A14E4B2AAE24202F2C6512A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Whether the board of directors of the issuer, or any committee of that board of directors, has, as of the date on which the issuer makes a disclosure under this paragraph, adopted any policy, plan, or strategy to promote racial, ethnic, and gender diversity among—</text><clause id="HC16B418A087748619BA89321CA3F4028"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the board of directors of the issuer;</text></clause><clause id="HC84ED846143C4268B4537F286832525E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nominees for the board of directors of the issuer; or</text></clause><clause id="H14827B4B3B46461698BB7A9C53904C31"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the executive officers of the issuer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H52F81F23662A4521B52DE4A97B5A3081"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alternative submission</header><text>In any 1-year period in which an issuer required to file an annual report under subsection (a) does not file with the Commission a proxy statement or an information statement relating to the election of directors, the issuer shall disclose the information required under paragraph (2) in the first annual report of issuer that the issuer submits to the Commission after the end of that 1-year period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE9A0AA4C2A046DB9DFCA38FC1C8275C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, and publish on the website of the Commission, a report that analyzes the information disclosed under paragraphs (2) and (3) and identifies any trends with respect to such information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FB2986E83594177BFA56CCCE4917E5E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Best practices</header><subparagraph id="H61030B90BC8F4C6485953866ED232C08"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Office of Minority and Women Inclusion of the Commission shall, not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, and every 3 years thereafter, publish best practices for compliance with this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A986AF1446C4962A72AE597DB665B86"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Comments</header><text>The Director of the Office of Minority and Women Inclusion of the Commission may, pursuant to subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, solicit public comments related to the best practices published under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H529E95397C784535B1281221337A24F2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Diversity advisory group</header><subsection id="HC77AD8E90FC542DCB8824F275F2E047F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="H50AD24BF838249CBBA001DED8AFEEBD7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisory Group</header><text>The term <term>Advisory Group</term> means the Diversity Advisory Group established under subsection (b). </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6141921C63E545E3A3BA27332C9BA7C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id83905770EA3644AFB34BB4DB3E6CCE91"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Issuer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>issuer</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4B3D20E4223C403A8051815FCEF4F93E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Commission shall establish a Diversity Advisory Group, which shall be composed of representatives from— </text><paragraph id="idB6614ABC5C414BE18333C93F58975F39"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Government and State and local governments; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD4080EA615FB416BAB447F12D6136EEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>academia; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6718E6ABF37B4D15AF037AE700C3E95A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the private sector.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2B852916F89461F8EB67A9AC3A95993"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Study and recommendations</header><text>The Advisory Group shall—</text><paragraph id="H164AD2C26AF04CDDBB99301BA6391D16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out a study that identifies strategies that can be used to increase gender, racial, and ethnic diversity among members of boards of directors of issuers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BFCB3530E8845859D5EE5E8516716CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 270 days after the date on which the Advisory Group is established, submit to the Commission, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HDBFCF7C8E82A4682AA231C51A2D6D954"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes any findings from the study conducted under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H033412876B574B1086E85C21472DC4E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>makes recommendations regarding strategies that issuers could use to increase gender, racial, and ethnic diversity among board members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD59F07380EE4E788A7B6FA3E99F3D5D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Advisory Group submits the report required under subsection (c)(2), and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives a report that describes the status of gender, racial, and ethnic diversity among members of the boards of directors of issuers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1B39D42830744E50A6DA19D49F6EE88B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public availability of reports</header><text>The Commission shall make all reports of the Advisory Group available to issuers and the public, including on the website of the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="id14E00C43E08A4543A92E3601EA329C93"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inapplicability of certain provisions</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply with respect to the Advisory Group or the activities of the Advisory Group.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

