<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-WIL23314-0Y7-CL-DTP"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S2440 IS: Exploitative Workplace Surveillance and Technologies Task Force Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 2440</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S309">Mr. Casey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S353">Mr. Schatz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S418">Mr. Fetterman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S370">Mr. Booker</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To establish an interagency task force on employer surveillance and workplace technologies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Exploitative Workplace Surveillance and Technologies Task Force Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6b3ec23db6aa402197a46baa0625e331"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="idF829571D176B4CBDB0DD6BC549998A7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicant</header><text>The term <term>applicant</term>, with respect to an employer, means an individual who applies, or applied, to be employed by, or otherwise perform work for remuneration for, the employer. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id7d6c7f23b2f14236ab120dcb4265891d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Automated decision system</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="idCD538B6A843444D3A9396EC9190FD209"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>automated decision system</term> means a system, software, or process that—</text><clause commented="no" id="id72E316E6CB714EB99C90093EDE6A07DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>uses computation, in whole or in part, to determine outcomes, make or aid decisions (including through evaluations, metrics, or scoring), inform policy implementation, collect data or observations, or otherwise interact with individuals or communities, including such a system, software, or process derived from machine learning, statistics, or other data processing or artificial intelligence techniques; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="idB8908DD9E6FF4E5891FE8E9E015A4687"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not passive computing infrastructure.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id3143D375C2354C248368AB06A5ADAC4C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Passive computing infrastructure</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>passive computing infrastructure</term> means any intermediary technology that does not influence or determine the outcome of a decision, make or aid in a decision (including through evaluations, metrics, or scoring), inform policy implementation, or collect data or observations, including web hosting, domain registration, networking, caching, data storage, or cybersecurity. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idB91CBA8141734FECAF643B74B92C7928"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Automated decision system output</header><text>The term <term>automated decision system output</term>, with respect to an employer, means any information, assumptions, predictions, scoring, recommendations, decisions, evaluations, metrics, or conclusions generated by an automated decision system used by the employer with respect to a worker of the employer. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7CA7D1CB175F42B3B8DD17E2A1F55C2D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Biometric information</header><subparagraph id="idF9F405AB10BA41AFA019A246E611EA20"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>biometric information</term> means any information generated from the technological processing of an individual’s unique biological, physical, or physiological characteristics that is linked or reasonably linkable to an individual, including—</text><clause id="id6915a821a0be404db0fe7b54cad3be11"><enum>(i)</enum><text>fingerprints;</text></clause><clause id="id612ee5d71e5d450ca65f57ad1029a584"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>voice prints;</text></clause><clause id="ida1cda91fd35a4624ae2473a43cd7f3e7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>iris or retina scans;</text></clause><clause id="id2959111878b74b80be4c7c9158feba68"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>facial or hand mapping, geometry, or templates; or</text></clause><clause id="id7c921e3ee39744b6b0be3fb6484d70d0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>gait or personally identifying physical movements.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3b3028bf1b7a4522b469769038c974e3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>biometric information</term> includes information on the absence of a biometric or the presence of a prosthetic. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id917ad4695f974850af449a331378a4a8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>biometric information</term> does not include—</text><clause id="id7ca0452cf6bf49b492e693c1259fd279"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a digital or physical photograph;</text></clause><clause id="iddff94db279e84a6f8c98bc3535257f1d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an audio or video recording; or</text></clause><clause id="id1b90a7f0d35f42509bae0d610ae0a32a"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>information generated from a digital or physical photograph, or an audio or video recording, that cannot be used to identify an individual. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id19d7699b2cd441b4970387b027d98b13"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Data</header><text>The term <term>data</term>, with respect to a worker, means any information that identifies, relates to, describes, is reasonably capable of being associated with, or could reasonably be linked, directly or indirectly, with the worker, regardless of how the information is collected, inferred, or obtained, including—</text><subparagraph id="id9545AC8D3FEA40CEB41E41BE01581260"><enum>(A)</enum><text>personally identifiable information with respect to the worker, including any name, contact information, government-issued identification number, financial information, criminal background, location information, photographs, biometric information, health or medical information, or employment history associated with the worker;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id76f34f46bd9545cfaede671a99f9f995"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any information related to the workplace activities with respect to the worker, including—</text><clause id="id7414DAAFB7F142F8BF309AF255CE2D88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>human resources information, including the contents of a personnel file or performance evaluation;</text></clause><clause id="id1856dc58b52b412582b69eed06edddf3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>work process information, such as productivity and efficiency information and time or attendance information;</text></clause><clause id="id98b63890abd14f01be0315f0df7b716b"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>information that captures workplace communications and interactions, including emails, texts, internal message boards, and customer interaction and ratings;</text></clause><clause id="id3c5060c5b8174635826db01401cd5434"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>device usage and information, including calls placed or precise geolocation information;</text></clause><clause id="id4a67188e839c4cd5bd888abf9a0c69a9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>audio-video information and other information collected from sensors, including movement tracking, images, videos, and thermal-sensor information;</text></clause><clause id="id7A34550735044DB0A56F9F1B4510DFC6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>biometric information;</text></clause><clause id="idF87C770D0F9F46CB9C6D1D2E81DBD5AF"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>information from a personality test taken by a worker, including such a test given electronically at the beginning of or during a work shift or during the application process;</text></clause><clause id="idf3d7423471254e33a72a1e5a38e645a4"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>inputs for an automated decision system or any automated decision system output;</text></clause><clause id="idaa1ad98ebaa44987840d85be898a8d44"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>information that is collected or generated to mitigate the spread of infectious diseases, including COVID–19, or to comply with any Federal, State, or local law; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd9724da42edd4059bdd5ba1388a706b7"><enum>(x)</enum><text>information related to the ability of a worker and any related workplace accommodations; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id033b1207865943cb9df15409d467c751"><enum>(C)</enum><text>online information with respect to the worker that is collected while the worker is on- or off-duty, including any internet protocol address associated with the worker, the online communication platform activity of the worker, any advertisement-related tracking identifier associated with the worker, the internet browsing history of the worker, or other digital sources or unique identifiers associated with the worker. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idbcad9205bcba4590b439a6faa295809d"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Employ</header><text>The term <term>employ</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id52DE8F95220A4909BC8C71D2F560B0D4"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Employer</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="idDCEADEFEB2C2440BB909A03FDE3ECFFB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>employer</term> means any person who is—</text><clause id="id7625abce42354696ac52ed7fefa9f666"><enum>(i)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id63BE6B3208784208B41D2485D5328CEF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a covered employer who is not described in any other subclause of this clause;</text></subclause><subclause id="id6FBEE878227A4886A956F6EC9FB0408A" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an entity employing a State employee described in section 304(a) of the Government Employee Rights Act of 1991 (42 U.S.C. 2000e–16c(a));</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="idCA6AA11ADF7E434BA514D2EB1E1FC9D7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an employing office, as defined in section 101 of the Congressional Accountability Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1301">2 U.S.C. 1301</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="id26AF651F9A9B495E9EEA25E00CCEB036"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an employing office, as defined in section 411(c) of title 3, United States Code; or</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="idFCD0C25611A8421EBDD969442E79FB02"><enum>(V)</enum><text>an employing agency covered under subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/63">chapter 63</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id8526c67a569f4303baaa0055ac0148fe"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>engaged in commerce (including government), or an industry or activity affecting commerce (including government). </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id0F43B7A4BBE14BA1B7A2D2D958C2E3E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered employer</header><text>In subparagraph (A), the term <term>covered employer</term>— </text><clause commented="no" id="ide41b02e0943343fbaaef18b78743dadf"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means any person engaged in commerce or in any industry or activity affecting commerce who employs, or otherwise engages for the performance of work for remuneration, 11 or more workers;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="id7cac9097436744db83ac1e3969e17498"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes—</text><subclause commented="no" id="id412a140c0f8d499ab619ee30d529e248"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any person who acts, directly or indirectly, in the interest of a covered employer in relation to any individual performing work for remuneration for such covered employer; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="id04925216ee16421a93cd8ded2f9312d4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any successor in interest of a covered employer;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="id957DF676370946D1AA499A4B4E669A79"><enum>(III)</enum><text>any public agency; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="id124E5DF62AA345D89DED7CF572E0A658"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the Government Accountability Office and the Library of Congress; and </text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="idD8CC4D0448DD4DF992D6262E9BC95F16"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>does not include any labor organization (other than when acting as an employer) or anyone acting in the capacity of officer or agent of such labor organization.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="ideedacf5630a245389ae2ffa750bbe59b"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Public agency</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, a public agency shall be considered to be a person engaged in commerce or in an industry or activity affecting commerce.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id65c95a3ef78b403b96a52c72e1fdc8bf"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the terms <term>commerce</term>, <term>person</term>, and <term>public agency</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2f32ed5f221543d98563daf8702f674a"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3371 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id07974F1A45B048F9BDDDE19879D82F92"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Government entity</header><text>The term <term>government entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="id6BB8AA8AE0854FC88A2757A0035C4AB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Federal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id2BDF886BAECA46348FAEB2B073066911"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State or political subdivision thereof;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idE9DAC4B7DF5740B18A2C367CBA86B047"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any agency, authority, or instrumentality of a State or political subdivision thereof; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idD2266693AB004D0BAB4763ACC0805918"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a Tribal government or political subdivision thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id89b5393d4d314444b54f2a0e8facc923"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Impact assessment</header><text>The term <term>impact assessment</term> means an ongoing study on and evaluation of the use of workplace surveillance or an automated decision system and the impact on workers of such surveillance or system.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id59C14089F9714408ACEDB81BAF0CBDEF"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> means any Indian or Alaska Native tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, component band, or component reservation individually identified (including parenthetically) in the list published most recently as of the date of enactment of this Act pursuant to section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfefc4c012a294934b6b4e81eac172b6c"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Labor organization</header><text>The term <term>labor organization</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2(5) of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152(5)</external-xref>), except that such term shall also include—</text><subparagraph id="id7ea76995bd8047bdb244210ebbe73361"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any organization composed of labor organizations, such as a labor organization federation or a State or municipal labor body; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida3e06276302c4ec28506f2fe2a737b8b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any organization which would be included in the definition for such term under such section 2(5) but for the fact that the organization represents—</text><clause id="id502828e396d34b99a22fc3ddeb7f1269"><enum>(i)</enum><text>individuals employed by the United States, any wholly owned Government corporation, any Federal Reserve Bank, or any State or political subdivision thereof;</text></clause><clause id="idca16c8f1844847848ef92a67797f4841"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>individuals employed by persons subject to the Railway Labor Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/45/151">45 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="id4ba3980256b64e048abdcfcfed6f492d"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>individuals employed as agricultural laborers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5167F7E2928A4C2FAB4D6DE8161E3141"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Online communication platform activity</header><text>The term <term>online communication platform activity</term> means any activity on an individual platform-based online communication account. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id7120F01685E14F5C8584D4144C97BAC8"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Precise geolocation information</header><subparagraph id="id667E7BE385D04116A61F55B205B4441B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>precise geolocation information</term> means information that is derived from a device or technology that reveals the past or present physical location of an individual or of a device that identifies or is linked or reasonably linkable to 1 or more individuals, with sufficient precision to identify street level location information of the individual or device or the location of the individual or device within a range of 1,850 feet or less.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idAAFCEC60B3EA4A1B9552D5343BFB91B6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>precise geolocation information</term> does not include information described in subparagraph (A) identifiable or derived solely from the visual content of a legally obtained image. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idE1F00B0A4C4F4F36BE013D8E2CACBEDD"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Service provider</header><text>The term <term>service provider</term>, with respect to an employer, means a person that—</text><subparagraph id="idC58B0AEFEE264E3F855A1236801046AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collects, processes, conveys, or maintains data with respect to such employer only at the direction of, in accordance with the direction of, and pursuant to a written contract with the employer (including any terms of service or service agreements);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idFBBB9FE018CB44ACA28A46C6CB19230B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not earn revenue from such collection, processing, conveyance, or maintenance of such data, except from the employer by providing contracted services to the employer with regard to such collection, processing, conveyance, or maintenance of such data; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idB53E95367DE848D5BC41CB0E535CF641"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not combine or link data associated with such employer with data associated with another employer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5AD14963AC77419987FD1EFC1BA915CF"><enum>(16)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States of the United States, the District of Columbia, or any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8ff3c9eb3f0e4490b8deace0dde921d5"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Technologist</header><text>The term <term>technologist</term> means an individual with experience in fields related to computational technology, or the technology industry that produces computational technology, such as advertising technology, application development, artificial intelligence, computer science, cybersecurity, data science, digital accessibility, digital forensics, human-centered design, product management, prototyping, service design, socio-technical systems, software engineering, technology ethics, user experience, or privacy rights, civil liberties, or civil rights related to technology. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id05447b04aa1b4af7b49758f0a3afdb82"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Third party</header><text>The term <term>third party</term>, with respect to an employer, means a person or entity—</text><subparagraph id="id8c2404be42c24dd0babfad6ade1673e1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to which such employer transfers or is able to transfer data, including any subsidiary or corporate affiliate of such employer; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id68afeabe6678452db2ace1374da12931"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is not—</text><clause id="id8b8863d1a37a489587e9ac82512e937d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such employer;</text></clause><clause id="id3d3a09e690af44e285ea22a22ec221c9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a service provider of such employer with respect to the data being transferred; or</text></clause><clause id="idD2F53469A6C8412E931FDF4D6A78F9DF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a government entity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idEAA580A7FDB14020806F72388948D078"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Transfer</header><text>The term <term>transfer</term>, with respect to data, means releasing, sharing, leasing, disseminating, disclosing, making available, or otherwise causing to be communicated, such data—</text><subparagraph id="idC5D6874DB31B4B3EA144D565C4D6C3F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to a third party; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6CB9B7CCF6E1405FAE6C65A6419F7092" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a third party that releases, shares, leases, disseminates, discloses, makes available, or otherwise causes to be communicated, such data, to another person. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="iddff0eb628fef4fc59bd3c12e5a89d989"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal government</term> means the recognized governing body of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id65c913e9836e4a7da648068912816c8e"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Worker</header><text>The term <term>worker</term> includes an applicant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id57C46D0B14244014B3210ADDFDD6D814"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Workplace surveillance</header><text>The term <term>workplace surveillance</term> means any collection (on- or off-duty) by an employer of data with respect to a worker, including the detection, monitoring, interception, collection, exploitation, preservation, protection, transmission, or retention of data concerning activities or communications with respect to the worker, including through the use of a product, system or service marketed, or that can be used, for such purposes, such as a computer, software, telephone, wire, radio, camera, sensor, electromagnetic, photoelectronic, handheld or wearable device, adaptive computing, assistive technology, durable medical equipment, or photo-optical system. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6e98dd2b533347b18f42529e11b11aa3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Workplace surveillance and technologies task force</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf89d6a347da4431d85c5bc6aebc11d0b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President shall establish an interagency task force, which shall be known as the <quote>White House Task Force on Workplace Surveillance and Technologies</quote> (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id050680a4441848b2b8052f455a5b6f9a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6600b0f13c724513b352f48401cf7dd7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Task Force shall be comprised of— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4448ae5eca2748dcb74b4371ee2c6cfb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>2 members appointed by the President, of whom—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1ad8736abfe447deaeb99e2221819394"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">1 shall be a representative of the Department of Labor; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idebd1d08c973c4809ab7c88dee8ec899c"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall be a representative of the Office of Science and Technology Policy; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd7cadda3bf4e41028e098c0d96c65ca0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>members who are representatives of—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id62671e11f3454d9bb1cd54f2a0032c65"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health;</text></clause><clause id="id0102a3a2e1e94b0eb997b9b161084315"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Disability Employment Policy;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide7bfd436f8e842bf9e50a11553f924f5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Wage and Hour Division of the Department of Labor;</text></clause><clause id="idacb124a592264230a45f0866bbf802eb"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0e92c969e6b14e4ea9359e5e8ea7b2af"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology;</text></clause><clause id="idfef25b9170c44c288011ed675b371383"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Attorney General;</text></clause><clause id="idb9afe1f8bd6c462da95ec32e315994ba"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Chair of the Federal Trade Commission;</text></clause><clause id="id653df63649c143f588d8afe647cf7e3b"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the Chair of the National Labor Relations Board;</text></clause><clause id="id3d5e455b99714806a825426a70417d11"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the Chair of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission;</text></clause><clause id="id1c386980d61e4333b175739ed3018ee1"><enum>(x)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Small Business Administration;</text></clause><clause id="idba06a5f9852e46d188d9dd85199acae1"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>the Director of the Domestic Policy Council;</text></clause><clause id="idec2138e17fb9420daed9fed2968f5518"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>the Director of the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9e31968eae704b28a4814afce23560b0"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id17f9eb527d9c45c180672fecd6e279c1"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United State Access Board; and</text></clause><clause id="iddec8f7cc77964cc39b966f205ac5e59e"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>any other Federal agency designated by the President. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb7eb8c34b8424dd29fd55bb32b6f212e"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The member appointed under paragraph (1)(A)(i) shall service as the Chair of the Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0e06b08fda5a45ebbe3f0f7517a306cf"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Vice Chair</header><text>The member appointed under paragraph (1)(A)(ii) shall service as the Vice Chair of the Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID49FC1DF7437F4D65827F32F3B59A5C61" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Period of appointment; vacancies</header><subparagraph id="id074CAA8C186848F69A84BF8EB7E8B53B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A member of the Task Force shall be appointed for the life of the Task Force. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ABA6BEF0A7647CD9CF8FFBE31E586FA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy in the Task Force—</text><clause id="id76B0CB8404734FF6A1DF2A252ED8694F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not affect the powers of the Task Force; and</text></clause><clause id="id484DA57A7CD74ED1BC86CBF65528ABB5" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id00adefb05b244cdaa42b3a6eb24120c9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Task Force shall meet not less than 4 times each year.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2a86b517d60043b884c88d5f1355ca78"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Subcommittees</header><text>The Task Force may appoint subcommittees or other working groups composed of Task Force members appointed under subsection (b), or their representatives, as may be necessary to accomplish the duties described in section 4.</text></subsection></section><section id="id1db7cb33a58d406b8e35b729e9d9f6b1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duties</header><subsection id="id254b33be911547dbbe83fb77ac77bee6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force shall study and evaluate the use of workplace surveillance by employers, including by studying—</text><paragraph id="idcf4bdce886654f79a553565ead01ae14"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the prevalence and types of workplace surveillance across different industries;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8e3b3d2febb8403498c39b4bf25a44b7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how employers are collecting data via workplace surveillance and are using, storing, securing, and transferring such data, including—</text><subparagraph id="idb25de849b3f04f3ca743810475ab3c92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the types of data collected by workplace surveillance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide2a4ceca652d48b6929747119384df58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether such data is provided by employers to a third party or otherwise ends up in files maintained by a third party; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3c7a0d0d3bfa4aa7a51582fb9e9faa13"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information on any disclosures to workers by employers of workplace surveillance used by the employer, and any provisions made available to workers to opt-out of such workplace surveillance;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide42c492503e44997a7e0c7b74d14df59"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the impact of workplace surveillance and the use of any automated decision system on—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id40fc5407ec094a209d1662aaba3c3c28"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">worker compensation; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id09a876620aef4db7a954a0de0ddfe6ad"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">worker performance reviews and subsequent decisions related to such reviews; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idcf5984fed18a434a9762c8029519800b"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">worker schedule policies; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idca770e14491b424bad4a71a35d23b54f"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">career advancement for workers; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id367d7c75fa354847993746064b711519"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assignment of duties for workers; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id69b4aec1155349b6a0af7bbb7ad9e14a"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">workplace safety, including with regard to worker physical and mental health;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2ae631c1b92d45f8a355bdde713e904d"><enum>(G)</enum><text>health care and long-term care coverage for workers; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id025c39f7d4c14305ad46c694cd363ac1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>disciplinary or termination decisions for workers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id756aae8dbdb54d16aa744c07ad0c4d0d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>interviewing or hiring workers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd35d62ce42024314b325b4651d4cadc3"><enum>(J)</enum><text>job quality;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2877072da976431f8c21158e078a70e2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the implications of workplace surveillance on worker organizing efforts and labor organization membership;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id269bf904534a4f17807d2dd723686ebb"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the impact of workplace surveillance and the use of any automated decision system on vulnerable populations, including workers with disabilities, low-wage workers, workers of color, older workers, and formerly incarcerated workers, and on gender equity in the workplace;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7ff2345b0a1d43aba7f4d2d661236d59"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the feasibility of requiring impact assessments for the use of workplace surveillance or an automated decision system with respect to certain employers or industries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida586eb7e8a2247d5b28b4d1a380c81f5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>third parties and service providers and their role in workplace surveillance and the technology used for workplace surveillance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd9a5de2e161d4dbe926e943c0fc8ffe9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out the duties under subsection (a), the Task Force shall, to the extent necessary and appropriate, regularly consult with—</text><paragraph id="id82637bb1bca9404e82233d6b68a6651e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>labor organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9ebae3422e5d47fc909cbd560ab2d861"><enum>(2)</enum><text>relevant stakeholders in the private sector; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id66ddb2c7028942b8b05a2c6036095320"><enum>(3)</enum><text>technologists and subject matter experts on—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id473b6cc828b9455185f019f8953f3c87"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">workplace surveillance; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id93455e7a8c96452fb8c16db9bb3e17f6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">technology used for workplace surveillance; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddb8c6c8e8d3541a69fe3e9eafcec3298"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">data; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbcc230ddd12046878f4805f500cf565a"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">workplace safety and health; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddd5951315f5a4673823402272c623490"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of workplace surveillance on vulnerable populations, including workers with disabilities, low-wage workers, workers of color, older workers, and formerly incarcerated workers and on gender equity in the workplace; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida95f25bcae5248b1bfbbba2971b60f56"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Federal agencies that are not represented on the Task Force; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id92ddd136b24c45ec9e87b0e06fd7a84d"><enum>(5)</enum><text>representatives from allied or partner countries. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb416fd988bdf42409136a2eef7f0fcd5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="idcc0302b2f98e47bf8ab91942d5ebdb9f"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Task Force shall submit a report to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and any other appropriate congressional committee, that includes a comprehensive review of the prevalence of workplace surveillance across different industries and how employers are using, storing, securing, and transferring data collected via workplace surveillance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id71bef7454763461a953410314f1fc962"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the report required by paragraph (1) is submitted, the Task Force shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and any other appropriate congressional committee, a report that includes findings on—</text><subparagraph id="idc0dfc6f20add486cbd7271423f6ab65f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the study described in subsection (a)(3) on the impact of workplace surveillance and the use of any automated decision system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idca6287f78d254733821959ad4f715c21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the implications of workplace surveillance on worker organizing efforts and labor organization membership; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd3d1d273fa6f442a9ba4688c340956a4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the effect of workplace surveillance and the use of an automated decision system on vulnerable populations, including workers with disabilities, low-wage workers, workers of color, older workers, and formerly incarcerated workers, and on gender equity in the workplace.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfda3d65789f4460b9a80c4b5cd132e6d"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the interim report required under paragraph (2) is submitted, the Task Force shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and any other appropriate congressional committee, and make available to the public on the website of the Executive Office of the President, a final report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="id817ca7f171994b6488d1f4ec43a8ea3b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recommendations to Federal agencies and such committees about how to address workplace surveillance and the technology used for workplace surveillance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7f910e89bbaa40fe872c4f1c59382adb"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations on how to conduct a government-wide coordinated strategy to address the rise of workplace surveillance and the technology used for workplace surveillance. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2497783e94e2475f8dd01e70e4ddddf8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Termination of Task Force</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id180d4eaddff84ee89336decfc276d99b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall terminate 60 days after the date on which the Task Force submits the report required under section 4(c)(3).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id77d6dd3ecdb24ccb81b662a6b258dfec"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional actions</header><text>During the 60-day period described in subsection (a), the Task Force may conclude any activities of the Task Force, including providing testimony to Congress concerning the final report submitted under section 4(c)(3). </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

