<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-KEN23266-MJX-05-H1N"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1729 IS: Human-services Emergency Logistic Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1729</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S309">Mr. Casey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S347">Mr. Moran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S331">Mrs. Gillibrand</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S288">Ms. Murkowski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S364">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S322">Mr. Merkley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S313">Mr. Sanders</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S406">Mr. Kelly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S306">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S341">Mr. Blumenthal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S361">Ms. Hirono</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S370">Mr. Booker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S386">Ms. Duckworth</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S366">Ms. Warren</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To facilitate nationwide accessibility and coordination of 211 services and 988 services in order to provide information and referral to all residents and visitors in the United States for mental health emergencies, homelessness needs, other social and human services needs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HA46995D5E298444A91F99A5751C60784"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Human-services Emergency Logistic Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HELP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="ida378ad23bd0b4accb55b19b4f1b4f967"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are as follows:</text><paragraph id="idc612bc65faeb4f9c8ad5eaf20b175ca6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To strengthen the existing 211 services and to coordinate 211 and 988 services in States throughout the Nation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idadd16c16c5df4454a4d30471b8335815"><enum>(2)</enum><text> To increase the availability, reliability, and responsiveness of 211 and 988 services, and improve information and referral through 211 and 988 services, across the country, 24 hours a day, 365 days a year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4002769341824cec9bc4b8c55827adb6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To reduce the use of 911 services for circumstances not related to law enforcement, fire, or medical emergencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide122f92887804d649abcf7717b457b60"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To more efficiently connect individuals with mental health services and other needed human services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb6317a7e80274171bfac2a78b64d49ad"><enum>(5)</enum><text>To reduce the arrests, incarcerations, and violent interactions between law enforcement and individuals that sometimes occur from inappropriate 911 emergency referrals.</text></paragraph></section><section id="idacab4ce0c8ef40e48a37da15a7e27d25"><enum>3.</enum><header>Allotments to strengthen nationwide accessibility and coordination of 211 and 988 services for information and referral for human services and mental health needs</header><subsection id="id34f31a95172d4adbb9b4b43cbb6ac98c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Out of amounts appropriated under section 4(a) that remain after application of section 4(b), the Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), acting through the Human Services National Board, shall make an allotment to each State, in accordance with the formula developed under subsection (b), to carry out a program for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="id9B3AB5E03E74482BB541CB1A47F18C0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensuring 211 and 988 services are directly accessible to all individuals in each State; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id78C91AADD23643DB89C2A9C432D1EFE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensuring capacity within each State for 988 services through the operational support of State designated crisis centers within the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline Network; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1FE4483A5B3B45C5A43DAF022B8D0852"><enum>(3)</enum><text>strengthening the reliability, accessibility, and responsiveness of methods of communication through 211 and 988 services, in order to provide information and referrals with respect to human services provided through the respective 211 or 988 services, including mental health emergency resources and suicide prevention resources provided through 988 services, homelessness resources, domestic violence resources, resources to identify and address child, adult, and elder abuse and exploitation, caregiver and child care resources, and other human service needs provided through 211 services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id84F1CD66B0C44886BD54031C7AF986C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>reducing law enforcement interactions with people with disabilities and individuals experiencing human-services or mental health needs, and increasing the capacity to divert calls from 911 or police departments to mental health and human services responders, as appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id129be9bd941a48c98017cc46e4f57dc3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allotments to States</header><paragraph id="idB44D8783E9544737A997FDAF389C965F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of making allotments under this section, the Secretary shall develop a formula for determining the allotment amounts for each State. Such formula shall be based on population, population density, poverty rate, and other evidence-based predictive data related to the needs of the State for, and access to, mental health and other human services. Allotments made under this section, and the services provided through such allotments, shall not supplant funding otherwise made available to the State for such purposes, or services otherwise provided by the State for such purposes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida6bcaea9a390494f9a7252b2cd444fc3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-Federal contributions</header><text>A State may not be eligible for an allotment under this section unless the State ensures that at least 25 percent of the resources of the program funded by the State allotment will be derived from non-Federal sources, which may include in-kind contributions of goods or services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idDEDA2FED40484C43850108F0E7D7C68D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirement regarding State allotment amounts</header><text>Of the amounts allotted to a State under this section, not more than 15 percent shall be allocated for evaluation, training, and technical assistance, and for management and administration of subgrants awarded under this section. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id24945EBE9CBD4D19A9DAC66E3458257C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>From the allotment made to a State under this subsection, the State Human Services Collaborative may retain the greater of <fraction>1/2</fraction> of 1 percent of such allotment or $50,000, for administrative costs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida0abbf8c526f43b7975098ba2f5e396d"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Human Services National Board</header><paragraph id="id79abd091240d47b09c4ac66a732118bc"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a Human Services National Board for purposes of—</text><subparagraph id="id77AA532D07CD45EA949A5B23184DAF0F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>managing and allocating funds under this section, including making allotments to States; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1B284374BAFA426489D1F713CF2EF719"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reviewing State plans for implementing and maintaining 211 systems and coordinating the 211 and 988 systems; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3EC634468DA8456C98897703300EA457"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evaluating State 211 and 988 systems, including with respect to capacity for answering and responding to calls; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1CB29710DD694FD68C75D08D23C0AA60"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evaluating the coordination and collaboration among 211, 988, and 911 services and other emergency and call center systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idc662ef3fe6534421b911d671057e44b2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><subparagraph id="id4AA38FA7C4DB4613A48BFDB17257C491"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Human Services National Board shall be comprised of not fewer than 19 members selected by the Secretary in accordance with subparagraph (B), of which 11 shall be permanent members, and 8 shall serve 3-year, rotating terms.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2b00cfc0c14a498cab013a25cfc8d8b6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Members</header><clause id="id513077226F80477CA69D54D1EC004557"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Permanent members</header><text>The 11 permanent members shall be comprised of one representative from each of—</text><subclause id="idcaf0bdfe35704dccbb66cec1752c1d8a"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Alliance of Information and Referral Systems;</text></subclause><subclause id="id3f98e57f6f9546f79ce895570ae93d6e"><enum>(II)</enum><text>United Way Worldwide;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide3faa36f6090463b90aa58290a595928"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the National Council on Independent Living;</text></subclause><subclause id="ida3b69e02405a48df9af968e57372bf6c"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the National Association of Area Agencies on Aging;</text></subclause><subclause id="id54429624c49d4fd08b5f5ecb7877d19e"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the Bazelon Center for Mental Health Law;</text></subclause><subclause id="id2D9BFCFE0EE2463199750195ECB95036"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights; </text></subclause><subclause id="id269ea4cc4e0e4317b00de88e007494d2"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the National Alliance to End Homelessness;</text></subclause><subclause id="id21178187AF484F68BFF19C34AE4DCD42"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>the Fraternal Order of Police;</text></subclause><subclause id="idC11EC78F461F46D4AB252D8A779B46B5"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline;</text></subclause><subclause id="id76E563D29CB0478299A76963FF06F9DD"><enum>(X)</enum><text>the National Domestic Violence Hotline; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id812F84D8C6C14D94962D782CCB74B941"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>the National Emergency Number Association.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id6f8f787fb1cf43138b5e76cb0c0e521b"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rotating members</header><text>The 8 rotating members shall be selected by the Secretary, with input from stakeholders and advocates, and shall include—</text><subclause id="id9812fe1eea134d08977c1c20dca5a0df"><enum>(I)</enum><text>1 representative of a faith-based organization dedicated to providing human services;</text></subclause><subclause id="idacf8bc6e20744d8699d2f0a22c1f2c8c"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 representative of an organization dedicated to ensuring racial and ethnic equity;</text></subclause><subclause id="idb1666ff8dac94a9f97b973128ece659c"><enum>(III)</enum><text>1 representative of a disability organization operated by a majority of people with disabilities;</text></subclause><subclause id="id6338e0e457414745b9f6d246391c196b"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>1 representative of an organization representing older adults;</text></subclause><subclause id="id97ea3b500aa243d290b91862e3ade22c"><enum>(V)</enum><text>1 representative of an organization representing Tribal and Native peoples;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide9c5d53159574912a7752cccc133bc74"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>1 representative of an organization representing LGBTQ+ populations;</text></subclause><subclause id="idca06f457b34d46a2a17ef22fa771b06a"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>1 representative of a secular organization dedicated to providing human services; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idA449727CD3F9419CA4D3260E371C2DB9"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>1 representative of a law enforcement labor or representative organization.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id79d0546d1c564e84bd70c02023b38e3e"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Additional rotating members</header><text>In addition to the members appointed under clauses (i) and (ii), the Secretary may appoint to the Human Services National Board up to 4 additional rotating members to represent specific populations or issues. Each such member shall serve a 3-year term.</text></clause><clause id="id743c77a41d4848b6980dc37cf509d066"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Ex officio members</header><text>Ex officio members of the Human Services National Board shall include 1 representative from each of—</text><subclause id="idb99be362e0ec4f4eaabbfbbfd8e889cf"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></subclause><subclause id="id3af29413200545f8bf720471f90ad559"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Department of Education;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide6180ad3f8b148ea94e0fc719cc18e12"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security; </text></subclause><subclause id="id7b582a20064e47789c0dac5f5973eef9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the Department of Housing and Urban Development; </text></subclause><subclause id="idC3DBC50E2E0D4B0AA57E04A6AD9A0329"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the Department of Commerce; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id7B9599A003F042678120F7DDD8A87076"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the Department of Labor.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id29a1cbce6f4f42da8ee1a17b25394526"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fiscal agent</header><text>The Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall be the fiscal agent of the Human Services National Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd3215d5a51874343890bb9a11f653eaa"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chair and Vice Chair</header><subparagraph id="id0d71d59615894dc3957a04af9a94209a"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Chair selection</header><text>The Chair of the Human Services National Board shall be selected by the Human Services National Board members, from among the permanent members described in paragraph (2)(B)(i), and shall serve a 5-year term.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id27634009e2974c34be06a6251e68dff4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vice chair selection</header><text>The Vice Chair shall be selected by the Human Services National Board members, from among the rotating members described in paragraph (2)(B)(ii), and shall serve a 3-year term.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id22c55b25f6d34ebe90d12e8f08487a4f"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State oversight entities</header><paragraph id="id1d75e8e820e948a9b7bc8a8590cd7717"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Human Services Collaboratives</header><subparagraph id="id6B22E47400724F16B6C22EDCE61E0982"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State seeking an allotment under this section, not later than 3 months after receiving an allotment, shall appoint a lead entity (referred to in this section as a <quote>Human Services Collaborative</quote>) for purposes of meeting the requirements of this subsection. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3767cd543f4e4c6d950b31c4d87bef8d"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Human Services Collaborative</header><text>A State lead entity shall be treated as the State Human Services Collaborative under this subsection if the entity—</text><clause id="id265e14b84e134aca9ee589c6295e2249"><enum>(i)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id474948BCF78C41B6B03B0EB2ADB1C39A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is a State entity or an independently incorporated nonprofit organization serving as the lead implementing agency coordinating and managing State and regional projects and operations for 211 in the State—</text><item id="id5D12CABEF66D46DD914160EA54FAB0CB" indent="up1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>under State law; or</text></item><item indent="up1" id="id0B74C87388EF479BB08B4E9AC4ABC992"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by order of the State public utility commission;</text></item></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="idF9259E94708C41EDA6418341740B4E78"><enum>(II)</enum><text>collaborates, to the extent practicable, with the entities listed in clause (ii); and</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="idE4C355D136E54B1AB79C837088C0AA31"><enum>(III)</enum><text>collaborates with the Administrator of the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline to coordinate 988 operations with 211 operations in the State; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idbdf49813b24c4f199ab0196e98c5cbc7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a collaborative entity established by the State for such purpose from among representatives of—</text><subclause id="id395f17d75645420490c953f09652ba8d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an informal, existing 211 statewide collaborative in the State;</text></subclause><subclause id="id4790250CF5CF45E195716373CF4296A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>crisis centers within the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline Network operating in the State;</text></subclause><subclause id="id496ccd89fc724fc1a4ba86757d242b8f"><enum>(III)</enum><text>State agencies; </text></subclause><subclause id="id169b0e27a09c4c1f82e6ccb0a63f7874"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>community-based organizations, including—</text><item id="id9e8c963560c543a289b73e94e14cdf13"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>organizations representing older adults;</text></item><item id="id4f2dc18bb3b142e88559efb27279dcfd"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>organizations representing people with disabilities;</text></item><item id="id40c6bc7ae4b2457ea083217f9fc2fb7c"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>where appropriate, organizations representing Native peoples and Tribal nations;</text></item><item id="id9ff913d976e04469931c0fc8774f399b"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>organizations representing people with mental health disabilities; and</text></item><item id="ida17fe5f6fd9e46caadd00e41e7b73fbb"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>organizations led by Black people, indigenous people, or people of color working to end racism;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="id8e49543a3e7444aa906f43fe99c39ff2"><enum>(V)</enum><text>faith-based organizations dedicated to providing human services;</text></subclause><subclause id="idfe1564e02d2542b5ac705cfbead794fa"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>nonprofit organizations providing human services;</text></subclause><subclause id="id606abc5275b144bc90252e456d5cbea7"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>comprehensive and specialized information and referral providers, including area agencies on aging, aging and disability resource centers, and 211 and 988 call centers;</text></subclause><subclause id="id842454d3291049b48d3fb3bf028f91b9"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>State and regional foundations; </text></subclause><subclause id="id6657eec6bc384479b4ceaca2cd11d503"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>businesses headquartered in, or with significant presence in, the State; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id4D0326612FFF49FE8A80B3FA78FD0A36"><enum>(X)</enum><text>law enforcement labor or representative organizations representing rank and file officers.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id82d2bc82bcb8455aa61b71bbc242c7a7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Human Services State Oversight Council</header><subparagraph id="id12E631A55D87482D998BE3E569EDEC34"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State receiving an allotment under this section shall establish a Human Services State Oversight Council (referred to in this section as a <quote>Council</quote>) to provide guidance and oversight of the 211 and 988 systems to the State Human Services Collaborative. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idFBE760B6052E49DFB5304995D4CDF791"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Members</header><clause id="id1c68da15881749b2bd4cb388f433244a"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each Council shall be comprised of not more than 25 stakeholders and service providers appointed by the governor of the State for staggered 3-year terms, including—</text><subclause id="idafd1ae2f4978492691f14056fc7748ce"><enum>(I)</enum><text>at least 3 representatives of human service providers;</text></subclause><subclause id="id877367cfc664436e9cf95338b3fd98cb"><enum>(II)</enum><text>at least 2 older adults;</text></subclause><subclause id="id57172f7362e54c2caae9cab2f447a1ed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>at least 3 people with disabilities;</text></subclause><subclause id="idbcdb550e608c49f0811742cc3d4036a5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>at least 3 additional people with mental health disabilities;</text></subclause><subclause id="idb3a5921d214742e2b16aa802c9d1a48e"><enum>(V)</enum><text>at least 1 individual with a child under 18 years of age;</text></subclause><subclause id="id3AAD5D1882AE48FD87FA5DD9216E35D1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>at least 1 individual caring for an older adult;</text></subclause><subclause id="idF25D1EFB347B4B74B719483A683638DD"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>at least 1 individual providing support for a relative with a disability; </text></subclause><subclause id="id386154d9555e4de88f4ad8c28d07cbcb"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>at least 3 individuals who are members of a family that receives means tested Federal benefits, such as temporary assistance for needy families under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>), the supplemental nutrition assistance program established under the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2011">7 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>), or the supplemental security income program established under title XVI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1381">42 U.S.C. 1381 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="idabf05b3e8f1c49ed9bc17cbb3bfd1173"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>at least 1 business representative; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id463260476E80480AA22C8CA72300F0E8"><enum>(X)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of a law enforcement labor or representative organization.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idC33152155CBD4DD98A61DBDFB2228305"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Conflicts of interest</header><text>No Council member may be an employee of an entity that receives a subgrant from the State Human Services Collaborative.</text></clause><clause id="id873e68ac5b824850a4be12e0f75d1153"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Chair and Vice Chair</header><text>With respect to each Council, the Council shall select from among its members a Chair, who shall be a recipient of human services, and a Vice Chair, who shall be a provider of human services or a business representative. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf9ea6a708dbb48f19cb9ef83b6293e7f"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>Each Council shall be responsible for—</text><clause id="ide847b807217f453e945377b6951f3671"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reviewing the annual State application to the Human Services National Board;</text></clause><clause id="idcd26304fe292408a9e0bd5d7885825e4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reviewing the annual Human Services Collaborative budget;</text></clause><clause id="id9085e56b6db74b7e8b930b5629c3a86d"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifying topics for, and ensuring an evaluation of, the State 211 and 988 services, consistent with subsection (h)(2);</text></clause><clause id="id7acfa2a3aa584473bd20a41d8aa3ac93"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>monitoring the State 211 and 988 services to ensure that such services are racially equitable; and</text></clause><clause id="ide47767da781e480dacbb958a09cdce22"><enum>(v)</enum><text>making recommendations to increase the awareness and effectiveness of 211 and 988 services in all parts and communities of the State.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idab58a2a92d2b415da55bff8c2bedeb94"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Human Services Collaborative of a State, on behalf of each State seeking an allocation under this section, acting under the direction of the State governor, shall submit an annual application to the Human Services National Board for such an allocation, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including the following:</text><paragraph id="id5dac679d7a064b809909e545132a2f4d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of how the Human Services Collaborative will—</text><subparagraph id="idC1F51EF5A40948518D9652561A02CE55"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that every resident of the State with phone or internet service can connect to the 211 and 988 services at no charge; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id26AF93DE3B0543A4ADAE99963A0AEDE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make available, throughout the State, 211 and 988 service information and referral with respect to human services, including information about the manner in which the Human Services Collaborative will develop, sustain, and evaluate the State's 211 and 988 services and ensure sufficient State capacity for answering and responding to calls to 211 and 988;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCBB56D32CB1D4EFD905C87F1AFB7989E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordinate with 911 systems and law enforcement agencies to divert calls to mental health and human services responders who can assist individuals and link individuals with voluntary, community-based services, as appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7aed3f0966c049018c4b76553c7cc76e"><enum>(D)</enum><text>use annual 211 and 988 operational data to inform the Collaborative's approach to assessing the program and establishing oversight metrics. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf58c5ac865af45cba856a54a30a27dd7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Information on the sources of funding and other resources for the State 211 and 988 services for purposes of meeting the requirements under subsection (b)(2). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide9a47c5e39104e0c97bd4d01f0b557fe"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Information describing how the Human Services Collaborative will provide to all individuals in the State, to the extent practicable, a statewide database available via the internet, that will allow such individuals to search for programs or services that are available from mental health and human services providers in the State. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id25b217656fef468c85ba71dd0f39fe3a"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Assurances that all activities and information provided by the 211 and 988 services and all entities receiving subgrants pursuant to this section will be directly accessible according to the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>), section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>), and part 1194 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id13d9e7b8115b4a398d485c396db3bdfe"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any additional information the Secretary may require. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idce300272ba4349c2a23342c865af6e75"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><paragraph id="id5a82678380074723834c2cffe0ba8ebc"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>For purposes of carrying out a program in a State, the State Human Services Collaborative may make subgrants to such entities as the Collaborative determines appropriate, which may include subgrants to provide funds—</text><subparagraph id="idd0c40a6205a94ab6a6b7511e06433b20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the provision of 211 and 988 services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id72834bdfb4dd42c397d0912a9155efa4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the operation and maintenance of 211 and 988 call centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id83400f9bd58a459bbdd8ab3a1467e9b6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for the collection and display of information in the statewide database;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ideb3a8f39213f40a892f84537d9296347"><enum>(D)</enum><text>for increasing public awareness of 211 and 988 services in the State in collaboration with 911 services and other emergency call centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0d2a6e6f7f2d4d09a0e6339a703c1318"><enum>(E)</enum><text>for coordination of the State’s 211 and 988 services, including the collection, accessibility, and display of information through a national data platform; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb654fc4fbdd1494183cbbec6217d841d"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to conduct statewide and regional planning for 211 and 988 services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0c8c00ef6e2b466d90636e71fc3aaf56"><enum>(G)</enum><text>for start-up costs of extending 211 and 988 services to unserved areas, including costs of software and hardware upgrades and telecommunications and internet costs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id66f73d294ef54c00a0da464df42860f1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>to ensure that 211 and 988 services are directly accessible, consistent with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>), section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>), and part 1194 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6ff6a234267542e49e50c17b4de69094"><enum>(I)</enum><text>for staffing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2900f75f46c345cb8b8e4a04549ee6e6"><enum>(J)</enum><text>for training;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id18fca7cdffa8408e82200b88f4c55d3a"><enum>(K)</enum><text>for activities related to accreditation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf7a78ab9fbfd4d138704d61c4179493b"><enum>(L)</enum><text>for the evaluation of State 211 and 988 activities and capacity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idedd261fbef9a4e33a7ebace31527a1d0"><enum>(M)</enum><text>for internet hosting and site development and maintenance for a statewide database;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id083e7792c9a6428794281a38dd1eb3a3"><enum>(N)</enum><text>for cloud-based data and messaging capacity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd7f169703f5c4be98300e6d690b9fdfc"><enum>(O)</enum><text>to encourage coordination and collaboration of 211 and 988 services within the State and ensure coordination and collaboration with local 911 Public Safety Answering Points;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf23ce715dd484934a348e58bb24682a9"><enum>(P)</enum><text>to integrate or share resources and service-level data with national platforms hosted by the Human Services National Board;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idedd8a20231b44597b3049dde480b30aa"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>to prepare and submit State and national reporting requirements and other activities approved by the Human Services State Oversight Council; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id73d35d6715474bd9aa63044ada450f36"><enum>(R)</enum><text>to provide stipends and travel reimbursement for individuals with disabilities and their family members for costs associated with serving on the Human Services State Oversight Council; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0E34D55D3C5B42E0974C875A498F67B7"><enum>(S)</enum><text>to carry out other activities approved by the Human Services National Board on behalf of the Secretary. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idaa30fa594a9649f7a46711a151ca1c2c"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In awarding a subgrant under this subsection, a lead entity shall consider—</text><subparagraph id="ide7b7d15b99d14563acb02f89f17df99e"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the ability of the entity seeking the subgrant to carry out activities or provide services consistent with this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7877c8a17a984d07acadbc73e989c0f0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the extent to which the award of the subgrant will facilitate equitable geographic distribution of subgrants under this section to ensure that rural communities have access to 211 and 988 services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6a8ad1461be746199f739202ee035832"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the extent to which the recipient of the subgrant will establish and maintain cooperative relationships with specialized information and referral centers, including Child Care Resource and Referral Agencies, crisis centers, referral agencies for aging or disability services, 911 call centers, 311 call centers, and other call centers, as applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idDDD49DB709404A889F05071D942BF031"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In awarding a subgrant under this subsection, a lead entity shall give preference to organizations that work with people with disabilities who are Black, Indigenous, or other people of color. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id5f667ee3ab0045d6a993e34e8a56310c"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Use of State allotment and subgrant amounts</header><paragraph id="id57a3b4dfa7da4052bdc5ee4d4fc6e0d1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts awarded as State allotments or subgrants under this section shall be used solely for either or both of the following purposes:</text><subparagraph id="idB929954FEBF34C49A952A21B0710A42B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To make available 211 and 988 services to all individuals in a State via voice, short message service or other messaging, internet, or other telecommunication methods.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idBF8F5A96AB3A47528F9565134AC9F32E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For community information and referral with respect to human services, among individuals, families, and agencies seeking such services and the providers of such services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id8715e4ece30a49e0a7dcc6036a0f8ede"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In making 211 and 988 services available, the recipient of a State allotment or subgrant shall, to the maximum extent practicable—</text><subparagraph id="id244212426ff344c7a01c9903b8a045ac"><enum>(A)</enum><text>abide by the Key Standards for 211 Centers as specified in the Standards and Quality Indicators for Professional Information and Referral published by the Alliance of Information and Referral Systems for 211 services; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7DCB81634295418EB198F1EF48AF6D12"><enum>(B)</enum><text>abide by the clinical standards and guidelines specified by the Administrator of the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline for 988 crisis centers that are part of the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline Network; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id26a589e391b64a9ea19c700f959f1242"><enum>(C)</enum><text>collaborate with public and private human services organizations and existing national, regional, and local information and referral systems to provide an exhaustive and comprehensive database of services from which to provide information or referrals to individuals using the 211 and 988 services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idcd87ed0d28cd4ee5af59997137ec7ae8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of subgrant funds</header><text>Amounts awarded through a subgrant under subsection (f) may be used by the subgrant recipient for the purposes described in subsection (f)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id4a49246d5d7648b186662e6d8d055fc3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports and evaluations</header><paragraph id="idF13B28D7800B4C8296D04990933A81CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>The State Human Services Collaborative of each State receiving an allotment under this section shall submit to the Human Services National Board, not later than 60 days after the end of each fiscal year in which such allotment is made, a report on the program funded by the State allotment. Each report shall—</text><subparagraph id="id4a9806c4f61f4ecc86e5bd20e11f1918"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describe the activities or services funded by the State allotment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7976faa5dfc643879a5560c3bbdb2017"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assess the effectiveness of such activities and services in making available, to all residents of the State, 211 and 988 services for emergency mental health services and information and referrals with respect to human services in accordance with the provisions of this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4c94c19cc5964b1786f6cf8bf2786b08"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assess the effectiveness of collaboration with human services resource and referral entities and service providers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id21AD5EA95EB84AB29106A41EC731EE54"><enum>(D)</enum><text>include the percentage of calls to 911 or to police that were diverted to mental health and other human services responders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddd7e485137fb4589beb8e84883398fb4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>describe the services to which individuals were linked through the 211 and 988 services and any efforts to track outcomes. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id75268d83ba894c668c8ff7c129572edf"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Each State Human Services Collaborative shall award a contract to an independent entity to conduct an evaluation of the State 211 and 988 systems biennially. The evaluation shall address—</text><subparagraph id="id4b356cc429db4012b28c0de99309982e"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any barriers to access to the State 211 and 988 services for residents and visitors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5D44E09101D849CAB5696E7546D047B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the State 211 and 988 services at connecting residents to needed human services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7acd8b259a6a4c77a0f02b78f8eccb65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the effectiveness of collaborations among 211 and 988 partners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf0874721b7084f69a0b4947eedc0bbbc"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the effects of the State 211 and 988 services on 911 law enforcement, fire, and medical emergency services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide2c731fe0a1b44dd844dacedfc62f26d"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the comprehensiveness of the information in the State 211 and 988 database;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf196c486c8c74413bed891a3ed87d1bf"><enum>(F)</enum><text>public awareness of the State 211 and 988 services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id351df4f88eca4f678fd9983643adc8a9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>user satisfaction with the State 211 and 988 services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3b98c8f978694687af1175838f98ba9f"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other topics identified by the Human Services State Oversight Councils.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id552ee0f4e21b4f29aa72088a711f4723"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id661a24b49d654ade9db59574e194d174"><enum>(1)</enum><header>211 service</header><text>The term <term>211 service</term> means providing residents with information and referrals, via voice telephone, text telephone, short message service, text, internet phone, or other telecommunication methods, with respect to health and human services and other provider agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0AB8AA67CDE94996ABC65809BECE320F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>988 service</header><text>The term <term>988 service</term> means the provision of mental health or suicide crisis support and resources through the universal telephone number within the United States designated for the purpose of the national suicide prevention and mental health crisis hotline system operating through the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida2f4779372184627bade374b02443612"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Human services</header><text>The term <term>human services</term> means services that—</text><subparagraph id="ide402243dc6cc483caea98a7dd91fbfff"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assist individuals in becoming more self-sufficient, in preventing dependency, and in strengthening family relationships; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id09c6262eee084df9aa06c1c3c3a626b8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>address social determinants of health;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id05056A57F7E047CBA6FDF4092EA97884"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support personal and social development; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6d7fb0463b564374a2c5d887f84640ca"><enum>(D)</enum><text>help ensure the health and well-being of individuals, families, and communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idF86493D9BC8E4920841C830E6C38DBB3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian Tribe; Tribal organization</header><text>The terms <term>Indian tribe</term> and <term>tribal organization</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfd8c51c671c8449dbfda4ab869162b64"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Older adult</header><text>The term <term>older adult</term> has the meaning given the term <term>older individual</term> in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id938d906609f24aca8374fac3f00d802e"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, or an Indian tribe or tribal organization.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idc6806a6bbee543aaaef430b5acb8ff0c"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="ida0061ff47fdd459f93adc4d3b87d317f"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act—</text><paragraph id="idCFA760EFEEC743BAA21C2C2231AEFF79"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$550,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025, of which, each such fiscal year, $350,000,000 shall be allocated for 211 services and $200,000,000 shall be allocated for 988 services; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD85BD37826E643EE81F10F150E95D6A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$450,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2026 through 2030, of which, each such fiscal year, $300,000,000 shall be allocated for 211 services and $150,000,000 shall be allocated for 988 services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id2a21146ba841493ba1c957ec20aedc69"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>Of the amount appropriated under this section for a fiscal year, the Human Services National Board may reserve <fraction>1/2</fraction> of 1 percent for administrative and national coordinating activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="id5eaea77136d54bcaabdb12fe31859a9e"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts appropriated pursuant to this section shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

