<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-DAV23A92-66V-MH-H3V"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1966 IS: Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1966</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S366">Ms. Warren</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S313">Mr. Sanders</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S361">Ms. Hirono</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend title 10, United States Code, to increase transparency and reporting on sexual violence in the Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id76e3b63c642b4d19a552e56e33bc633a"><enum>2.</enum><header>JROTC program certification</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2031 of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddfc45a9ef25f40d98f84f7387efff2db"><subsection id="id9674d1a5dca448ae829a11c1461cfbb5"><enum>(i)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="idb309378857d246e09225035c1ddd0162"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense shall permanently suspend any Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps unit that fails to notify the Department of Defense and the Department of Education of allegations that an instructor sexually harassed or assaulted a student participating in the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps within 48 hours after the institution is notified of the allegation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3183d2e932f446fc87bbf1aad45d6d45" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate and the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives an annual report including information on units suspended pursuant to this subsection and a justification for the reinstatement of any such unit.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="ida659607e591b4adb9c2b1ccf7f42c5d5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Defense climate surveys</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 481 of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="id70386f5462bb403bb83fb173ad9fc2f6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="idca24b8e012d5469eafa74e20e56bfe7a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>four surveys</quote> and inserting <quote>five surveys</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id992749169411467abb61b192ad7fecea"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="id87d052f8f2d44ccf811f3898e1f4576b"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>four surveys</quote> and inserting <quote>five surveys</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="idb849953563994ace8a4c69da31010cf5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id825f5fb7cdbc46c3a59c6ce9ad507be2"><subparagraph id="ida4efbdcaff894f949f6f6ced97b93399" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To identify and assess gender issues and discrimination among members of the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps and the Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id00b5593b105e4d3aaac4174b99e41673" indent="up1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>To identify and assess disability issues and discrimination among members of the Armed Forces serving on active duty.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4ca5aa97ae24419882c73b30b84138ff" indent="up1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>To identify and assess disability issues and discrimination among members of the Armed Forces serving in the reserve components.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0b8d26e5161f4ae5b36d4a50bc812d27" indent="up1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>To identify and assess racial and ethnic issues and discrimination among members of the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps and the Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc00f006c0ba349b7a20b530c0bc0712d" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>To identify and assess disability issues and discrimination among members of the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps and the Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb1a7272cfcd9423dafd9fa058aca6d23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e), by inserting <quote>and publish on a publicly accessible website of the Department</quote> after <quote>the Secretary shall submit to Congress</quote>. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9acf31c242f5420fbc830768fed2be3c"><enum>4.</enum><header>Program inspections</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2031(b) of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="id23d897062dcd41b58cbc62ceb89cb315"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5785ca6046d04c5c8b9323a15e6ebd24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (5) as paragraph (8); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id44d1a114f65b41e19c1a4d36e0534361"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (4) the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2f74982d1f1f44c58d83ff0d55ee4140"><paragraph id="idd3cf7618c602433abf660f169d985330"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the institution has been inspected and approved by the military department concerned in the previous 18 months;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id56b78d3d88c24861ac6ab1d48f95b9ef"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the military department concerned certifies that—</text><subparagraph id="id82aea63d28cb4f83b1bb6b6d689a23c0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the institution—</text><clause id="idc85b884c1c7b4f2d84abb1844f1a3ee2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has created a process for students to report violations of their rights under title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>), and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), including the rights of students to not be subject to discrimination or subject to retaliation for reporting a violation of those laws; and</text></clause><clause id="id9fff3699709e475995d85e04a3fad015"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has notified the students and instructors of those rights and the process for reporting violations of those rights, including information on available reporting options, including mandatory reporters, and available supportive measures to ensure students have access to any accommodations needed in the aftermath of experiencing discrimination; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id05dfa025c2e4402e85d17f1e920f832f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the unit includes biannual training to inform students of methods to prevent, respond to, and report sexual assault and harassment;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7061c39af9a74cb2894f97a1c3a2e2bc"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the institution agrees to report all allegations of violations described under paragraph (6)(A) to the military department concerned and the Department of Education’s Office for Civil Rights not less than annually; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="idd935a2eedd4a49b98a7026fef8cf649b"><enum>5.</enum><header>Annual report on allegations of discrimination and sex-based harassment in JROTC programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2031 of title 10, United States Code, as amended by section 2 of this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idffa58fa82d1c4bb7b824ecf7848d8050"><subsection id="id2b4da6bf17f240bdb4a55455920bc550"><enum>(j)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="iddfa3b732ce8d4664b074ba4da852d15c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than March 31 each year, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Education shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on allegations of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking) and discriminatory harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy, and related medical conditions in all JROTC programs during the preceding year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id569b19b3e1c24617a3fd0b37ac59fcdb" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each report required under paragraph (1) shall set forth the following:</text><subparagraph id="idad6b95beeac846be981fbdc1fe3ab6de"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of reported allegations of a possible violation under title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>) in school-affiliated JROTC programs, including—</text><clause id="ide18eff84669b42338f7fe0681c62654e"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of such reported allegations that were investigated;</text></clause><clause id="id833491eecbe94b1e802f307cf41b5ec0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the outcome of those investigations;</text></clause><clause id="id3b8db2f695804a4fa51e132f19207ec8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of allegations the Department of Defense, military services, or Department of Education received directly from students or third parties, including whether the individual making the report raised concerns that the institution had not properly investigated the incident or reported it to proper authorities within and outside of the school on any initial allegation that was reported to the institution; and</text></clause><clause id="idecb9457033704d2d8d0295a0f7dbe616"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the number of such reported allegations by State, including the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, Northern Mariana Islands, and United States Virgin Islands, in which these reports occurred.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8392e5c2a731460ea618cfa9808cd974"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of reports that the Department of Defense, military services, or Department of Education have received during the reporting period involving allegations of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, by instructors against students in the JROTC program, including— </text><clause id="ide43e7a9abbf049e2bf8ba2fdc59c3f69"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the type of incident;</text></clause><clause id="idb698f50ae0584aec85a583b640487819"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the military service;</text></clause><clause id="ideff755ce731c4cfea69585d965560428"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of instructors and number of allegations they each received;</text></clause><clause id="idb1b08293c62b479c8ef7d66d88b39733"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the number of reports of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, that have been investigated;</text></clause><clause id="id30c1c754bdbc484694b08575e93c4208"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the number of reports or investigations that have led to the removal of instructors from JROTC programs;</text></clause><clause id="id9eaffe6a9d6d49ffa6871950db9a0ab7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the number of allegations the Department of Defense received directly from students or third parties, including whether the individual making the report raised concerns the institution had not properly investigated the incident or reported it to proper authorities within and outside of the school on any initial allegation that was reported to the institution; and</text></clause><clause id="idaa9eb77ba1894ac9865d56fe329d164e"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the number of such reported allegations by State, including the District of Columbia, in which these reports occurred.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id27c11d93a3114fbe8153c97c9d24b8a9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of reports that the Department of Defense, military services, or Department of Education have received during the reporting period involving allegations of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy, and related medical conditions, by students against students in the JROTC program, including—</text><clause id="iddd9186fba56a4dc5b8b71a3d2395ac3c"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the type of incident;</text></clause><clause id="id81ae80b91bed4f05bb47c10ae3ba3f49"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the military service;</text></clause><clause id="idcdeba64d22824c7f8aee4a31ddecb368"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of students who were alleged to have committed such acts and the number of allegations that each student received;</text></clause><clause id="idf55b3ecb840b4934b55a0952fa7d29af"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the number of reports of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, that have been investigated;</text></clause><clause id="id604c8e96c15d49d8bbc7677ac640d8e6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the number of reports or investigations that have led to the removal of students who were alleged to have committed such acts or students who were alleged victims of those acts from the JROTC program;</text></clause><clause id="ide7cc88ae6ae04d048dd5862b3fac98a6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the number of allegations the Department of Defense or Department of Education received directly from students or third parties, including whether the individual making the report raised concerns the institution had not properly investigated the incident or reported it to proper authorities within and outside of the school on any initial allegation that was reported to the institution; and</text></clause><clause id="id29581919e8684afeb0ed5873ac74f806"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the number of such reported allegations by State, including the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, Northern Mariana Islands, and United States Virgin Islands in which these reports occurred.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4cc5102d87d24c019c4ce338b1d3285c"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any steps the Department of Defense and the Department of Education have taken to mitigate sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking) in JROTC programs during the preceding year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id552548d7190e43d4a85a2b9bfe92a82a" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Each report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form and may not be marked as controlled unclassified information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida6a04ad19a9c4c8f832cea512279ab4b" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Each secondary school (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7081">20 U.S.C. 7081</external-xref>)) participating in the JROTC program under this chapter that receives funding under title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 shall develop and submit to the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Education for inclusion in the report required under paragraph (1) a statement of policy regarding—</text><subparagraph id="idf50b8167a8604798b7ebe57ed0d02978"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the secondary school’s programs to prevent sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7e75a47ceb8e42d89ef60e2fa07f5500"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the JROTC program’s provision of evidence-based training to JROTC recruits, in coordination with school-based mental health services providers as defined in section 4102(6) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7012">20 U.S.C. 7012(6)</external-xref>), if applicable, regarding—</text><clause id="id556145b732aa45189c1164bb4c13a0aa"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the mental health resources and services made available to them;</text></clause><clause id="id333dca5e0df04c2eb62a720c8976ec91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>mental health education; and</text></clause><clause id="id002a04367d04445192a28826868980fa"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>methods that students can use to seek help for themselves and others, including for sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idac9d7cc3a209478b89ad6f84b6d4866f"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the procedures that the secondary school will follow once an allegation of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, or other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, has been reported, including a statement of the standard of evidence that will be used during any school conduct proceeding arising from the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id07037346b7b74d6bae3395ac6237f73d" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Education shall annually report to the authorizing committees regarding compliance with this subsection by the JROTC program, including an up-to-date report on the Secretary’s monitoring of such compliance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd51307dd60e14cdfa826d02574d691be" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="idbe51b6718b5644b1977688d6c6256e54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Education shall seek the advice and counsel of the Attorney General concerning the development and dissemination to the JROTC program of best practices information about campus safety and emergencies related to sexual misconduct.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id882de4ed695849808bcdc47bb30b886d" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Education shall seek the advice and counsel of the Attorney General and the Secretary of Health and Human Services concerning the development and dissemination to the JROTC program of best practices information about preventing and responding to incidents of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, including elements of institutional policies that have proven successful based on evidence-based outcome measurements. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idcd588cf0b7764485b37dfd33c8ce9f69" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id99678c58f1d74bd68c2780a9a80fdc77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>No officer, employee, or agent of an institution participating in any program under this chapter shall retaliate, intimidate, threaten, coerce, or otherwise discriminate against any individual for exercising their rights or responsibilities under any provision of this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id717e3569db5040ee9b160a15a7ed47b1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each report required under paragraph (1) shall include all reported incidents of retaliation against reporters of the key prohibitions outlined in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idaa1afcab2e4245d98fb75dbc8c2fe208"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Each individual who exercised their rights or responsibilities to report under any provision in this subsection shall be offered mental health assistance from a school-based mental health services provider as defined in section 4102(6) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4E679631951343FE8F1FA3FD877BFA7D" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In this subsection, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id980325017F024F01BB933CC9B7990231"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0DCD9A1F0B9B4A38A2ABE2A09DDF3D5A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="id4c6aaf98e06e41bbbf2abd6c795d9611"><enum>6.</enum><header>Informed consent</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id846b3eea412942168a0190b5f8143c8d"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Informed consent requirement</header><text>Section 2031 of title 10, United States Code, as amended by section 5 of this Act, is further amended by inserting after subsection (j) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="id4399B31527394E1883108B57F7222409" style="OLC" act-name=""><subsection id="id83631E87E9FC45BFAF0A4499A2B0CE39"><enum>(k)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id1c9bdb284d324b3faef001364596485b"><enum>(1)</enum><text>No student shall be enrolled in the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps without the full and informed consent of both the student and the student's legal guardian. Students and legal guardians shall be notified of the voluntary nature of the program, process for disenrolling from the program, and the program’s requirements, including academic and physical expectations for students.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id820361c7d39a4cb4b5cc86a1cc58ed20" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall suspend any Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps unit found to have violated the full and informed consent requirement under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id33a7799e5a5b4177bdf8fa08e7e855eb"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, develop and implement a plan to collect affirmative, informed consent from students and their legal guardians before enrollment in the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps, as required by subsection (k) of section 2031 of title 10, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="idf952f1dcb74e4e1ca8ee6c7894130b7b"><enum>7.</enum><header>Comptroller General review</header><subsection id="idd00b108bfc91405c90b544cbf9cc663c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on efforts to increase transparency and reporting on sexual violence in the Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps Program.</text></subsection><subsection id="id7e7566000b0c47339d62c98680d13e50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include a description of the following:</text><paragraph id="id15ff344050284180bb66c27f9d982432"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The implementation of section 2031 of title 10, United States Code, as amended by sections 2, 4, 5, and 6 of this Act, and subparagraph (E) of section 481(a)(2) of title 10, United States Code, as added by section 3 of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcb0cbf7684b14fdebf0c105b3e165d64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The adequacy of the Department of Defense’s vetting process for Junior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps instructors in preventing individuals who engage in harassment from becoming JROTC instructors and an analysis of whether any additional needed components of the vetting process.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id62a3cd89c39443e9b5f0a8df3fa9a9c6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Department of Defense and the Department of Education’s oversight of compliance of units with respect to title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>), and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/701">29 U.S.C. 701 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4ea420a7965746eab85424e329dd885c"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any changes in the number of incidents of sex-based harassment (including sexual harassment, sexual assault, domestic violence, dating violence, and stalking), harassment based on disability, race, color, national origin, and other sex-based harassment, including sexual orientation, gender identity, transgender status, pregnancy and related medical conditions, reported to institutions or law enforcement agencies or reported in the climate surveys pursuant to subparagraph (E) of section 481(a)(2) of title 10, United States Code, as added by section 3 of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id81f5f159f22643b48ca1b2f16a0aa347"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The sufficiency of military department unit inspections.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id173cb1ddbd4c48f48dc54686ab794e41"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><paragraph id="id19e796ed0aa4454186980b78d92b232c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id340a50bb45334bab91df9abb6dee34e7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

