<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BUR23425-60M-LL-DXK"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1619 IS: Disrupt Fentanyl Trafficking Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1619</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S376">Ms. Ernst</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S362">Mr. Kaine</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Defense to develop a strategy to counter fentanyl trafficking in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5eaa094e8e9a4338b2ff0e1e4200baed" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Disrupt Fentanyl Trafficking Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8fd69cbb5dcd45b7a237d411a976163f"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><subsection id="id160b4b42d47043e0ad6bd5053cf86fb7"><enum>(a)</enum><text>fentanyl trafficking across the borders of the United States, and the consequences of that trafficking, constitute an unprecedented, nontraditional, and long-term threat to the national security of the United States;</text></subsection><subsection id="id8ec87aef0e374fccaa2815deefc5a7d2"><enum>(b)</enum><text>transnational criminal organizations have established effective control over significant areas within Mexico, which has enabled the development of fentanyl production and trafficking infrastructure;</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idab57bf0b0dd044aaa87033ebb029f11c"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">combating fentanyl trafficking demands—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide53ff1c36fe645a1aa168da5a9b2e8ac"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improved interagency command, control, communications, and intelligence sharing to enhance the effectiveness of the interdiction of fentanyl at the borders of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6c5cbf36f6fb4dadb2f4ed8108b8ac47"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whole-of-government solutions comprised of an integrated and synchronized interagency organizational construct committed to dismantling the process of trafficking fentanyl from chemical precursor to production to delivery in the United States and enabling partner nations to do the same;</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id63ee7b641cf245d29573e630a8ecbde0"><enum>(d)</enum><text>it is within the national security interest of the United States for Federal, State, and local law enforcement agencies, the Department of Defense, the Department of State, other counter-drug agencies, and stakeholders to effectively communicate and that the failure of effective communication affects the prevention, interdiction, and prosecution of fentanyl trafficking and distribution into and within the United States; and </text></subsection><subsection id="id78b8ba0b6179422ea9ceab7cc9b632d3"><enum>(e)</enum><text>the United States must partner with Mexico and Canada to combat fentanyl trafficking through institution building, the dismantling of cartels, and seizures of fentanyl in Mexico, Canada, and intrastate transit zones. </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id37ab0ecc71a94591ba1158fdda28b92c"><enum>3.</enum><header>Development of strategy to counter fentanyl trafficking and report</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4d95551e74d54c86899d424422bec21c"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strategy</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idef72402e5f394829baacf2694f7ee8b3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in coordination with other Federal agencies as the Secretary considers appropriate, shall develop and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a strategy to use existing authorities, including the authorities under section 124 of title 10, United States Code, as appropriate, to target, disrupt, or degrade threats to the national security of the United States caused or exacerbated by fentanyl trafficking.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id45f1175675cf4d1ea664da32ce0300a7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall outline how the Secretary of Defense will—</text><subparagraph id="ide9117071552c44b0b980e468974b96d3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>leverage existing authorities regarding counterdrug and counter-transnational organized crime activities with a counter-fentanyl nexus to detect and monitor activities related to fentanyl trafficking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id79ad7b7fce8a4fb1a8d8594a3bd3a7ae"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support operations to counter fentanyl trafficking carried out by other Federal agencies, State, Tribal, and local law enforcement agencies, or foreign security forces;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id50343aac3aa14e5c9f1c369053be3895"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate efforts of the Department of Defense for the detection and monitoring of aerial, maritime, and surface traffic suspected of carrying fentanyl bound for the United States, including efforts to unify the use of technology, surveillance, and related resources across air, land, and maritime domains to counter fentanyl trafficking, including with respect to data collection, data processing, and integrating sensors across such domains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7a546febcfa14dc190ebe9d43a8e8de7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide military-unique capabilities to support activities by the United States Government and foreign security forces to detect and monitor the trafficking of fentanyl and precursor chemicals used in fentanyl production, consistent with section 284(b)(10) of title 10, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id46ca3b30eaf540fa862580a6b467e83f"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">leverage existing counterdrug and counter-transnational organized crime programs of the Department to counter fentanyl trafficking; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7338b93a39a44adda8a126a3c39706ac"><enum>(F)</enum><text>assess existing training programs of the Department and provide training for Federal, State, Tribal, and local law enforcement agencies conducted by special operations forces to counter fentanyl trafficking, consistent with section 284(b) of title 10, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3cf7caf416904d3f84005b721b93df10"><enum>(G)</enum><text>engage with foreign security forces to ensure the counterdrug and counter-transnational organized crime programs of the Department—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1f625034d0f54b1d8e2eaae9ff9656b0"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support efforts to counter fentanyl trafficking; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide95d95e601e84c568e772021d12bc3f5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build capacity to interdict fentanyl in foreign countries, including programs to train security forces in partner countries to counter fentanyl trafficking, including countering illicit flows of fentanyl precursors, consistent with sections 284(c) and 333 of title 10, United States Code; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idba7b454d9db445378ed0338cf596ecde"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use the North American Defense Ministerial and the bilateral defense working groups and bilateral military cooperation round tables with Canada and Mexico to increase domain awareness to detect and monitor fentanyl trafficking; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0075f92541ed4296ae2f1f5ba450f9a9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>evaluate existing policies, procedures, processes, and resources that affect the ability of the Department to counter fentanyl trafficking consistent with existing counterdrug and counter-transnational organized crime authorities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idefc7354e566048b98b2780e5b3cd97bb"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6fda8593dde64135aab817a1c42b5754"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Briefing</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the submission of the strategy required by paragraph (1), the Secretary shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the strategy and plans for its implementation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6203301f38654f5fbc6e6259c7bab97a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on law enforcement reimbursement</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on—</text><paragraph id="idec6adb5c7e0144c898050ed77c8b500f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any goods or services provided under section 1535 of title 31, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Economy Act</quote>), during the period beginning on January 1, 2010, and ending on the date on which the report is submitted, by the Department of Defense to Federal civilian law enforcement agencies for counterdrug and counter-transnational organized crime operations on the southern border of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide12840d9a2e944229b5eb2f8914eea90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any payments made for such goods or services under such section during such period.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id549562059cd14841ab098b278c285fca"><enum>4.</enum><header>Cooperation with Mexico</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf88584e54dfa4c549ceeeb0e76221ddf"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall seek to enhance cooperation with defense officials of the Government of Mexico to target, disrupt, and degrade transnational criminal organizations within Mexico that traffic fentanyl.</text></subsection><subsection id="id7a831624a3604fd794d7efa74d74b06f"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on enhanced security cooperation</header><paragraph id="id4434535d965348eb8b2649d4e74dba99"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on efforts to enhance cooperation with defense officials of the Government of Mexico specified in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1597cb939c4046e0b17f0ee679e95ce9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="idb8e292edcb2644dd8d87b77b2d002d6f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the impact of the efforts to enhance cooperation described in paragraph (1) on targeting, disrupting, and degrading fentanyl trafficking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3382852ca4da49578ab4e45952121a38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of limitations on such efforts, including limitations imposed by the Government of Mexico;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id29f89331e92f4de7b3458898e7ceb1f9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations by the Secretary on actions to further improve cooperation with defense officials of the Government of Mexico;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4bcfc3e7eb3a44d69cc6d9dc429edba4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations by the Secretary on actions of the Department of Defense to further improve the capabilities of the Government of Mexico to target, disrupt, and degrade fentanyl trafficking; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idaf22096a41db4fb8aad0fa4d2cf5dc68"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other matter the Secretary considers relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida2929a3ea55346bcb80a4cf0a14b5794"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) may be submitted in unclassified form but shall include a classified annex. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="ide83423ef3cf648e08a9f46eabb6dab48"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddba4775b418b48e3b2b4649507b29f36"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id597F0AF4125149188682F12A874FAE34"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id57E4EF89228C47D88C5450B7D313BE26" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4cee6ae70e074a8ea0dc84d0c9bae57b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fentanyl</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fentanyl</term> means fentanyl and any fentanyl-related substance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id10fbd354e2fd47e39db13f9ebe494f29"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fentanyl-related substance</header><text>The term <term>fentanyl-related substance</term>—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id99ed4c51efe24630956b5d4e9cebfe48"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any substance that is structurally related to fentanyl by 1 or more modifications of—</text><clause id="idf6bc7789533449b2bce6d631a176ef6d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>replacement of the phenyl portion of the phenethyl group by any monocycle, whether or not further substituted in or on the monocycle;</text></clause><clause id="id8c5afacbb0cb4fb5b12a3cc9493a2d67"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>substitution in or on the phenethyl group with alkyl, alkenyl, alkoxyl, hydroxyl, halo, haloalkyl, amino, or nitro groups;</text></clause><clause id="id3c20dcbbcc774df692c2690931b04188"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>substitution in or on the piperidine ring with alkyl, alkenyl, alkoxyl, ester, ether, hydroxyl, halo, haloalkyl, amino, or nitro groups;</text></clause><clause id="iddc6186f8d2cd4f5c9fbce09ab66d06bc"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>replacement of the aniline ring with any aromatic monocycle whether or not further substituted in or on the aromatic monocycle; and</text></clause><clause id="ide4c5a64dae174ab89b5561f67353d0e3"><enum>(v)</enum><text>replacement of the N-propionyl group with another acyl group; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8cb163af16bb4b75919e00b6259c6142"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include a substance described in subparagraph (A) that is—</text><clause id="id731289567bbe4048aea1d09598acd033"><enum>(i)</enum><text>controlled by action of the Attorney General pursuant to section 201 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/811">21 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>); </text></clause><clause id="id0ffdce6b78ec41c8b100c2aa9e4f28aa"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expressly listed in Schedule I of section 202(c) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812</external-xref>) or another schedule by a statutory provision; or</text></clause><clause id="id5a765c5a308744a4b79a15505a426fb7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>removed from Schedule I, or rescheduled to another schedule, pursuant to section 201(k) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/811">21 U.S.C. 811(k)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id32ff12d12028457da4ad05733bee5bfd"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Illegal means</header><text>The term <term>illegal means</term> includes the trafficking of money, human trafficking, illicit financial flows, illegal trade in natural resources and wildlife, trade in illegal drugs and weapons, and other forms of illegal means determined by the Secretary of Defense. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id02b06d5108894e949d5c7ac373b02cf6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Security cooperation program</header><text>The term <term>security cooperation program</term> has the meaning given that term in section 301 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5500f2466ef449aaa5bb725bd36a57ac"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Transnational criminal organization</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id47f5503e230e4d1ea817a9e271602a50"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>transnational criminal organization</term> means a group, network, and associated individuals who operate transnationally for the purpose of obtaining power, influence, or monetary or commercial gain, wholly or in part by illegal means, while advancing their activities through a pattern of crime, corruption, or violence and protecting their illegal activities through a transnational organizational structure and the exploitation of public corruption or transnational logistics, financial, or communication mechanisms. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id935d58308080439a9eb1ee68bcf65309"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional organizations</header><text>The term <term>transnational criminal organization</term> includes any transnational criminal organization identified in the most recent Drug Threat Assessment of the Drug Enforcement Agency. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

