<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BUR23114-C4L-MR-JNN"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S622 IS: Helping Heroes Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 622</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230302">March 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S229">Mrs. Murray</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S343">Mr. Boozman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S253">Mr. Durbin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S259">Mr. Reed</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S324">Mrs. Shaheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S313">Mr. Sanders</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S247">Mr. Wyden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S362">Mr. Kaine</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S288">Ms. Murkowski</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSVA00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To improve services provided by the Department of Veterans Affairs for veteran families, and for other purposes. </official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Helping Heroes Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id423B3E5DE4CD4CD9AEF755D199AF8811"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="idC000233AC05244448FF1C19EB0B2EE05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3078C2553811421BB742EAA277FF8110"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disabled veteran</header><text>The term <term>disabled veteran</term> has the meaning given that term in section 4211 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idEF1FA43F9BFB4F17870B44CB996647C6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible child</header><text>The term <term>eligible child</term>, with respect to an eligible veteran, means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="id6F31D26EEFC84AF6B212B36B781CEDED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a ward, child (including stepchild), grandchild, or sibling (including stepsibling or halfsibling) of the eligible veteran; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idAE8955623D124E2BA971543271FD16F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is less than 18 years of age.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id82105A5BA2CA488C819DE1D805378D43"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible veteran</header><text>The term <term>eligible veteran</term> means a disabled veteran who has a service-connected disability rated at 70 percent or more.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide4ffa53b95bd43f5b44cbcdde00bdfc6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Family Coordinator</header><text>The term <term>Family Coordinator</term> means an individual placed at a medical center of the Department pursuant to section 3.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id42fc56982d9844189e8d740a793a230a"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Family Support Program</header><text>The term <term>Family Support Program</term> means the program established under section 4.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd079c7c1b7154867a242d8e69b02e1a2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Non-Department provider</header><text>The term <term>non-Department provider</term> means a public or non-profit entity that is not an entity of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id344512ee0b164b71a7fd39e0c57fbf8b"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id308923210bf34ed8a4e3066138dfd9ba"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Supportive services</header><text>The term <term>supportive services</term> means services that address the social, emotional, and mental health, career-readiness, and other needs of eligible children, including—</text><subparagraph id="id1f49fd9952f642ff98aff1601831646d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>wellness services, including mental, emotional, behavioral, and physical health and nutritional counseling and assistance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1809443ac01948edb1fbe9ce999a995a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>peer-support programs for children;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8787491389df4883870babd85d527e15"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assistance completing college admission and financial aid applications, including the Free Application for Federal Student Aid described in section 483(a) of the Higher Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1090">20 U.S.C. 1090</external-xref>), and accessing veterans’ education benefits as defined under section 480(c)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087vv">20 U.S.C. 1087vv</external-xref>) that eligible children may be eligible to receive;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idee2dfc3b6fe04315aea6ccbf48c583d9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>assistance with accessing workforce development programs, including programs providing the activities authorized under section 129 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164</external-xref>), and programs of vocational rehabilitation services, including programs authorized under title I of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/720">29 U.S.C. 720 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9ca4533882bb479697ecd68d0674c6f3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>sports and recreation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf2f64691c31d4337bc64ffa564adefe1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>after-school care and summer learning opportunities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id28b6eacc51f343f8a52a8235c06b2728"><enum>(G)</enum><text>dependent care, including home and community-based services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id565957e7973344d58f4aeed62890060a"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other resources for low-income families;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id50dc7d3c1fe8408ba4897621d6c777f3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>assistance transitioning from active duty in the Armed Forces to veteran status; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida14f8017658741d7a364308469c09629"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other services or activities the Secretary considers appropriate to support the needs of eligible children.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="id0f2f6cbba0b046409d117d1990899a0f"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirements for Family Coordinators</header><subsection id="id1ab1a5d73e78477cb99475f78d6adce6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="idf39398b50e4c48d5a52e0a1927bc2115"><enum>(1)</enum><text>place at each medical center of the Department not fewer than one Family Coordinator; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idff06117dc98243899266abf030f9f038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure adequate staffing and resources at each such medical center to ensure Family Coordinators are able to carry out their duties.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id14355e796a7f4dd8bbbbfb59c8955119"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Family Coordinators</header><paragraph id="id74562b5de90043529cc0ddeffb86bfbb"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Employment</header><text>Each Family Coordinator placed at a medical center of the Department under subsection (a) shall be employed full-time by the Department as a Family Coordinator and shall have no other duties in addition to the duties of a Family Coordinator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1926A50D34D845D7873869FCF805A4A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><subparagraph id="id5A5D01E7A30A41D5A3D08D8F0A6E0C7F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To qualify to be a Family Coordinator under subsection (a), an individual shall—</text><clause id="idcaa820318c06428cbd1fe0f2747f2d62"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be a social worker licensed, registered, or certified in accordance with the requirements of any State; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="ide1df6d36196f4c5abad38b1af17c49ef"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have a graduate degree in social work or a related field.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id0691AE5487CB4DF79B4F39CCF39DC8ED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the qualifications required by subparagraph (A) to permit individuals in other professions to serve as Family Coordinators.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id814fafcbd0b9406eb29215a792d07861"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>Each Family Coordinator shall—</text><subparagraph id="id354d81b938da48148e50688c0ac4a5a0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the needs of the families of veterans using evidence-based strategies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1a360f06a2104c69bc181c40f6d72f30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>build positive relationships with such families;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0a944914415e4e7a95c09832acba78da"><enum>(C)</enum><text>refer veterans to local, State, and Federal resources that support veterans and their families; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida4dd2c961ff043458497479c53fd34ae"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop and maintain a list of—</text><clause id="id4cabefcd8b9a41d6a39648afad85e7b2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>supportive services offered by the medical center at which the Family Coordinator is placed; and</text></clause><clause id="idc867d336b7254669a5d55882385dfd68"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supportive services offered at reduced or no cost by non-Department providers located in the catchment area of such medical center; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide68dd38204e4440e9121b88ef9ce8869"><enum>(E)</enum><text>develop and maintain on an internet website a list of family resources that shall be made available for all veterans in the catchment area of such medical center who are enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department established and operated under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="ide24d8d71f12c4cb59e53f31a5139cf44"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of Family Support Program</header><subsection id="idc644064b2e994722aacb9602dcbfb2ec"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a program to be known as the Family Support Program to provide and coordinate the provision of supportive services to eligible veterans and eligible children.</text></subsection><subsection id="idd43f454030e34d83b6ac9a3b3d8d68ab"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation of Family Support Program</header><text>To carry out the Family Support Program, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="id5b729701d7374905ad4c90c3d69716ff"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide supportive services through medical centers of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd2311f8b30cc470d9f414d5c967ab6ef"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with relevant Federal agencies to provide supportive services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id35d4d2550d694e369719d24da72902e3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide funding to non-Department providers pursuant to subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddcababb57b8a4eb3ab1bbcacba803cea"><enum>(4)</enum><text>engage in any other activities the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idc0d056531a004b07a5473db8eb4d8ecf"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding to non-Department providers</header><paragraph id="id86848389eb6f45e282959e9bf59d1366"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may enter into contracts and award grants to provide funding to eligible non-Department providers to participate in the Family Support Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id407f791725444e54955f9f25500e4d4d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><subparagraph id="id7f3cfd9548b841d0b5f216696b0975ce"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and make publicly available the criteria for a non-Department provider to be eligible to participate in the Family Support Program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfd54c365f16a44c6a74276730e0007db"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The criteria required by subparagraph (A) shall include requirements for a non-Department provider—</text><clause id="id6372fd9ca42040d795b1e24de2f6fb93"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to provide a description of—</text><subclause id="idADA1E45F06054101B030957E6C17B6ED"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each supportive service proposed to be provided to eligible children; and </text></subclause><subclause id="idBEDB583738A644FDBC2606DB96C06189"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the demonstrated record of the non-Department provider in providing such supportive service;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id96df7696207140c79edea27019c6648b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to demonstrate the ability to serve families of veterans in a manner that is trauma-informed and culturally and linguistically appropriate; and</text></clause><clause id="id7c39bd842ab547b89cafa65b90d4da6f"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to agree to oversight by the Secretary regarding—</text><subclause id="idc320d97740e74b8a88d838de5e848090"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the use of funds provided by the Department under this subsection; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id658f55eef04940a29319e83aa2a1da46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the quality of supportive services provided.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id55b44467c0044715a60965d23ef3d4de"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The Secretary shall promptly provide to eligible non-Department providers selected by the Secretary to participate in the Family Support Program notice of the award of funds under this subsection to ensure such providers have sufficient time to prepare to provide supportive services under the Family Support Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida4c1ed70ae274384892bfbcd375a1bcc"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header><text>Funds provided under this subsection shall be used to provide supportive services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7d25ce85283842969567cba0e861783d"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Training</header><text>For each non-Department provider selected by the Secretary to participant in the Family Support Program, the Secretary shall offer training and technical assistance regarding the planning, development, and provision of supportive services under the Family Support Program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id3d07d530358e49cf9a7a4fe7e282674f"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination with other department of veterans affairs programs</header><text>The Secretary shall share best practices with and facilitate referrals of eligible veterans and their families, as appropriate, from the Family Support Program to other programs of the Department, such as the program of support services for caregivers of veterans under section 1720G(b) of title 38, United States Code. </text></subsection><subsection id="idbac1e9c92bbb4861a2edaef77b69d7de"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="idce23e37bde974ab4ba1a4fddeb68a7e4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the commencement of the Family Support Program, and annually thereafter, each non-Department provider in receipt of funds under the Family Support Program shall submit to the Secretary a report describing the supportive services carried out with such funds during the year covered by such report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id99cc4a93dc3141b0a9853b413c23627e"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><subparagraph id="idc54e200b32a849e19fa4095abeeb2688"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report on additional resources</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the potential need for additional resources for family members of eligible veterans other than eligible children.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id967B3D60ED684BF2A708E246D94C2F95"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report on progress</header><clause id="idD54F2E0431BB45A7A2E382376698669C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the commencement of the Family Support Program, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the progress of the Family Support Program.</text></clause><clause id="id0742b9ac57f34b22bee6e4732f3bfe35"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required by clause (i) shall include—</text><subclause id="id218c8f76a16747c5a6555a49413ba85d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the number of eligible veterans and eligible children who received supportive services under the Family Support Program;</text></subclause><subclause id="idf0ce2486f5e34f2395a8c1e655a3689e"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the demographic data of eligible veterans and family members, including—</text><item id="id802f71d286ba4ae5873eb4e0a671f728"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the relationship to the eligible veteran;</text></item><item id="idff30953535c04a24a0f6c001f46275a8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>age;</text></item><item id="idf719c353628141ac89b1d82acfd05d48"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>race;</text></item><item id="id563ed8f4ae87486d8cb001a133343bbb"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></item><item id="ide9319e226e21436faed3124f6c1741d1"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>gender identity;</text></item><item id="idf371818b794a4afa8692a4fee1121c61"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>sexual orientation; </text></item><item id="id796EA4D1E97842C093DC416FEF93EA77"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>disability; and</text></item><item id="idfe6fc6a7189f4d15b8ecd2333af41137"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>English proficiency and whether a language other than English is spoken at home; </text></item></subclause><subclause id="idbbd9100f600341798d23e748184ead12"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a summary of the supportive services carried out under the Family Support Program and the costs to the Department of such supportive services; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id334d5e51df384c67ad3f3078ad0eeca3"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an assessment, measured by a survey of participants, of whether participation in the Family Support Program resulted in positive outcomes for eligible veterans and eligible children.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="ide448343d85834c068619c6e75fb09056"><enum>5.</enum><header>Outreach on availability of services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct an outreach program to ensure eligible veterans who are enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department established and operated under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code, employees of the Department, and potential State, local, and Federal entities are informed of the Family Support Program and the availability of Family Coordinators.</text></section><section id="idF4F2573805E84FAF907151D310FF0E50"><enum>6.</enum><header>Transition assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall include information regarding supportive services available for members of the Armed Forces who are being separated from active duty and their families, including mental health and other services for children, in the transition assistance curriculum offered by the Department.</text></section><section id="id61940cb011a143f88084a53f471921ab"><enum>7.</enum><header>Survey</header><subsection id="id134B062A48B840B297F5AD66686E00DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for five years, the Secretary shall conduct a survey of disabled veterans and their families to identify and better understand the needs of such disabled veterans and their families. </text></subsection><subsection id="id69B7C2C1D4B745C08945A08FEAE38BA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The survey required under subsection (a) shall include questions with respect to—</text><paragraph id="idEC82C4AB39504431AC5BCBEDF0E2253B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the types and quality of support disabled veterans receive from the children of such disabled veterans; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2FF2F48310E84B9D8F28DF7CAF9CADCF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the unmet needs of such children.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id892ae6364392460d82da0e6069111c62"><enum>8.</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Programs or activities receiving funds under this Act may not discriminate on the basis of race, color, national origin, religion, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability status, or age.</text></section><section id="id625730611F1E4DA49F0302B6BBAB5F7C"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary such funds as may be necessary to carry out this Act. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

