<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BOM23239-DX3-WL-NVN"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 S1341 IS: EDUCATORS for America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1341</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S259">Mr. Reed</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S309">Mr. Casey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S409">Mr. Luján</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S390">Mr. Van Hollen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S247">Mr. Wyden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S284">Ms. Stabenow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S322">Mr. Merkley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S359">Mr. Heinrich</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To reauthorize title II of the Higher Education Act of 1965, and for other purposes. </official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="idB3F7A31AF7D247C4BECF4C479E6C7333"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id907887C71A1C446583EC850635284299"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="idb8b10147bd814baa8f70b5ce9cf524c0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Despite an increased need for prekindergarten through grade 12 teachers, the number of students completing bachelor’s degrees in education has been in decline over the last 2 decades.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idefb22f9db67b4464afe9fa37427f0fdd"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Pay is by far the reason that undergraduates cite most often for not pursuing teaching as a career. Pay was named as such a reason by 72 percent of respondents in a large 2018 survey of prospective college students.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide770fb3831e54615b3874f9b6521c1a1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Because they earn less than other bachelor’s degree recipients, teachers face particular challenges repaying student loans. Estimated payments on the average amount education graduates have borrowed is equivalent to 9 percent of the average starting teacher salary, well in excess of the 7 percent threshold recommended by economists as affordable for borrowers at that income level.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcf5dafa65c404a7f89ec7079cf590d06"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The number of students earning undergraduate and graduate degrees in the high-demand specialties of mathematics, science, and foreign language education are in decline and the numbers earning degrees in special education and teaching English as a second language are insufficient to meet demand in many localities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9504352d302f4d4b8abfbdc1cb7938b1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Prior to COVID–19, the number of institutions offering degrees in education was stable, but the number with small programs was on the rise. One-third of the 1,500 institutions that award bachelor’s and master’s degrees in education granted 30 or fewer such degrees in 2019.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7382cd395fd042818a01db70e8cfdaf5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An October 2020 survey of American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education members, which includes 700 schools, colleges, and departments of education at public and private 4-year colleges and universities, revealed that nearly 60 percent have experienced a decline in undergraduate enrollment due to COVID–19, 83 percent have had budget cuts, and half have reduced staffing. The Association predicts that, absent additional support, a sizable number of educator preparation programs will close, eliminating needed capacity to produce the profession-ready teachers that the Nation needs. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id15953df60a464be795970adb9dc5f752"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A 2015 Government Accountability Office analysis showed that only 19 percent of students who were eligible for the Federal Teacher Education Assistance for College and Higher Education Grant program (referred to as <quote>TEACH Grants</quote>) in the 2013–2014 academic year utilized this program, yet the cost of college remains a barrier for many students who seek to become teachers. Institutions like the University of Northern Iowa have successfully utilized TEACH Grants for 57 percent of its TEACH Grant-eligible teacher candidates, with over one thousand moving into teaching positions in high-need fields in high-need schools. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id650c7102a26444ad8d6c4063dd630c5a"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Only 22 percent of educators feel they are <quote>very prepared</quote> to teach social and emotional learning in classrooms, and 51 percent report that the level of social and emotional learning professional development offered at their school is not sufficient. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbcdb6e8fd2c041b1a5559b8bf6414a12"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Our Nation’s schools are experiencing a severe diversity gap that negatively impacts student achievement and school culture. Fifty percent of current students are from minority groups while only 18 percent of teachers are from such groups, according to a 2016 study by the Brookings Institution. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide47a416b74f8473899c6b98ed214d26b"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A 2016 report conducted by the Department of Education shows that teachers of color tend to provide more culturally relevant teaching and better understand the situations that students of color may face. These factors help develop trusting teacher-student relationships. Researchers from Vanderbilt University also found that greater racial and ethnic diversity among school principals benefits students, especially students of color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id50bb853c1a384e62842ff08695bb65b2"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Research shows that increasing diversity in the teaching profession can have positive impacts on student educational experiences and outcomes. Students of color demonstrate greater academic achievement and social-emotional development in classes with teachers of color. Studies also suggest that all students, including White students, benefit from having teachers of color because they bring distinctive knowledge, experiences, and role modeling to the student body as a whole.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id0ef3b10618914c16b167ea968596056c"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Effective school leadership is second only to direct classroom instruction among school-based factors in raising student achievement, and principal impact is greatest in low-achieving, high-poverty, and minority schools.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id7db118559ca5454fa51d3b8eddefc767"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Principals improve teaching and learning through their ability—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="id041D3E137E994B64B5BA5976078D8485"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to shape a vision of academic success for all students; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idD09A8AC203AB4CB8AE8E1F4618312071"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to create a safe and supportive school climate; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id534910BC09A4497F91E2E617575E4500"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to cultivate leadership among teachers and other school staff; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id4CFAE8E039F0447598BDFB6A597A0B98"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to improve instruction; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id0669C251D7F64D4795067060D171BC55"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to manage people, data, and processes to foster school improvement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="idf0c3718e225648c1827f55c101676b25"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Recent research from the Wallace Foundation on principals’ impact on students and schools notes that it is difficult to envision a higher return on investment in kindergarten through grade 12 education than the cultivation of high-quality school leadership.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id8cd8cedfd61e43e196ba5cfc33ef1699"><enum>(15)</enum><text>In the 2015–2016 school year, only 22 percent of public school principals were individuals of color, including 11 percent who identified as Black and 8 percent who identified as Hispanic.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id4F317A0D8F8140C5B12D4F44C43125DB"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Minority teachers, school leaders, and other educators can also serve as cultural ambassadors who help students feel more welcome at school or as role models.</text></paragraph></section><section id="id10B945651EA94FAD9363D357C5F2F87C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Educator quality enhancement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6850910EBE8646DCB02C96BA55631E10"><title commented="no" id="ID6898F0EC51BE49639A8793A2FA7B1BDF"><enum>II</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Educator quality enhancement</header><section id="id7434f1080831482ca6bcba0327554786"><enum>200.</enum><header>Purposes; definitions</header><subsection id="id89C9FA22EB1B482F966C4CE50AD9A17C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this title are to—</text><paragraph id="idcec39f235e93409889f217739f6fe922"><enum>(1)</enum><text>build the capacity of educator preparation programs to ensure that all students have access to diverse, profession-ready educators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id668f9ecd622a46ea85b9c35f4ffb6315"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide incentives to individuals to enroll in and complete high-quality educator preparation programs in high-need fields at the baccalaureate or graduate levels at institutions of higher education, particularly to individuals who belong to groups that are currently underrepresented in the education profession;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8847995faa9841ae8564ed051824a1bb"><enum>(3)</enum><text>authorize investments in higher education educator preparation programs along with critical State and local partners to support and expand promising and successful practices; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc4a75751b16e4bf4ba14e7e570e1f197"><enum>(4)</enum><text>create mechanisms to integrate innovations in the preparation of profession-ready educators to meet the ever changing needs of students and schools.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="IDE237E3DEDF0C4520981238393CD8FE83"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2BC116BE012B4D798E2D90069A78F236"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Arts and sciences</header><text>The term <term>arts and sciences</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="IDCCBCE2A3CDF84267B62073BDC575EB63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>when referring to an organizational unit of an institution of higher education, any academic unit that offers one or more academic majors in disciplines or content areas corresponding to the academic subject matter areas in which teachers provide instruction; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDAEA0885FE3714CC6B2BDC6A8BDDB537D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when referring to a specific academic subject area, the disciplines or content areas in which academic majors are offered by the arts and sciences organizational unit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id59838d9950ec434c86be59848bfdcc70"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification or licensure</header><text>The term <term>certification or licensure</term> means State requirements for certification or licensure to teach in that State, and may include the following:</text><subparagraph id="id8a4cbe8f59ae425883d624c75b61c4af"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A regular or standard State certificate or advanced professional certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3cdc4799ab3f48979da5857b2a1325fb"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A probationary certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1b5daf8aa7444cf8ad8c5f45281373e5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A temporary or provisional certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6fc369bdb5ef4ca386af181ac7442c57"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A waiver or emergency certificate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID34AC0CA2161741EA8FBF40BED1674D69"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Children from low-income families</header><text>The term <term>children from low-income families</term> means children counted under section 1124(c)(1)(A) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDF177A1230BB042D1A914F47AB45C73EA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Early childhood educator</header><text>The term <term>early childhood educator</term> means an individual with primary responsibility for the education of children in an early childhood education program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2865c40f4957460eb47160dff62d9e2e"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>early childhood education program</term> means a public education program serving children from birth through age 8, and may include a Head Start program or an Early Head Start program carried out under the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq.</external-xref>), including a migrant or seasonal Head Start program, an Indian Head Start program, or a Head Start program or an Early Head Start program that also receives State funding or a public preschool program. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID43EC678983A147278AF2B96FF645EC6E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Educational service agency</header><text>The term <term>educational service agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id386173a3306e43af921fae981801268b"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Educator</header><text>The term <term>educator</term> means a teacher, principal, school leader, specialized instructional support personnel, or other staff member who provides or directly supports instruction, such as a school librarian, or counselor. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id156f900016f84df3b3b6463c50d2b7fe"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Educator preparation program</header><text>The term <term>educator preparation program</term> means a program that leads to a regular or standard State certificate or advanced professional certificate for an educator. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID2B39006A153E4E3BAE510A032A3C15C9"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Eligible partnership</header><text>The term <term>eligible partnership</term> means an entity that—</text><subparagraph id="IDC195C1356172483E92AF422C0919EF70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="ID34519C9C4C4E415EAD336848E4540AD7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a high-need local educational agency;</text></clause><clause id="IDFAC4ECB550924CF4817984843B3E8C8E"><enum>(ii)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="IDEAFB72C6331047EEAA6D6E2E1ED8A7CA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a high-need school or a consortium of high-need schools served by the high-need local educational agency; or</text></subclause><subclause id="IDA715E214A4D844069E9757EE05006FC9" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>as appropriate, a high-need early childhood education program;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="ID09CD576467ED457FA9CE5F459B81BE5E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a partner institution; and</text></clause><clause id="ID4D5267A8C805402687321E617EAA87C9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a school, department, or program of education within such partner institution, which may include an existing teacher professional development program with demonstrated outcomes within a four-year institution of higher education that provides intensive and sustained collaboration between faculty and local educational agencies consistent with the requirements of this title; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID75DAEE0EE5784ABFA909B5D078F8539E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include any of the following:</text><clause id="ID3CB0F4EE0A3A4C329C286585140181D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Governor of the State.</text></clause><clause id="ID5A65D2BB96E8483FB0E9FD522E5F20C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The State educational agency.</text></clause><clause id="IDE991E259E5504020A4B2E436FC8F72DB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The State board of education.</text></clause><clause id="IDD442C0FE6437470BB17923185D1A4A8E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The State agency for higher education.</text></clause><clause id="ID68FA44A32ABE411083F0311BFA150B5E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A business.</text></clause><clause id="ID6998CFBF09BF40E48B8894CEF5CC2C00"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>A public or private nonprofit educational organization.</text></clause><clause id="IDD3E34EF8126F4194960001DBB0B261BE"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>An educational service agency.</text></clause><clause id="ID4EBD5923228C4CF1BAE0E86A280BC1FB"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>A teacher organization.</text></clause><clause id="ide56d086c7871470fbdfa23b090758db4"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>A school leader organization.</text></clause><clause id="ida1f7caf9d26949adaa180266ef82ca66"><enum>(x)</enum><text>An organization representing specialized instructional support personnel. </text></clause><clause id="ID7C08C8F78D7B46CD81EBA45D712787C0"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>A high-performing local educational agency, or a consortium of such local educational agencies, that can serve as a resource to the partnership.</text></clause><clause id="IDECFDDB0563084A1DA35948BB77E016C7"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>A charter school (as defined in section 4310 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965).</text></clause><clause id="id52f2c2a353f747238f70a383cdb86683"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>A school or department of arts and sciences within the partner institution.</text></clause><clause id="idfac3fac3608744d386a8ed39a5785b57"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>A school or department within the partner institution that focuses on psychology and human development.</text></clause><clause id="id87ee907519804965a90d80a822073d64"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>A school or department within the partner institution with comparable expertise in the disciplines of teaching, learning, and child and adolescent development.</text></clause><clause id="idda434bb0b74d4c06aa3e8cd5963930db"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>A public or nonprofit entity operating a program that provides alternative routes to State certification of teachers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID2B1D704A9DC24B17848D8EA13F34CFE6"><enum>(10)</enum><header>English learner</header><text>The term <term>English learner</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id50F5A6F7F7174D549EC1DCB81CA0D569"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Evidence-based</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id37146d4d371847a980f488567493b0de"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Evidence of student learning</header><text>The term <term>evidence of student learning</term> means multiple measures of student learning that include the following:</text><subparagraph id="ide5b5c3da41fd4182a98df2e53b3749d6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Valid and reliable student assessment data, which may include data—</text><clause id="id2f29f4d95e8c4183959612be9d50326c"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based on—</text><subclause id="id1df8134f9ac6476fb1a030a328a2e7bb"><enum>(I)</enum><text>student learning gains on State student academic assessments under section 1111(b)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idea358c5827eb433783f7dc881771a630"><enum>(II)</enum><text>student academic achievement assessments used at the national, State, or local educational agency level, where available and appropriate for the curriculum and students taught;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id2b1cc4fd3ddb4726bf07f5e459198341"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>from classroom-based formative assessments;</text></clause><clause id="iddacbe8eb7f804571991c434f1758b477"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>from classroom-based summative assessments; and</text></clause><clause id="ida21c4babdb5e4741b1c119bf9e320456"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>from objective performance-based assessments.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1961a3f19b3e47969cf9ec323289a244"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Not less than one of the following additional measures:</text><clause id="idb5c6563dafec4a88be3b60cc92cd849a"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Student work, including measures of performance criteria and evidence of student growth.</text></clause><clause id="id941c50223676429481a71f5127270255"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Teacher-generated information about student goals and growth.</text></clause><clause id="ida55f453c267440a1bad7c2dc832ae5c3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Parent or caregiver feedback about student goals and growth.</text></clause><clause id="idff109008b43242ba890023dfb0b372d5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Student feedback about learning and teaching supports.</text></clause><clause id="id54770a58d9854155b2257831687304f8"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Assessments of effective engagement and self-efficacy.</text></clause><clause id="idc258adfc4c1744bf8768ed6977fbab8e"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Other appropriate measures, as determined by the State.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDD6E7A19DF49A4097AF560A155BC0B7EF"><enum>(13)</enum><header>High-need early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>high-need early childhood education program</term> means an early childhood education program serving children from low-income families that is located within the geographic area served by a high-need local educational agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id87365c42ed134f318fd7d5662e4cbc67"><enum>(14)</enum><header>High-need local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>high-need local educational agency</term> means a local educational agency—</text><subparagraph id="id0c1f3eec31ea46d89dba3fb03f39d17e"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id24a4e37c40a74560b409d92d37ee5d19"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that serves not fewer than 10,000 low-income children;</text></clause><clause id="idb566d28159814322942f2a642ab0685d" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for which not less than 20 percent of the children served by the agency are low-income children;</text></clause><clause id="id9a56401274be41fe9ca861e5713b0c4b" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that meets the eligibility requirements for funding under the Small, Rural School Achievement Program under section 5211(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 or the Rural and Low-Income School Program under section 5221(b) of such Act; or</text></clause><clause id="id842a611a5bfa472b8d550c71f4e8bce5" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>that has a percentage of low-income children that is in the highest quartile among such agencies in the State; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9f04aa43187c4e3e8436f2c160ac4a2d"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id669ee310dd4248d7b83e8d14fd06d39b"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for which a majority of schools are identified for comprehensive support and improvement under section 1111(c)(4)(D) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, targeted support and improvement under section 1111(d)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, or additional targeted support under section 1111(d)(2)(C) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></clause><clause id="id9203a3421f0f483b9de7b21baf75c8a2" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for which 1 or more schools served by the agency has a high teacher turnover rate or a high percentage of teachers with emergency, provisional, or temporary certification or licensure; or</text></clause><clause id="id89dec3aff6874e02a530b7ebede90700" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for which there is a high percentage of positions in State-identified areas of teacher or school leader shortage, including in special education, English language instruction, science, technology, engineering, mathematics, and career and technical education.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID941FEB2423BD4222BC9398C483CEBAAE"><enum>(15)</enum><header>High-need school</header><subparagraph id="IDD614F2F16E5E47E192339782ABDB6BC4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>high-need school</term> means a school that, based on the most recent data available, meets one or both of the following:</text><clause id="ID0DE2295D6DB148EF8371585BAE720FB0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The school is in the highest quartile of schools in a ranking of all schools served by a local educational agency, ranked in descending order by percentage of students from low-income families enrolled in such schools, as determined by the local educational agency based on one of the following measures of poverty:</text><subclause id="ID92E9A0FC5A994B52B5CEC6DA3AD62A19"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The percentage of students aged 5 through 17 in poverty counted in the most recent census data approved by the Secretary.</text></subclause><subclause id="ID7239DB2313064DF4B88F52608FEA79F2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The percentage of students eligible for a free or reduced price school lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act.</text></subclause><subclause id="ID7825253385C843759D4A8BF49FF14FCC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The percentage of students in families receiving assistance under the State program funded under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act.</text></subclause><subclause id="ID3030CA4BE49449389884ED84FB14D0BE"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The percentage of students eligible to receive medical assistance under the Medicaid program.</text></subclause><subclause id="IDC21DD94B29CF43F082954F78CA579CC0"><enum>(V)</enum><text>A composite of two or more of the measures described in subclauses (I) through (IV).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="ID520151F4211643358C169E2BA1E66858"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In the case of—</text><subclause id="ID7497A2D848CF488799D6B99671D4CCEB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an elementary school, the school serves students not less than 60 percent of whom are eligible for a free or reduced price school lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act; or</text></subclause><subclause id="IDCAC7F0D04FA440F6BED2F8575B636DF9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other school that is not an elementary school, the other school serves students not less than 45 percent of whom are eligible for a free or reduced price school lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDEE71F6D11BE84C7F82528C9850FC88DE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule</header><clause id="ID7040430C6EBA45CE9C6B66A026A5AF49"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Designation by the secretary</header><text>The Secretary may, upon approval of an application submitted by an eligible partnership seeking a grant under this title, designate a school that does not qualify as a high-need school under subparagraph (A) as a high-need school for the purpose of this title. The Secretary shall base the approval of an application for designation of a school under this clause on a consideration of the information required under clause (ii), and may also take into account other information submitted by the eligible partnership.</text></clause><clause id="ID01580B11720145C8BF6F220DCE03B8E1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>An application for designation of a school under clause (i) shall include—</text><subclause id="ID4D3729EA5B1C42C7987A834BF74A1ACA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the number and percentage of students attending such school who are—</text><item id="ID2C18B819B00E48E6BDFE5ABFB220368E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>aged 5 through 17 in poverty counted in the most recent census data approved by the Secretary;</text></item><item id="ID45D9E03FB8C24D2E84BFEAE3E5867910"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>eligible for a free or reduced price school lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act;</text></item><item id="ID6D66F46B31EC4CA3BD5088151335E74E"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in families receiving assistance under the State program funded under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act; or</text></item><item id="ID2AD1A4EA58BF483295D6D329B187EA3A"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>eligible to receive medical assistance under the Medicaid program;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="ID6D3B0D8696F8420DA76E25C890AE4F67"><enum>(II)</enum><text>information about the student academic achievement of students at such school; and</text></subclause><subclause id="ID2A13D10E35154A4AAEDBA9B619A8683A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>for a secondary school, the graduation rate for such school.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idc45dadb60d78414aba4036e543ceaf42"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Induction program</header><text>The term <term>induction program</term> means a formalized program for new educators during not less than the educators’ first 2 years in the profession that is designed to provide support for, and improve the professional performance and advance the retention in the field of, beginning educators. Such program shall promote effective teaching skills, instructional leadership skills, and profession-readiness for educators and shall include the following components:</text><subparagraph id="id3b7a714b1fea4def93a868534b377ab2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>High-quality mentoring.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id98e04d7d3c38497f867c03afb70d042e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Periodic, structured time for collaboration with educators in the same department or field, including mentor teachers, as well as time for information-sharing among teachers, principals, administrators, other appropriate instructional staff, and participating faculty in the partner institution.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9ecebe61a0494993a81d52fd83e3830f"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The application of evidence-based practice on instructional practices.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida74e6e4058954b2a8743b598f3c663e3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Opportunities for new educators to draw directly on the expertise of mentors, faculty, and researchers to support the integration of evidence-based practice and research with practice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id56e5734649c44b2fa3b061f22af3a0f9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The development of skills in instructional and behavioral interventions derived from evidence-based practice and, where applicable, research.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8836ed67a50f4e23ae43a42da1e7acd2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Faculty who—</text><clause id="id1f75026b45b24e2b976d0627f0a3ede7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>model the integration of research and practice in instruction;</text></clause><clause id="id12b93690fbe847c6b3b8d3caed53171e"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>model personalized instruction; and</text></clause><clause id="id629090019f154caba3c7238aa8b89cf1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>assist new educators with the effective use and integration of technology in instruction.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id635b1fd473f44ed894e5ad033f5c3c67"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Interdisciplinary collaboration among exemplary educators, faculty, researchers, and other staff who prepare new educators with respect to the learning process and the assessment of learning.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idce55076ff5b74082960d81f0baf2a744"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Assistance with the understanding of evidence of student learning and the applicability of such evidence in classroom instruction.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4444e9b1ecb2473b9d4b24b0941ac3e4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The development of skills to implement and support evidence-based practices that create a positive and inclusive school culture and climate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7ab2027b64d640e0b2f849838c9cddcb"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Regular and structured observation and evaluation of new educators by multiple evaluators, using valid and reliable measures of teaching skills, instructional leadership skills, and profession-readiness.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb6acfa76f8104e08a4390c3f4b3e0565"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDF1187C1BC239415190482D6232F17B33"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Parent</header><text>The term <term>parent</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDBA8B2D80CEA74EA78EBDE60F203626A0"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Partner institution</header><text>The term <term>partner institution</term> means an institution of higher education, which may include a 2-year institution of higher education offering a dual program with a 4-year institution of higher education, participating in an eligible partnership that has a teacher preparation program that—</text><subparagraph id="idb136df1347f24617b76bd81191cb40d8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a record of preparing profession-ready educators;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb863a14c26be4f22881e1b9bb16ed645"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is approved by the State to offer an educator preparation program; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1551df3d510e4bc7a173b45a73ff9200"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not low-performing, as determined by the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID4CB70785708A4F4FB27668693E990C44"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Professional development</header><text>The term <term>professional development</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id489b619aa1364b0fb87f45e5496a5717"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Profession-ready</header><text>The term <term>profession-ready</term>—</text><subparagraph id="id8325d77a436e4fca8c98a3a2e703053c"><enum>(A)</enum><text>when used with respect to a principal, means a principal who—</text><clause id="id24d70b7b22024a08a6401f2e4b526042"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has an advanced degree, or other appropriate credential;</text></clause><clause id="id540bf3e82e2c46ef81408077892f01fa"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has completed a principal preparation process and is fully certified and licensed by the State in which the principal is employed;</text></clause><clause id="id6726f446230848fb8fc7f5eb46e683bf"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has demonstrated instructional leadership, including the ability to collect, analyze, and use data on evidence of student learning and evidence of classroom practice;</text></clause><clause id="id68d236cb5a2c48ebadd852ce388d66cd"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has demonstrated proficiency in professionally recognized leadership standards, such as through—</text><subclause id="id3bf65217c8fd48b3a8e1c965874cd20e"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a performance assessment;</text></subclause><subclause id="idc937d3e8169d48ca9886ee7fce6079c0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>completion of a residency program; or</text></subclause><subclause id="ida9bffba28b9d4422ab88e5a543254ff1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>other measures of leadership, as determined by the State;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idf9dc00d25adb48ebaf7a769b730f247f"><enum>(v)</enum><text>has demonstrated the ability to work with students who are culturally and linguistically diverse; </text></clause><clause id="id7497398bc861479b9c8e6a81d3e1e5d7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>has demonstrated skill as an instructional leader; and </text></clause><clause id="id2df25cb9072d418da58f252710ca6022"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>has demonstrated proficiency in the use of instructional technology, assistive technology, and the application of technology to create equity and access for all students;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id84b7b7a5396f4d8c9aaeb27edc641074"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when used with respect to a teacher, means a teacher who—</text><clause id="ide45458e195884e1aa36ce9c111d21735"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has completed a teacher preparation program and has a certification or licensure described in paragraph (2)(A) for the State in which the teacher teaches;</text></clause><clause id="id0583eb7f460e4df982407ec112cfa474"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has demonstrated content knowledge in the subject or subjects the teacher teaches;</text></clause><clause id="id5eac21afb1f44d42af749586c2d342c4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has demonstrated the ability to work with students who are culturally and linguistically diverse; and</text></clause><clause id="id1305cacdf87d4bcd84980e9b0bc111c8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has demonstrated teaching skills, such as through—</text><subclause id="id5048b078e1f443e6a157e741afb8dccb"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a teacher performance assessment; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idd8eb4143ff774b8c95547560ca82b100"><enum>(II)</enum><text>other measures of teaching skills, as determined by the State; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id167c1ab844e845468657a889b73639d7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>when used with respect to any other educator not described in subparagraphs (A) or (B), means an educator who has completed an appropriate preparation program and has a certification or licensure described in paragraph (2)(A) for the State in which the educator is employed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="ida600d911fc794854982519208736bf47"><enum>(22)</enum><header>School leader residency program</header><text>The term <term>school leader residency program</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2002 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id89c755b361744e2eafeb3c4e89931ec9"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Social and emotional learning</header><text>The term <term>social and emotional learning</term> means the process through which all young people and adults acquire and apply the knowledge, skills, and attitudes to develop healthy identities, manage emotions, achieve personal and collective goals, empathize with others, establish and maintain supportive relationships, and make responsible and caring decisions. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5b3d1387c5fa4b4b8f7a0c4195af3a0e"><enum>(24)</enum><header>Specialized instructional support personnel</header><text>The term <term>specialized instructional support personnel</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID5A0C6E1CFB1043B4AB1FB41178498CE0"><enum>(25)</enum><header>Teacher mentoring</header><text>The term <term>teacher mentoring</term> means the mentoring of new or prospective teachers through a program that—</text><subparagraph id="ID685DD114A79048FEA1B9E5C6A229A405"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes clear criteria for the selection of teacher mentors who will provide role model relationships for mentees, which criteria shall be developed by the eligible partnership and based on measures of teacher effectiveness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idda2d839eddcd4e668b1f5f10d516951d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides evidence-based training for such mentors, including instructional strategies for literacy instruction and classroom management (including approaches that improve the schoolwide climate for learning, which may include positive behavioral interventions and supports and social and emotional learning);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID5BBA371C257345948602C16BD76219EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides regular and ongoing opportunities for mentors and mentees to observe each other's teaching methods in classroom settings during the day in a high-need school in the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDCB068A5486D64FC296D223744BB08240"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides paid release time for mentors, as applicable;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDC44F8ECF330940F5AEF91F16755CC263"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provides mentoring to each mentee by a colleague who teaches in the same field, grade, or subject as the mentee;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID4E85C2ADCC45434397B928587E169CDC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>promotes evidence-based research on—</text><clause id="ID645CB95004DE4F4789B2AC62BB312F88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>teaching and learning;</text></clause><clause id="ID27AFA720C49346C1AFB3CCBB7E04A36E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assessment of student learning;</text></clause><clause id="ID43B664A7CDB045069016E3D61947D4A6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the development of teaching skills through the use of instructional and behavioral interventions; and</text></clause><clause id="ID70F78D7A824C46139692CDF3DA1745C1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the improvement of the mentees' capacity to measurably advance student learning;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idE9336903B8D24746A2B677FC1F6FDA13"><enum>(G)</enum><text>integrates technology effectively into curricula and instruction, including technology consistent with the principles of universal design for learning and technology to collect, manage, and analyze data to improve teaching and learning for the purpose of improving student learning outcomes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID7AAC5B673EBB41DF99D84546E5B108ED"><enum>(H)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="IDD4F8E63FD9184216A7A9FA34E245FEB2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>common planning time or regularly scheduled collaboration for the mentor and mentee; and</text></clause><clause id="ID8C654AF3D8B44FF39197A89F6FD9FFFA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>joint professional development opportunities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID45DD5CE2DA08492EB21284E5553A8BA8"><enum>(26)</enum><header>Teacher residency program</header><text>The term <term>teacher residency program</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2002 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID2246DF38A5E34AE48C2CE4F5E3B0461D"><enum>(27)</enum><header>Teaching skills</header><text>The term <term>teaching skills</term> means skills that enable a teacher to—</text><subparagraph id="ID5D5C37D5BEFC427EB7E8319BDEE7187F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increase student learning, achievement, and the ability to apply knowledge;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID3552FA534867469A8C2DA1071DAC0DC7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>convey and explain academic subject matter;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDA51E6B24595E4446B0EAE9354B3554C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>teach higher-order analytical, evaluation, problem-solving, and communication skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDBED1B4F984AD4D52AFBB29D210BA58B5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>employ strategies grounded in the disciplines of teaching and learning that—</text><clause id="ID33EDF7CE1F624E2584E87F1B89FB345E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are based on evidence, practice, and research, where applicable, related to teaching and learning;</text></clause><clause id="ID794E21B6DDF4480794AEF439A95BB99D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are specific to academic subject matter; and</text></clause><clause id="ID678AE24CA29C48A4AE2E666B9FEDE842"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>focus on the identification of students' specific learning needs, particularly students with disabilities, students who are English learners, students who are gifted and talented, and students with low literacy levels, and the tailoring of academic instruction to such needs;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8dcaec52714844b19aa9ba8b0186ad38"><enum>(E)</enum><text>design and conduct an ongoing assessment of evidence of student learning, which may include the use of formative or diagnostic assessments, performance-based assessments, project-based assessments, or portfolio assessments, that measures higher-order thinking skills (including application, analysis, synthesis, and evaluation) and use this information to inform and personalize instruction;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfd72959dbc474ec4a4659dc7d7c5eebe"><enum>(F)</enum><text>support the social, emotional, and academic achievement of all students, including by effectively creating an inclusive classroom environment, and implementing positive behavioral interventions, trauma-informed care, and other support strategies that enhance student motivation and engagement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id581f74ae0d314a1e993227487dd35df0"><enum>(G)</enum><text>incorporate the principles of universal design for learning; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id25588dd1cccb4d34baca3fb61d01db08"><enum>(H)</enum><text>integrate technology effectively into curricula and instruction, including technology consistent with the principles of universal design for learning and technology to collect, manage, and analyze data to improve teaching and learning for the purpose of improving student learning outcomes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID7BDEBEF9EAE54A3EB22C2D98342420BC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>communicate and work with parents, and involve parents in their children's education; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID7E7F3B82245A4A38A02FE556A0726F56"><enum>(J)</enum><text>use, in the case of an early childhood educator, age-appropriate and developmentally appropriate strategies and practices for children in early childhood education programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id34c71020c6694eacb576ce5d0e47681c"><enum>(28)</enum><header>Teacher performance assessment</header><text>The term <term>teacher performance assessment</term> means a pre-service assessment used to measure teacher performance that is approved by the State and is—</text><subparagraph id="id00dfe40e64f64e8d947581ea5e0b201d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>based on professional teaching standards;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9090d13dac9a4e86a47aa99fb0809cd8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>used to measure the effectiveness of a teacher's—</text><clause id="id9e55f7f838b7441c94bc2600eaeec095"><enum>(i)</enum><text>curriculum planning;</text></clause><clause id="id51c29ac02ea34683a169517d51f2322b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>instruction of students, including appropriate plans and modifications for students who are English learners and students who are children with disabilities;</text></clause><clause id="id49d08c0b1b2847b49c7899506f99f436"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>assessment of students, including analysis of evidence of student learning; and</text></clause><clause id="ida302cdf67f6c4787be06f4f55f1b7134"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>ability to advance student learning;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide7abccc9d43d43fa9d0805b02e9eeb35"><enum>(C)</enum><text>validated based on professional assessment standards;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9254fa6ef51b4b599d626eeb4615e2f7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>reliably scored by trained evaluators, with appropriate oversight of the process to ensure consistency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id912c60760b464aa8bf205eb54cb338ed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>used to support continuous improvement of educator practice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id1de6eb56a6de4b25849c06b0a8517d3d"><enum>(29)</enum><header>Teacher preparation entity</header><text>The term <term>teacher preparation entity</term> means an institution of higher education, a nonprofit organization, or an organization that is approved by the State to prepare teachers to be effective in the classroom.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id30dd4aec1196429d88f47e88737ba17a"><enum>(30)</enum><header>Teacher preparation program</header><text>The term <term>teacher preparation program</term> means a program offered by a teacher preparation entity that leads to a specific State teacher certification. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><part commented="no" id="IDBB7F2E0FD87547D48CC64A67BCD16AAC"><enum>A</enum><header>Grants to States for strengthening educator preparation</header><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="idDD9A2F18A9A74D21BA23DE72706A007E"><enum>201.</enum><header>Allotments to States</header><subsection id="idBCB7C84B73024B568178196BE200B9E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><paragraph id="idB9E0BA352F5945E29D46DD35C0DDB6F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reservation of Funds</header><text>From the total amount appropriated to carry out this part for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reserve—</text><subparagraph id="idA1B55668548F401F9D43E07DED8B0C01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one-half of 1 percent for allotments for the outlying areas (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965) to carry out this part, to be distributed among those outlying areas on the basis of their relative need, as determined by the Secretary, in accordance with the purpose of this part; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2BD0D31292EB4AB4B551DB324ACEEEDF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one-half of 1 percent for the Secretary of the Interior to carry out this part for schools operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id15C699034EA94A79A8DFC0B2052DD732"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Formula</header><text>From amounts made available to carry out this part and not reserved under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall allot funds to each State having an approved application under this section to carry out this part in proportion to each such State’s share of funding under part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, except that no State shall receive less than 0.5 percent of the amounts made available to carry out this paragraph. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9540685ABC464592AC8B269D781C83E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>Notwithstanding section 103, in this section the term <term>State</term> means the several States of the United States, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idDB45953193D34E2BB2B590CC1A514351"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><subparagraph id="id4D1FAE5441844B4F858F56B61631059E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Development of the strategic plan</header><text>Each State may use an amount equal to not more than 30 percent of the amount allotted to the State, for a period not to exceed 1 year, to carry out activities related to the development of the strategic plan, as described in subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5B3FE4C011914D5A8C9A564E676437CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent years</header><text>For each year following the first year after receiving an allotment under this section, the State—</text><clause id="id986968A8A41C43F398970C410F337AA7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall use not less than 95 percent of the amount allotted to the State under this section to carry out activities described in subsection (d); and</text></clause><clause id="id617D3D09F9484443A7F4B51623815D29"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may use not more than 5 percent of the amounts allotted to the State under this section for administration and accountability and reporting requirements.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idC8C22D015C1F4F5698F13944166FF942"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each State desiring an allotment under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require. Each such application shall contain—</text><paragraph id="id50CB8311437C4111B7F1FC32CFF223B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the identification of a State agency to lead the grant, which shall be determined by the Governor in consultation with the State educational agency;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id686CFDA70CE648A3A4FCA0DD2016F6E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the certification or licensing requirements with respect to each form of certification or licensure described in section 200(b)(2) for early childhood, elementary school, and secondary school teachers in the State at the time of the application;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4bc624c9cd0a49e7a39ebb901f647297"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the certification or licensing requirements with respect to each form of certification or licensure described in section 200(b)(2) for specialized instructional support personnel; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD3898A951A2446F7B99714A6AE5F4024"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of the State authorization requirements for teacher preparation programs (including alternate and traditional routes to certification) and the number of teacher preparation programs authorized in the State (including alternative and traditional routes to certification);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idEFB60A46690544F79C61D24DAD5A8035"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a description of the teacher preparation needs assessment that the State will conduct, including how the State will assess—</text><subparagraph id="id454FEFB8D42F4DAA9DE54815ADA1C8E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>teacher workforce needs for public preschool, elementary, and secondary schools in the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9a9955d317e34859964d64a5f374248f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number and percentage of teachers of record who are not profession-ready as described in section 200(b)(20)(B); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idE4BD67CB96134D4695230D8DF674DBB7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the demographics of the student population and the demographics of the educator workforce, and the extent to which the educator workforce reflects the demographics of the student population;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4EBF8612D375425DB61C723A53E25DC7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>high-need fields, high-need schools, and high-need local educational agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6D5D78156A2945D580D77F57AD8A935F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the State's educator equity plan described in section 1111(g)(1)(B) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1f50e1010b244577b32ef20a3f4039e3"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the extent to which currently authorized teacher preparation programs in the State are producing profession-ready candidates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id09A2BFC2FFE14904A9A861B99D2598B5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the capacity of programs that are authorized in the State, as of the time of the application, to meet the State's teacher workforce needs, including the capacity of—</text><clause id="id5436D7D84A2E4352BF86950DDB8FB89B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>pipeline programs, such as associate degree to baccalaureate transfer pathway programs with community colleges;</text></clause><clause id="idf80902ec17bc4108800f7ea186a3c42b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text><quote>grow your own</quote> programs that provide pathways to standard teacher certification through partnerships between local educational agencies, institutions of higher education, and community-based organizations to recruit and prepare community members to become teachers in local schools;</text></clause><clause id="id1d45e989eae54b748c9ecbfad600cd06"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>career awareness programs, including career and technical education and other pathways, in public schools; and</text></clause><clause id="id2C393133A34E4D67B6475D0B404AA9B1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>programs to support the career progression of educators, including retention, leadership opportunities, and professional development;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0c17b9e96ea24a8e8a99d2e074e75244"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a description of the school leader, principal, and other educator preparation needs assessment that the State will conduct, including how the State will assess—</text><subparagraph id="id0d61aa7f0aaa448f9187b68c0caf47c5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the principal and other educator workforce needs for public preschools and elementary and secondary schools in the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id51092651dab54d13a3aaa0b084fae179"><enum>(B)</enum><text>high-need positions, high-need schools, and high-need local educational agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb110b54f240c4774a4b1339e6e28b5cb"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the extent to which authorized educator preparation programs in the State, as of the time of the application, are producing profession-ready candidates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddb4849fdb90f4771bf0c0e0db187ecdf"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the capacity of programs authorized in the State, as of the time of the application, to meet the State's principal and other educator needs, including meeting nationally recognized ratios for specialized instructional support personnel in schools, where applicable; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id3F5D3D3BF1B84818A794BEBC91C09D24"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a timeline for the State's activities to develop a strategic plan, including a timeline for stakeholder engagement with administrators of institutions of higher education, elementary school and secondary school principals and administrators, educator preparation programs, teachers, specialized instructional support personnel, parents, students, civil rights organizations, community-based organizations, and workforce development programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="idD85353F97DD1446FA8E1DFF6FA960398"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development of a strategic plan</header><text>During the first year after receiving an allotment under this section, a State may use not more than 30 percent of the funds allotted to conduct the needs assessments described in paragraphs (5) and (6) of subsection (b) and develop a strategic plan for the State to improve educator preparation programs to address the needs identified in paragraphs (5) and (6) of subsection (b). </text></subsection><subsection id="id2B360C3194CF46C48AF404B860687055"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Submission of strategic plan</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving an allotment under this section, each State shall submit a strategic plan to the Secretary, which shall contain the following information:</text><paragraph id="id444CD88663904E4E8F8DF1445E08634D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The State's goals relating to educator preparation, supporting quantitative and qualitative evidence for those goals, and intermediate and long-term implementation timelines. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id45E6BBA1AA44498EAD9430E48EF882DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The results of the needs assessments described in paragraphs (5) and (6) of subsection (b). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6680EB1D17754B799EDA39C89EEFB382"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The State's plan for meeting the educator workforce needs in the State, including how the State will prioritize institutions of higher education with the greatest share of prospective educators, institutions that enroll the highest percentage of prospective educators from underrepresented groups, and institutions of higher education with the highest placement of educators in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4FA31EE5CF334927A35907508C0B77CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The State’s plan for removing barriers to an inclusive and equitable workforce that supports the needs of populations that are underrepresented in the field of education, including teachers of color, first generation college students, and teachers with disabilities, including recruitment, preparation, and retention. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida6c4b4de1eb644858236fac72e27ff68"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header><text>A State shall use funds allotted under this section to implement the strategic plan submitted under subsection (d), which may include the following activities: </text><paragraph id="id876179C304794B0BAA6882507EE855B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Strengthening and professionalizing educator certification and licensure, and other credentialing, so that it aligns with evidence-based practices and high professional standards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8b1e1fac323b49d2906cf13399ef7581"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Developing and implementing an equitable and evidence-based State approval system for alternative route program providers and programs and traditional and alternative route programs at institutions of higher education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3e656e79139c4d259ad4e1e922a9e877"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Supporting the implementation of evidence-based performance assessments for teacher licensure or certification in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4da132fce9704e2aa7faaa6fe295808d"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Regularly assessing the workforce needs of prekindergarten through grade 12 educators across the State, including the diversity of the workforce, and providing that information to institutions of higher education that prepare educators in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id322BC065D2D545398B0B24CAB360DE3E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Providing transparency to the public as to how authorized educator preparation programs are meeting professional standards and requirements.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id10EA30AD6E3045B5A0D15B2075D218B0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Providing subgrants to partner institutions, consortia of partner institutions, or eligible partnerships, to enable those institutions and partnerships to carry out activities related to the strategic plan described in subsection (d), including—</text><subparagraph id="id146367d84445483e8586ac7444edecf0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>developing and offering induction, mentoring, or professional and leadership coaching for all novice teachers and principals in a high-need local educational agency, which shall be provided by faculty or staff at the institution of higher education and teachers and school leaders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7646426F0D41430CA10FD337EB899F39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing and offering professional development that brings research to practice for educators in schools of district partners; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8E68784BB8E748209316DD4F24D7CC82"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developing and offering second endorsement coursework;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idD99F8F1B1CD044BBA249F6FDAE2972F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>creating and expanding dual certification programs in special education and general education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6850F9DA71514A70AEBB80EA5BC44C46"><enum>(E)</enum><text>developing and offering ‘grow your own’ programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6CFED91A40C240A28EFF21214AB54830"><enum>(F)</enum><text>developing or strengthening career ladder positions for educators, such as teacher leaders, with certification requirements and coursework leading to certification, which may include nationally recognized, standards-based advanced certification;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id64C989B5A5B84735B8F63E6536B0DC99"><enum>(G)</enum><text>designing and implementing statewide pre-service residencies for teacher and principal candidates using the model described in section 202(e) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5596A7ADEE0B43C49737AFED3B1E0353"><enum>(H)</enum><text>developing and implementing a statewide best practices network for the preparation of profession-ready educators; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5709A658AFF0478D89A75CDBECD5FA30"><enum>(I)</enum><text>creating or expanding teaching fellows programs whereby individuals preparing to be teachers receive tuition waivers for use in comprehensive preparation provided by a teacher preparation program that includes extensive clinical experience that is tightly aligned to coursework, before becoming the teacher of record, in exchange for teaching in one of the identified workforce need areas in the State for a period of years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id56b54382b7bf44069620e4e791a38f13"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual report on the implementation of the strategic plan</header><text>Each State receiving an allotment under this section shall make publicly available a report, on an annual basis, on the implementation of the strategic plan submitted under subsection (d). </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="id728E000657CD4FE39367279B5F79DF43"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><paragraph commented="no" id="idA901949BD30946E289FCD2823CF8131E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>A State shall provide for activities described in this section in such State, an amount which is equal to or greater than the average amount provided for such activities by such State during the 3 most recent preceding fiscal years for which satisfactory data are available.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="idA859C43FE31B4A668D7F63EE794AD962"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), the Secretary may waive the requirements of this subsection if the Secretary determines that a waiver would be equitable due to—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="id5757489538274478BAE11E91455DDA71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>exceptional or uncontrollable circumstances, such as a natural disaster or a change in the organizational structure of the State; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id9D74565020494A1BA2B628154554CC11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a precipitous decline in the financial resources of the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="idb659de3de03a41e7ab4a1a294177309c"><enum>(h)</enum><header>State maintenance of equity</header><text>As a condition of receiving an allotment under this section, a State shall meet the maintenance of equity requirements in section 2004(b) of the of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/2">Public Law 117–2</external-xref>). </text></subsection><subsection id="id60759DB729494085855E832F66CD2204"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available under this section shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, and local funds that would otherwise be expended to carry out activities under this section. </text></subsection></section><section id="id43ad0f69565249c7bd9c906b4d87fc18"><enum>202.</enum><header>Accountability for equitable access to profession-ready teachers</header><subsection id="id3c5d6094327b4123afae7b3efe5a981e"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Institutional and program annual reports</header><paragraph id="id0aa53f2761144aeabcdb480b7f5a31b7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reporting</header><text>Each teacher preparation entity approved to operate teacher preparation programs in the State and that receives or enrolls students receiving Federal assistance shall report annually to the State and the general public, in a uniform and comprehensible manner that conforms with the definitions and methods established by the Secretary, the following: </text><subparagraph id="id58e05a9b6082442181010e5cdd65dfd4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Pass rates</header><text>For the most recent year for which the information is available for each teacher preparation program offered by the teacher preparation entity, the following: </text><clause commented="no" id="id14555221dd8d4f1eae0e3aa42949c419"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), for those students who took the assessments used for teacher certification or licensure by the State in which the entity is located and are enrolled in the teacher preparation program, the percentage of such students who passed such assessment.</text></clause><clause id="id60e299891f4a44bbb1f1c2d8fa1702ed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In the case of an entity that requires a valid and reliable teacher performance assessment in order to complete the preparation program, the entity may submit in lieu of the information described in clause (i) the pass rate of students taking the teacher performance assessment. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id59c29214d4754c9c83fd750b2c97b333"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entity information</header><text>A description of the following:</text><clause id="id49edf8df3def464693b363f35465880f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of students in the entity (disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status).</text></clause><clause id="id3ba1a9dbdd46459fb5da73f604e02807"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of hours of supervised clinical preparation required for each program.</text></clause><clause id="idcc730667bd4f4ec49cce553c7312a75a"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The total number of students who have completed programs for certification or licensure (disaggregated by subject area and by race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status, except that such disaggregation, consistent with applicable privacy laws, shall not be required in a case in which the result would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual student).</text></clause><clause id="idc60e515d83b34954b63fa44be04c3d07"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The criteria for admission into the program.</text></clause><clause id="id9036c1e99fe84401a0c2aab22578b633"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The number of full-time equivalent faculty, adjunct faculty, and students in supervised clinical experience. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id914cfa4fb9b04844b2e3c768701db6e1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Accreditation</header><text>Whether the program or entity is accredited by a specialized accrediting agency recognized by the Secretary for accreditation of professional teacher education programs. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id79311446a5ed471088f79c9062741adf"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Designation as low-performing</header><text>Which programs (if any) offered by the entity have been designated as low-performing by the State under section 207(a). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide62747f64523444b870c2fcde7193fe6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual State report on teacher preparation</header><paragraph id="id32e14ff6e5a6415db2f9a73aad5244fd"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State that receives funds under this part shall provide to the Secretary, and make widely available to the general public, in a uniform and comprehensible manner that conforms with the definitions and methods established by the Secretary, an annual State report on educator preparation in the State, both for traditional teacher preparation programs and for alternative routes to State certification or licensure programs, which shall include not less than the following:</text><subparagraph id="id1089f7766de74bc4a6e2d14e2c42591e"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of the teacher certification and licensure assessments, including teacher performance assessments, and any other certification and licensure requirements, used by the State, including evidence on validity and reliability of those assessments and the methods used to determine performance standards.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id30325ab7efb4418a9555fc5a9e676048"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The standards and criteria that prospective teachers must meet to—</text><clause id="id7F4D04020159466D8B69A6E21AE0F6DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>attain certification or licensure described under each of subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of section 200(b)(2); and</text></clause><clause id="id1ECD9BF9018F4000971393AC94E7FDAB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be certified or licensed to teach particular academic subjects, areas, or grades within the State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7cb0b2086de34bf9a5d3e16f30482cb1"><enum>(C)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="ide08c3cbf20d544b7982f77acde478ca9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of certifications or licensures described under each of subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of section 200(b)(2) issued by the State, disaggregated by grade and subject area.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="id233E3CAFFD5B40AA8DA6FAC44F84E9EC" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number and percentage of teachers who received a certification or licensure described in section 200(b)(2)(A) and who did not complete any formal teacher preparation program, but have received such certification or licensure by alternative means such as passing a test, disaggregated by field. </text></clause><clause commented="no" indent="up1" id="id40411DBD091143FF85AF665E2684A929"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The number and percentage of teachers of record who are not profession-ready, disaggregated by field.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab7e8bbd01244d12bddcf398d6f96336"><enum>(D)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id5342bf6c42c24a28a38098245270d32c"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), for each of the assessments used by the State for teacher certification or licensure, the pass rates of such assessments for individuals having completed each teacher preparation entity in the State and for all such entities, disaggregated by subject area, race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status, except that such disaggregation shall not be required in a case in which the result would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual.</text></clause><clause id="idb8cf4937cc0b4617b59bd0bcc0a11f7f" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In the case of a State that has implemented a valid and reliable teacher performance assessment, the State may submit in lieu of the information described in clause (i) the pass rate of students taking the teacher performance assessment, disaggregated by subject area, race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status, except that such disaggregation shall not be required in a case in which the result would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual student.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5e0b61441cae4d4ba0055d0b149bf126"><enum>(E)</enum><text>For each teacher preparation program in the State the following:</text><clause id="idaa58f6fa6d1642b69ce9238c51ae7ed3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of students in the program (disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status).</text></clause><clause id="id2f594cfc0d2b41228f3735a65088c45a"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of hours of supervised clinical preparation required.</text></clause><clause id="id660d83900720400ba2ad9f6558a587c8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Whether such program has been identified as low-performing and during which years of operation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3d70c7514fd1464796739eb2c113508a"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A description of alternative routes to teacher certification or licensure in the State (including any such routes operated by entities that are not institutions of higher education), if any, including, for each of the assessments used by the State for teacher certification or licensure, the percentage of individuals participating in such routes, or who have completed such routes during the two-year period preceding the date for which the determination is made, who passed each such assessment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id85b59e379ea04de79831d08c0e0e2712"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The percentage of candidates completing programs in each field, including special education, who use alternate routes compared to those who complete traditional programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id021ee02b7849461d8a5ade780bb92d02"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A description of the State’s criteria for assessing the performance of teacher preparation programs within institutions of higher education in the State. Such criteria shall include indicators of the academic content knowledge and teaching skills of students enrolled in such programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1fcf737af63a45f2ba2859beb7f1255e"><enum>(I)</enum><text>For each teacher preparation program in the State—</text><clause id="idf39acb14d3c54f63b806b742572de831"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of students in the program, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status (except that such disaggregation shall not be required in a case in which the number of students in a category would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual student); and</text></clause><clause id="id6e3a41724dc94668b0d82b5dd57e657e"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the range and average number of hours of supervised clinical experience required for those in the program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id43d4b4b0f3784ee4ba82df63c57df410"><enum>(J)</enum><text>For the State as a whole, and for each teacher preparation entity in the State, the number of teachers prepared, in the aggregate and reported separately by the following: </text><clause id="id2fe52fe1a2d4476c91013b3753151ca0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Area of certification or licensure.</text></clause><clause id="id0ce3aabd241e466c99cec8b395df09d2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Academic major.</text></clause><clause id="id4f08c456b0d640a38ce9819d9ea4e7c7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Subject area for which the teacher has been prepared to teach.</text></clause><clause id="id8cf34d3322484a2ab19fed410cdf7ada"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The relationship of the subject area and grade span of teachers graduated by the teacher preparation entity to the teacher workforce needs of the State. </text></clause><clause id="idb59314454b144f3e9e8f3f08420232e7"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The percentage of teachers graduated teaching in high-need schools.</text></clause><clause id="id6a30ac3c493c452b87678a351da7da93"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Race, ethnicity, sex, and disability status.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbff41bd85507460b8e0822cf1df659d4"><enum>(K)</enum><text>A comparison of standard licenses and certifications issued to the areas of identified teacher shortage in the State. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc9cc692063d44622b2fa74e6a4ce78a7"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The capacity of the statewide longitudinal data system to report valid and reliable outcome data on the graduates of teacher preparation entities in the State and where available the results of such data on the following: </text><clause id="idffe14daf65c64c54ab05843ab8bffaa5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Job placement of program completers within 12 months of graduation.</text></clause><clause id="id56ddc6d338cb4b28b42f91182af319c4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Retention of program completers in teaching after 3 years.</text></clause><clause id="idd08ef7b2a6214bde91413080f9e330bb"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Other outcome indicators used by the State, such as average results from teacher evaluations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide3375f3060b84c9bb8d5c609fd79065d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition against creating a national list</header><text>The Secretary shall not create a national list or ranking of States, institutions, or schools using the information provided under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id43965d2655674e06af5fee8a6958d848"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No requirement for reporting on students not residing in the State</header><text>Nothing in this section shall require a State to report data on program completers who do not reside in such State. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id929282245f6c41a782ac9fa403b0cb1a"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Data quality</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe regulations to ensure the reliability, validity, integrity, accuracy, and consistency of the data submitted pursuant to this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id93fe175d9ffc46f18a8370a462f227d6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report of the secretary on teacher preparation</header><paragraph id="ida6747913317245509192c178649377f1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary shall, until 2025, annually provide to the authorizing committees, and publish and make widely available, a report on teacher qualifications and preparation in the United States, including all the information reported in subparagraphs (A) through (L) of subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0b80a7e0a5544d68a8f82458458c5491"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enhanced report</header><subparagraph id="idDACC24C43C7C4492BE42A26030A4B26A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The Secretary shall instruct the National Center for Education Statistics to convene an expert panel that includes researchers and practitioners to study and make recommendations for revised reporting of teacher qualifications and preparation in the United States. The recommendations shall include suggestions for how to—</text><clause id="id36417ADE839A4F9CB4F8E4ED2A41728B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consolidate and streamline reporting across existing Federal and State requirements and Federal data collections to provide a concise and robust set of State and national indicators on the size, diversity, and quality of the teacher workforce and the equitable distribution of profession-ready teachers; and</text></clause><clause id="id78B96D1088044E71BC04A0D02FD8AE90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reduce reporting burdens on educator preparation entities, local educational agencies, and States. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id37DF0AD4FDAF4516BFB616EB6213DC3F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revised reporting</header><text>The Secretary shall publish revised reporting requirements of teacher qualifications and preparation in the United States in the Federal Register with sufficient time for the new reporting requirements to be in place for 2025. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id88432e932c5948f88181dca27630bbe3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>In the case of a teacher preparation program with fewer than ten scores reported on any single initial teacher certification or licensure assessment during an academic year, the Secretary shall collect and publish, and make publicly available, information with respect to an average pass rate on each State certification or licensure assessment taken over a three-year period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9bbd7ecf1e974d27a3a415c08283a27a"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary, to the extent practicable, shall coordinate the information collected and published under this part among States for individuals who took State teacher certification or licensure assessments in a State other than the State in which the individual received the individual’s most recent degree. </text></subsection></section><section id="id1c6b1842c4094235be3d3e6d8478739d"><enum>203.</enum><header>State functions</header><subsection id="id391FE3000C434A78A8327429E3378866"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State assessment</header><paragraph id="id892a6ec6f68047acbfdc9ec296bf85cf"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order to receive funds under this part, a State shall conduct an assessment to identify low-performing teacher preparation programs in the State and to assist such programs through the provision of technical assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id668d462ca8f04ba7b2541976aacda7d3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Provision of low-performing list</header><text>Each State described in paragraph (1) shall— </text><subparagraph id="id5ff74f368194492b80b21dae1e33eb3a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide the Secretary with an annual list of low-performing teacher preparation programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4ecb9163e6734c338b8f62e3f322f305"><enum>(B)</enum><text>report any teacher preparation program that has been closed and the reasons for such closure; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1f0aaa134b514000bfa379fb887e8091"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describe the criteria determined under paragraph (3) for identifying low performing programs. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idbb595ce7a2c04a5888fdc92ed81065bb"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determination of low-performing programs</header><text>The levels of performance and the criteria for meeting those levels for purposes of the assessment under paragraph (1) shall be determined by the State in consultation with a representative group of community stakeholders, including, at a minimum, representatives of leaders and faculty of traditional and alternative route teacher preparation programs, prekindergarten through 12th grade leaders and instructional staff, current teacher candidates participating in traditional and alternative route teacher preparation programs, the State's standards board or other appropriate standards body, and other stakeholders identified by the State. In making such determination, the State shall consider multiple measures and the information reported by teacher preparation entities under section 202. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0ea70f426c264fb397eb80c8536b4995"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting and improvement</header><text>In order to receive funds under this part, a State shall— </text><paragraph id="id743045b1d59c48e59f23f18e149f8b66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>report any teacher preparation programs described in subparagraphs (A) or (B) of subsection (a)(2) to the Secretary; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0a21d52a7ad447a8aa9d7a8c7c35b988"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a period of improvement and redesign (as established by the State) for programs identified as low-performing under subsection (a); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9244aea48e1844d390e6702bc018971a"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide programs identified as low-performing with technical assistance for a period of not longer than 5 years; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb92fa54412d344068ab80511dc227afd"><enum>(4)</enum><text>subject low-performing programs that have not improved to the provisions described in subsection (c) (as determined by the State). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id97e05d741afd49ecaace86ebacf8336a"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination of eligibility</header><text>Any teacher preparation program that is low-performing and has not improved for a period of 5 years— </text><paragraph id="idb378c5c1517a429a889441d834b1fc34"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be ineligible for any funding for professional development activities awarded by the Department; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id111ab73f316845d885d1f62c11051a93"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not be permitted to provide new awards under subpart 9 of part A of title IV; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id81e6320b2ba14b4fae8b4047fded8a00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall provide transitional support, including remedial services if necessary, for students enrolled in the program in the year prior to such closure. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9c86a4e1d65e43b29df8ebc2067a63da"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application of the requirements</header><text>The requirements of this section shall apply to both traditional teacher preparation programs and alternative routes to State certification or licensure programs. </text></subsection></section><section id="ID7692F301E2F64E149E1D0217F42B8212"><enum>204.</enum><header>General provisions</header><subsection id="IDD14F8C80ED49466C9188CA9FAD69DD71"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Methods</header><text>In complying with sections 202 and 203, the Secretary shall ensure that States and institutions of higher education use fair and equitable methods in reporting and that the reporting methods do not reveal personally identifiable information.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="ID9761DD0C527D48969B31BE28EBD307F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>For each State that does not use content assessments as a means of ensuring that all teachers teaching within the State meet the applicable State certification or licensure requirements, including any requirements for certification obtained through alternative routes to certification, in accordance with the State plan submitted or revised under section 1111 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, and that each person employed as a special education teacher in the State who teaches elementary school or secondary school meets the qualifications described in section 612(a)(14)(C) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="IDC090E8DE92FA44DBBBA03666ECE4CECF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, collect data comparable to the data required under this part from States, local educational agencies, institutions of higher education, or other entities that administer such assessments to teachers or prospective teachers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="IDC426C53218444372AF5449D029242325"><enum>(2)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of this part, use such data to carry out requirements of this part related to assessments, pass rates, and scaled scores.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID69F6C1E8902D4C948AF172A1E51BDA80"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Release of information to educator preparation programs</header><paragraph id="ID2F0C5945A5834275AB1101C6426B5892"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purpose of improving educator preparation programs, a State that receives funds under this part, or that participates as a member of a partnership, consortium, or other entity that receives such funds, shall provide to an educator preparation program, upon the request of the educator preparation program, any and all pertinent education-related information that—</text><subparagraph id="ID0114F9F2EBB84E68A87ACE124FEC6DBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may enable the educator preparation program to evaluate the effectiveness of the program's graduates or the program itself; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID91C65DE1257346C5A70DD8350228FB82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is possessed, controlled, or accessible by the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID7A1F6270449945DCBE5F02CB6EC9B832"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content of information</header><text>The information described in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="ID039CD08353CA41F79D06524DECE194FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall include an identification of specific individuals who graduated from the educator preparation program to enable the educator preparation program to evaluate the information provided to the program from the State with the program's own data about the specific courses taken by, and field experiences of, the individual graduates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID37599A1628704F7F8C70C7DBD3B3A98B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include—</text><clause id="ID97ABC15EDD324C7C8089BCE28F0F67E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>kindergarten through grade 12 academic achievement and demographic data, without revealing personally identifiable information about an individual student, for students who have been taught by graduates of the educator preparation program; </text></clause><clause id="IDCB3D421CD4034FE7A4C4756AA0104F1D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>teacher effectiveness evaluations for teachers who graduated from the educator preparation program; and</text></clause><clause id="idfeaa0f8de2304a54b242c2aac7bc9665"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>survey data on program quality as it relates to the preparedness on different aspects of teaching or school leadership from preparation program completers and principals in schools or superintendents in local educational agencies where completers are placed. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id08311880FCC04B928750EC9444A5D570"><enum>205.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this part $500,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 5 succeeding fiscal years.</text></section></part><part commented="no" id="id3346D6AB135646719D4A66EA4855904D"><enum>B</enum><header>Grants to institutions</header><section id="id3D8C31A79AE44079830B6DD9CF2EC508"><enum>220.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this part are to—</text><paragraph id="id4f80595b56bd4913a1d9f9bff497f630"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expand the pool of profession-ready diverse educators to meet the workforce demands of high-need schools and high-need fields;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id143a061c48684362aaba6e13645c1ca7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that new teachers, principals, and other educators are profession-ready and prepared to meet the learning and social and emotional needs of a diverse student population in a range of settings, including rural and urban areas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDE77368DC86854C51B789FA881DEB826E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>strengthen the quality of prospective and new teachers, principals, and other educators by strengthening the preparation of prospective teachers, principals, and other educators and enhancing professional development activities for new teachers, principals, and other educators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID83F0B4D4296B42D084098C5248348BCD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recruit individuals, particularly individuals from underrepresented populations and individuals from other occupations, to become teachers, principals, and other educators; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6A93CA0C6C7C49AFAA90611C97D51E0C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>build and strengthen partnerships between educator preparation programs within institutions of higher education and local educational agencies and high-need schools in order to meet the needs of those agencies and schools staffing needs. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="id95B417CEA1DB44ECAB8ED486EF15F0B2"><enum>221.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection commented="no" id="id7dd9c622d3424f4e90b8c9faa2366ea7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this part $500,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 5 succeeding fiscal years. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="id54416C3351E1400F957A4ED53565AE89"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Minimum appropriations for each subpart</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that not less than 25 percent of the funds appropriated to carry out this part for a fiscal year are allocated for each of subparts 1, 2, and 3 of this part. </text></subsection></section><subpart id="id7764424C78FA4EC7897F854009BE3427" style="OLC"><enum>1</enum><header>Educator quality partnership grants</header><section id="IDD7C3B73082C1430ABC79D56A8F9961D6"><enum>222.</enum><header>Partnership grants</header><subsection id="ID4470CBACE09E4BF29A0F7BE68030A928"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>From amounts made available under section 221, the Secretary is authorized to award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible partnerships, to enable the eligible partnerships to carry out the activities described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="ID82F885F3CEB64466A37E9CA890A94B76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each eligible partnership desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. Each such application shall contain—</text><paragraph id="ida0630ea2e929492e93b4453103d5df55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a needs assessment of the partners in the eligible partnership with respect to the preparation, ongoing training, professional development, and retention of general education teachers, special education teachers, multilingual education teachers, principals, other educators (including specialized instructional support personnel), school librarians, and counselors, and, as applicable, early childhood educators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID17F129AF028F4152A04192D1CAAA7EFA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the extent to which the program to be carried out with grant funds, as described in subsection (c), will prepare profession-ready educators with strong teaching, leadership, and other professional skills necessary to increase learning and academic achievement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID509BC186B7034608847BBD2442AFF890"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of how such program will prepare profession-ready teachers, principals, and other educators to understand and use research and data to modify and improve classroom instruction and improve student motivation and engagement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDB25FA44CBFD14F11A5C4C309FFE15F52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of—</text><subparagraph id="IDF5EDA63C831E448C90BEA9DAE02F5FB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the eligible partnership will coordinate strategies and activities assisted under the grant with other teacher, principal, and other educator preparation or professional development programs, including programs funded under part A of this title, the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, and the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, and through the National Science Foundation; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID0FA5764CD5A141F29BF6007AB93E8093"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the activities of the partnership will be consistent with State and local innovations and activities, and other education innovations and activities, that promote educator quality, diversity, and student academic achievement; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id420ea3d408c64386b45196891d9fcd19"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the eligible partnership will develop strong partnerships between local educational agencies and institutions of higher education within the partnership and community connections (which may include collaboration with teacher and school leader representatives within the local educational agency) to ensure that candidates develop an understanding of the students and families in the communities in which they will be teaching, prepare candidates to teach in those communities, and understand school contexts to address needs in the local educational agency;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDE4E9C2F3C86B4589AECA7584C61643D1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment that describes the resources available to the eligible partnership, including—</text><subparagraph id="ID8EC6ADC4A59948079C8B6E582D815227"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the integration of funds from other related sources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID2AFAA19B7633450CBB9BBBD4DDB71DB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the intended use of the grant funds; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDAAE8B8BED8CB4D1398C4877481EDC891"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the commitment of the resources of the partnership to the activities assisted under this section, including financial support, faculty participation, and time commitments, and to the continuation of the activities when the grant ends;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDC4007F66C8034686B3EF1F4A14FA4F0E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a description of—</text><subparagraph id="ID634D800428FD4CA2B3644B4D8D40335E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the eligible partnership will meet the purposes of this part;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDC7AF2BECEF4E46F8A5D31C227F1AB5CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the partnership will carry out the activities required under subsection (d), (e) or (f), based on the needs identified in paragraph (1), with the goal of providing a pipeline of diverse profession-ready educators needed by the local educational agency or schools that are part of the eligible partnership;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID1AA5DB28CCE145B2A2CBCA732E4F1543"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if the partnership chooses to use funds under this section for a project or activities under subsection (g), how the partnership will carry out such project or required activities based on the needs identified in paragraph (1), with the goals of meeting the workforce needs of the partner local educational agency or schools that are part of the eligible partnership through the provision of profession-ready diverse educators;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDDE91131F73874B0ABD7FA69F9AC40EA6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the partnership's evaluation plan under section 224;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID1653DDD0527E486F959B48F1A0D22590"><enum>(E)</enum><text>how the partnership will align the teacher preparation program under subsection (d) with the—</text><clause id="IDBD2DE5B3754D4EE185820B291DB54041"><enum>(i)</enum><text>State early learning standards for early childhood education programs, as appropriate, and with the relevant domains of early childhood development; </text></clause><clause id="IDE4510C6BC18845E28B927C5497EE3C91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>State academic standards under section 1111(b)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, established by the State in which the partnership is located; and</text></clause><clause id="ida61470578b604c8ebbce3ed34362ea54"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>activities identified under section 2101 and section 2103 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 and where applicable, the school support and improvement activities identified under section 1111(d) of that Act; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID03659A012D734110B0DA327FD524E9C1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>how the partnership will prepare educators to teach and work with students with disabilities, including training related to early identification of students with disabilities and participation as a member of individualized education program teams, as defined in section 614(d)(1)(B) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDE3F5CEE070D64553A4A2D5FD433E8D47"><enum>(G)</enum><text>how the partnership will prepare educators to teach and work with students who are English learners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1ed0aa9424f2477481fd72bd2f33a13f"><enum>(H)</enum><text>how the partnership will prepare educators to teach diverse students, including students of different races, ethnicities, language, gender identity or sexual orientation, and students with disabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idF7328A1846C44340A4E07267BABEA5ED"><enum>(I)</enum><text>how the partnership will design, implement, or enhance a year-long and evidence-based educator pre-service clinical program component; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id626061527bda4867a9830a04654affe6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>with respect to the induction program required as part of the activities carried out under this section—</text><subparagraph id="id278be89fcc9847b1a5b54d1c09a8e6f9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the educator preparation program will design and implement an induction program to support all new educators who are prepared by the educator preparation program in the partnership and who are employed in the high-need local educational agency in the partnership, and, to the extent practicable, all new educators who teach in such high-need local educational agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd1f8ef6c5bf74e44b2d13c8f3348cbc9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of how higher education faculty involved in the induction program will be able to substantially participate in an early childhood education program or an elementary school or secondary school classroom setting, as applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb739004598194d618ac148e4ba205b84"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of Grant Funds</header><text>An eligible partnership that receives a grant under this section—</text><paragraph id="id39ccf6d429d6417983261317a6921d83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall use grant funds to carry out a program for the pre-baccalaureate or post-baccalaureate preparation of teachers under subsection (d), a pre-service principal preparation program under subsection (e), a teaching or principal residency program under subsection (f), or a combination of such programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8e45073f2bf345b19c89eeac51989716"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may use funds to carry out other educator development programs under subsection (g), based upon the results of the needs assessment in subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="IDDB0FB99D6BE441C0B0C4F18B2DE75DE0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Partnership grants for the preparation of teachers</header><text>An eligible partnership that receives a grant to carry out a program for the preparation of teachers shall carry out a pre-baccalaureate teacher preparation program or a 5th year initial licensing program that includes all of the following:</text><paragraph id="ID2A1D505FAF0446AEA5679A0250258003"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Activities</header><subparagraph id="ID65E2DCFA4BA044DBA9CE81F7654939A8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Implementing activities, described in subparagraph (B), within each teacher preparation program and, as applicable, each preparation program for early childhood education programs, of the eligible partnership that is assisted under this section, to hold each program accountable for—</text><clause id="ID3C230A07B63C4E30837043A1E89336B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>preparing—</text><subclause id="IDAAA6E64E6AE14CD3A9E2C7443252FA90"><enum>(I)</enum><text>profession-ready teachers; and</text></subclause><subclause id="ID4CD0C9D616324BB29D481DA778D0AE1B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such teachers and, as applicable, early childhood educators, to understand evidence-based research related to teaching, learning, and classroom management, and the applicability of such practice and research, including strategies to incorporate universal design for learning, the effective use of technology, instructional techniques, strategies consistent with the principles of universal design for learning, and core competencies of social and emotional learning, and through positive behavioral interventions and support strategies to improve student achievement; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="ID7AF82C2AE64449A2BAF51DB39A73FBFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>promoting strong teaching skills and, as applicable, techniques for early childhood educators to improve children's cognitive, social, emotional, and physical development.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDF398B607F6664DBC8D5663C4A6D6A669"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required activities</header><text>The activities described in subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="ID9E9F06A927EE4BF2AD0580B4A7337793"><enum>(i)</enum><text>implementing teacher preparation program curriculum changes that improve, evaluate, and assess how well all prospective and new teachers develop teaching skills;</text></clause><clause id="ID0A763C9C92374AD9B2BA4BB375C4E98B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>using evidence-based research, where applicable, about teaching and learning so that all prospective teachers and, as applicable, early childhood educators—</text><subclause id="IDA39DD7F89D1C4F3B84EFC8E96B4BC4AD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>understand and can implement evidence-based teaching practices in classroom instruction;</text></subclause><subclause id="id266b3436976440e2818cbc149422be2c"><enum>(II)</enum><text>have knowledge of the scientific basis of how students learn, including the skills to recognize and evaluate student social and emotional competencies and needs;</text></subclause><subclause id="ID53BB068A948D488D85A0D7F298AAAF47"><enum>(III)</enum><text>possess skills to analyze student academic achievement data and other measures of student learning, and use such data and measures to improve classroom instruction and student engagement;</text></subclause><subclause id="ID2358946138A64AA8826FCE7D89645078"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>possess teaching skills and an understanding of effective instructional strategies across all applicable content areas that enable general education and special education teachers and early childhood educators to—</text><item id="ID02A625FAA888452D9B1D9D4AD4F19EDA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>meet the specific social and emotional learning and academic needs of all students, including students with disabilities, students who are English learners, students who are gifted and talented, students with low literacy levels and, as applicable, children in early childhood education programs; </text></item><item id="ID3B147A9D97A3437DB61D0125F0EF95D7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>differentiate instruction for such students; and</text></item><item id="idb1cfb85575154b3dbd7e7e17611a8862"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>use culturally relevant pedagogy and curricular materials;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="ID02FFB1D10FCA4743B2EA3769A423453A"><enum>(V)</enum><text>can effectively participate as a member of the individualized education program team, as defined in section 614(d)(1)(B) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act; </text></subclause><subclause id="idd585103cc812413e8427c57ea57298e0"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>possess the skills to meet the academic, social, and emotional needs of students and create inclusive and culturally responsive learning environments; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id49f725b34a4346c5b45444b2e0008409"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>can successfully employ effective strategies for comprehensive literacy instruction (as defined in section 2221(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965);</text></subclause></clause><clause id="ID57231165024746D8ACD2686F4A22DBFA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensuring collaboration with departments, programs, or units of a partner institution outside of the teacher preparation program in all academic content areas, as appropriate, to ensure that prospective teachers receive training in both teaching and relevant content areas in order to meet the applicable State requirements to becoming fully certified or licensed as described in section 200(b)(2)(A) and become profession-ready, or with regard to special education teachers, meet the qualifications described in section 612(a)(14)(C) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, which may include training in multiple subjects to teach multiple grade levels as may be needed for individuals preparing to teach in rural communities and for individuals preparing to teach students with disabilities; </text></clause><clause id="ID534C690513CC4E76847D0B67BC990CF0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>developing admissions goals and priorities aligned with the hiring objectives of the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership, which may include consideration of applicants who reflect the communities in which they will teach as well as consideration of individuals from underrepresented populations in the teaching profession;</text></clause><clause id="IDF222F18BE70D4D99B06037609F2353AE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>implementing program and curriculum changes, as applicable, to ensure that prospective teachers have the requisite content knowledge, preparation, and degree to teach Advanced Placement or International Baccalaureate courses successfully; and</text></clause><clause id="id877f9593426c4c188f77cc4f40c35432"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>embedding social and emotional competencies into the program and curriculum, as applicable, to ensure that new and prospective teachers have the requisite content knowledge and skills. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDA0AECA2DBA1F4166B689A7CF1A6B4FA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clinical experience and interaction</header><text>Developing or improving a sustained preservice clinical education program to further develop the teaching skills of all prospective teachers and, as applicable, early childhood educators, involved in the program. Such program shall do the following:</text><subparagraph id="IDE972C0E1D3AC40F9971FD76F67F8F550"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Incorporate year-long opportunities for enrichment, including—</text><clause id="ID351FEB61F2C8486B83CBE37B7A46E2AB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>clinical learning in classrooms in high-need schools served by the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership, and identified by the eligible partnership; and</text></clause><clause id="IDE65E69F0FD6E48E3948BC1FEF6853CEC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>closely supervised interaction between prospective teachers and faculty, experienced teachers, principals, other administrators, and school leaders at early childhood education programs (as applicable), elementary schools, or secondary schools, and providing support for such interaction.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDFD82536AC0FB47438EE5AB645095DA6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Integrate pedagogy and classroom practice and promote effective teaching skills in academic content areas.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID5509580ADC8E48DF8CF0EEDF280A37FA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Provide teacher mentoring.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID30C4FFB2E7AF489D94DF4D0A2BD07867"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Be offered over the course of a program of teacher preparation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID1243C6D4CA414DE2892E7A7D6E0E7BF8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Be tightly aligned with course work (and may be developed as a fifth year of a teacher preparation program).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDB8AB2AE16FE04BE799F57C20A21ECE25"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Where feasible, allow prospective teachers to learn to teach in the same local educational agency in which the teachers will work, learning the instructional initiatives and curriculum of that local educational agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID21A0C0BCB20E44B78A86389FF5AAEA2E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>As applicable, provide training and experience to enhance the teaching skills of prospective teachers to better prepare such teachers to meet the unique needs of teaching in rural or urban communities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDC585032EBDF54C9183B9CA1D392029B1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Provide support and training for individuals participating in an activity for prospective or new teachers described in this paragraph or paragraph (1) or (3), and for individuals who serve as mentors for such teachers, based on each individual's experience. Such support may include—</text><clause id="IDADF1EADC353C4B3181F85DD8207FC31A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with respect to a prospective teacher or a mentor, release time for such individual's participation;</text></clause><clause id="IDE929098041D54A3582A43F1D6C823964"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to a faculty member, receiving course workload credit and compensation for time teaching in the eligible partnership's activities; and</text></clause><clause id="id1bfc9e983ff74c359cac11324d5e99d2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to a mentor, a stipend, which may include bonus, differential, incentive, or performance pay, based on the mentor’s qualifications and responsibilities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID9A3AF377DFE64B728F4E64460D8F1423"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Induction programs for new teachers</header><text>Creating an induction program for new teachers or, in the case of an early childhood education program, providing mentoring or coaching for new early childhood educators. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID97ACD8C6B028466D927AFFB4C0C395B8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Support and training for participants in early childhood education programs</header><text>In the case of an eligible partnership focusing on early childhood educator preparation, implementing initiatives that increase compensation for early childhood educators who attain associate or baccalaureate degrees in early childhood education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8a97425ccf3e4270bcc365c2dcab3420"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Teacher recruitment</header><text>Developing and implementing effective mechanisms to ensure that the eligible partnership is able to recruit qualified individuals, including individuals from groups that are underrepresented in the education profession, to become teachers who meet the applicable State requirements to be fully certified or licensed as described in section 200(b)(2)(A) and become profession-ready, and with regard to special education teachers, meet the qualifications described in section 612(a)(14)(C) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, through the activities of the eligible partnership, which may include an emphasis on recruiting into the teaching profession—</text><subparagraph id="ID801BFE758E5742D28E8D779C1BB0800B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>individuals from underrepresented populations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id81c9aaa4647d47cca8abfb5674914754"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals to teach in rural communities and teacher shortage areas, including mathematics, science, special education, career and technical education, and the instruction of English learners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID2FFD3B7F192047629E5CB221D5EAFFCC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>professionals from other occupations, former military personnel, and recent college graduates with a record of academic distinction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDA02DF68460FE4A4C964802CA2A89A2F8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Literacy training</header><text>Strengthening the literacy teaching skills of prospective and, as applicable, new elementary school and secondary school teachers—</text><subparagraph id="idf0c40c5576f247f6a9955f551a86f6bb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to implement comprehensive literacy instruction programs (as defined in section 2221(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDA3ADE40DAAE448EA817568AC97DCB38B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to use screening, formative, diagnostic and summative assessments to determine students' literacy levels, difficulties, and growth in order to improve classroom instruction and improve student reading and writing skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDE11C53A7E0154867B5E92B3A92813387"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to provide individualized, intensive, and targeted literacy instruction for students with deficiencies in literacy skills; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID19F41C8A38814DE8B819DFAC6938C87C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to integrate literacy skills in the classroom across subject areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide4c7dce9bf6640d88ef8202ec1d911cd"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Partnership grants for principal preparation</header><text>An eligible partnership receiving a grant to carry out an effective program to prepare profession-ready principals shall carry out a program that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="id8a5de2db2558485d9a39350b64dc9da4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Development of leadership skills with a demonstrated impact on student and school success, including the ability to create a continuous learning environment for teachers, staff, and students.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idabf7b5d3139a4c6289aba45d3bfae847"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Rigorous recruitment and selection criteria for successful educators who have shown potential as leaders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd479acf1ae2943f7a18f4bdf9104b5f5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Program faculty with prior school leadership experience and deep knowledge of effective leadership practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id19a1901ab6d24c5aa4c04e5bd23ec889"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Comprehensive clinical experiences that are linked to coursework and help principal candidates address context-specific problems and the needs of special population groups, including students who are children with disabilities, English learners, and students from economically disadvantaged families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idec8dee5e417d44caa5a0f85761998f60"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Peer networks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida264b801741944f0831be8a1d784ea10"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Mentoring, supervision, and evaluation of candidates throughout the clinical experience.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0c4ac625cb224ccda0983a3ca693f44c"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Opportunities for ongoing professional learning and coaching for practicing school leaders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id332968f2e8844a9da5f4fc042f4e3e7a"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Partnership grants for the establishment of teaching and principal residency programs</header><paragraph id="id8656efbb05004add92ff2aed98957d6b"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible partnership receiving a grant to carry out an effective teaching or principal residency program shall carry out a program that includes the following activities:</text><subparagraph id="ide0d5ab171cc34d5481e01457aa80d402"><enum>(A)</enum><header>For teaching residency programs</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a teaching residency program shall carry out both of the following activities:</text><clause id="idca2cac8d5f524302b9e57eb73946e300"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Supporting a teaching residency program described in paragraph (2) for high-need schools and in high-need subjects and areas, as determined by the needs of the high-need local educational agency in the partnership.</text></clause><clause id="id6860c5f722204d98bd3b25a3f6514f0c"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Placing graduates of the teaching residency program in cohorts that facilitate professional collaboration, both among graduates of the residency program and between such graduates and mentor teachers in the receiving school.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6504561203c446eabe75676a2b7cb864"><enum>(B)</enum><header>For principal residency programs</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a principal residency program shall support a program described in paragraph (3) for high-need schools, as determined by the needs of the high-need local educational agency in the partnership.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id570a0b59f82444e2a714ce5213e184ed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Teacher residency programs</header><subparagraph id="idb84f1672699d4798b7c7f03bf3d79de2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment and design</header><text>A teaching residency program under this paragraph shall be a program based upon models of successful teaching residencies that serves as a mechanism to prepare teachers for success in high-need schools in the eligible partnership and shall be designed to include the following characteristics of successful programs:</text><clause id="idc4f70043f1ae4e13a8bd9a426f6a4b8b"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The integration of pedagogy, classroom practice, and teacher mentoring.</text></clause><clause id="id42611667b6784cba98e8204d0191f32b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The exposure to principles of child and youth development as well as understanding and applying principles of learning and behavior.</text></clause><clause id="id52b38f29db6644a293feebdf2d1362ff"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Engagement of teaching residents in rigorous graduate-level coursework to earn a master's degree while undertaking supervised clinical preparation.</text></clause><clause id="id6302facae68d498897fbfab12445ec92"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Experience and learning opportunities alongside a trained and experienced mentor teacher—</text><subclause id="idfcc6ba6ffbc14cc6adf940c41dd04ab6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>whose teaching shall complement the residency program so that school-based clinical practice is tightly aligned with coursework;</text></subclause><subclause id="id801e04ee3c4e4897b206bdb97ab70fc9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>who shall have extra responsibilities as a teacher leader of the teaching residency program, as a mentor for residents, and as a teacher coach during the induction program for new teachers, and for establishing, within the program, a learning community in which all individuals are expected to continually improve their capacity to advance student learning; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idb49f643db9a9486381ef66e82b3ddadb"><enum>(III)</enum><text>who may be relieved from teaching duties or may be offered a stipend as a result of such additional responsibilities.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id96b3549779b441b6b5bf9ff095ba57ac"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The establishment of clear criteria for the selection of mentor teachers based on the appropriate grade level, subject area knowledge, and measures of teacher effectiveness, which—</text><subclause id="id96735CD13E6647E9835A65565654182F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall be based on, but not limited to, observations of—</text><item id="idb99721659ac240bf92f0280dab08d57c"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>planning and preparation, including demonstrated knowledge of content, pedagogy, and assessment, including the use of formative, summative, and diagnostic assessments to improve student learning;</text></item><item id="id804a61e6852c496588518a01ce38a355"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>appropriate instruction that engages all students;</text></item><item id="id6db1cf7d26dd4fcebb01be7549864015"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>collaboration with colleagues to improve instruction; and</text></item><item id="idC1C8B93B61194619BE0D384810B6D6E9"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>analysis of evidence of student learning; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="id8A42C0F65CFF488C8FA7D29FECA08CBC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may include criteria regarding meeting nationally recognized, standards-based advanced certification requirements.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id7fd06d92926743749d8f47551b0701a4"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The development of admissions goals and priorities—</text><subclause id="id7317e8f990e641e3b1f8aa28dfecad4a"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that are aligned with the hiring objectives of the local educational agency partnering with the program, as well as the instructional initiatives and curriculum of such agency to hire qualified graduates from the teaching residency program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id6e82c4723b6548d8a45c75a60d1ef750"><enum>(II)</enum><text>which may include consideration of applicants who reflect the communities in which they will teach as well as consideration of individuals from underrepresented populations in the teaching profession.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id151c3171fef84a99923d9b0e49cce0b3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Support for residents once such residents are hired as the teachers of record, through an induction program, professional development, and networking opportunities to support the residents through not less than the residents' first 2 years of teaching.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc20428bbf8604c84acc28c683bd058fc"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection of individuals as teacher residents</header><clause id="id47f203965cef4fc7b0cf518b0664d917"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>In order to be eligible to be a teacher resident in a teacher residency program under this paragraph, an individual shall—</text><subclause id="id5efed5f8a39c4f0989d7699fcdfc1e44"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be a recent graduate of a 4-year institution of higher education, an individual in the final year of an undergraduate teacher preparation program, or a professional possessing strong content knowledge and a record of professional accomplishment in another field; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id4e847200285a4ce69ba94848bce55723"><enum>(II)</enum><text>submit an application to the residency program.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id28e243a62eb64032ae9baf4bb2b36952"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a teaching residency program under this subsection shall establish criteria for the selection of eligible individuals to participate in the teaching residency program based on the following characteristics:</text><subclause id="idb0f4a49df21142bf8aaf4a78fe061b4a"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Strong content knowledge or record of accomplishment in the field or subject area to be taught.</text></subclause><subclause id="id2bab1d10065845faa396879d618a6f6d"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Strong verbal and written communication skills, which may be demonstrated by performance on appropriate assessments.</text></subclause><subclause id="id457c091a788b402b9eba92085ad189f4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Other attributes linked to effective teaching, which may be determined by interviews or performance assessments, as specified by the eligible partnership.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id87a69b64d4ff4f49963867d2bcdab145"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Principal residency programs</header><subparagraph id="id939f8172956b4fa8ac71fd014868515a"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment and design</header><text>A principal residency program under this paragraph shall be a program based on models of successful principal residencies that serve as a mechanism to prepare principals for success in high-need schools in the eligible partnership and shall be designed to include the following characteristics of successful programs:</text><clause id="id9f451c29675c406986179f7c59b76543"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Engagement of principal residents in rigorous graduate-level coursework to earn an appropriate advanced credential while undertaking a guided principal apprenticeship.</text></clause><clause id="id399597d4a9e64550bd7dd1013881f4db"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Experience and learning opportunities alongside a trained and experienced mentor principal—</text><subclause id="id6d7ad30127334735aa17096e0efa1e73"><enum>(I)</enum><text>whose mentoring shall be based on standards of effective mentoring practice and shall complement the residency program so that school-based clinical practice is tightly aligned with coursework; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idfd7ef8e5c49345a9900f7f587d58b07c"><enum>(II)</enum><text>who may be relieved from some portion of principal duties or may be offered a stipend as a result of such additional responsibilities.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id01c46cd5a2de4e2e85c337c5a4338b61"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The establishment of clear criteria for the selection of mentor principals, which may be based on observations of the following:</text><subclause id="id103f80fa6afc4a489d337c0fa402761d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Demonstrating awareness of, and having experience with, the knowledge, skills, and attitudes to—</text><item id="id8e6bfe9b9f6040a383d4729770453f12"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>establish and maintain a professional learning community that effectively extracts information from data to improve the school culture and personalize instruction for all students to result in improved student achievement;</text></item><item id="idce475be28cb047c1a4e8fc0a7b38c59e"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>create and maintain a learning culture within the school that provides a climate conducive to the development of all members of the school community, including one of continuous learning for adults tied to student learning and other school goals;</text></item><item id="id18aa93db61dc4a6db33984464eee15ba"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>engage in continuous professional development, using a combination of academic study, developmental simulation exercises, self-reflection, mentorship, and internship;</text></item><item id="id8e187a95bdc1447b8d1cabe766b9eee5"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>understand child and youth development appropriate to the age level served by the school, and use this knowledge to set high expectations and standards for the academic, social, emotional, and physical development of all students; and</text></item><item id="id0e0ca54e9b79447cad15bfe518fa582f"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>actively engage the community to create shared responsibility for student academic performance and successful development.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="idf701b6b81d4641a3aefca505e8c9602f"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Planning and articulating a shared and coherent schoolwide direction and policy for achieving high standards of student performance.</text></subclause><subclause id="idbec276531a1e425c89fb3c67ac6bbc31"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Identifying and implementing the activities and rigorous curriculum necessary for achieving such standards of student performance.</text></subclause><subclause id="id3974b21b52584c2081670253dfb60ae5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Supporting a culture of learning, collaboration, and professional behavior and ensuring evidence-based instructional practice.</text></subclause><subclause id="id581309feb4b74462af3eb8d2afba9758"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Communicating and engaging parents, families, and other external communities.</text></subclause><subclause id="idbc0dbe2b62be402281c5316a19c13d08"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Collecting, analyzing, and utilizing data and other evidence of student learning and evidence of classroom practice to guide decisions and actions for continuous improvement and to ensure performance accountability.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idd51259d9c6464427b1184580951ae593"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The development of admissions goals and priorities—</text><subclause id="id880688cf58b0463ca1a325da99421594"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that are aligned with the hiring objectives of the local educational agency partnering with the program, as well as the instructional initiatives and curriculum of such agency to hire qualified graduates from the principal residency program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id839d8713d9fd4b748763e29389d7f6ac"><enum>(II)</enum><text>which may include consideration of applicants who reflect the communities in which they will serve as well as consideration of individuals from underrepresented populations in school leadership positions.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idf13733cdda34427ea2be29286586ca48"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Support for residents once such residents are hired as principals, through an induction program, professional development to support the knowledge and skills of the principal in a continuum of learning and content expertise in developmentally appropriate or age-appropriate educational practices, and networking opportunities to support the residents through not less than the residents' first 2 years of serving as principal of a school.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id57400142e05648ae8a4c97d261bf85fc"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection of individuals as principal residents</header><clause id="id9ead49c8d3f94aea848b1ad377e82519"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>In order to be eligible to be a principal resident in a principal residency program under this paragraph, an individual shall—</text><subclause id="ide2ea53db21bb47a793687dc00e31310e"><enum>(I)</enum><text>have prior experience teaching prekindergarten through grade 12;</text></subclause><subclause id="id100e37cc146645769c5fa805cb101eb8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>have experience as an effective leader, manager, and written and oral communicator; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id2e83c1337a344adda74627ca73dbe5e3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>submit an application to the residency program.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id5a3266fa1de34f43810028c099b9ef4f"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a principal residency program under this subsection shall establish criteria for the selection of eligible individuals to participate in the principal residency program based on the following characteristics:</text><subclause id="id30fcc5b9e7f24198aa28de3d97978c5d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Strong instructional leadership skills in an elementary school or secondary school setting.</text></subclause><subclause id="idcecfcd3fe12943f1af76c5ae43bf0860"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Strong verbal and written communication skills, which may be demonstrated by performance on appropriate assessments.</text></subclause><subclause id="id16bcc2da8a4448a396ce7f9379fae031"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Other attributes linked to effective leadership, such as sound judgment, organizational capacity, collaboration, and openness to continuous learning, which may be determined by interviews or performance assessment, as specified by the eligible partnership.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id579b36b402784fb9aff1ab8e8952b406"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Stipends or salaries; applications; agreements; repayments</header><subparagraph id="id12f69d60db1f44abbb9d24620c78416d"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Stipends or salaries</header><text>A teaching or principal residency program under this subsection—</text><clause id="ide93bdbf559e546e2bc973c3e6cc6ab1e"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall provide a 1-year living stipend or salary to teaching or principal residents during the 1-year teaching or principal residency program; and</text></clause><clause id="id8dc4f111639343c182783b0ac13f91de"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may provide a stipend to a mentor teacher or mentor principal.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id021b54e0ed964227a3bba0de33d57d9a"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applications for stipends or salaries</header><text>Each teacher or principal residency candidate desiring a stipend or salary during the period of residency shall submit an application to the eligible partnership at such time, and containing such information and assurances, as the eligible partnership may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf1a3739fa8064d44a2f48324ec9854e8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Agreements to serve</header><text>Each application submitted under subparagraph (B) shall contain or be accompanied by an agreement that the applicant will—</text><clause id="idabb8e56bd3c64d1b95ac264e261c48f8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serve as a full-time teacher or principal for a total of not less than 3 academic years immediately after successfully completing the 1-year teaching or principal residency program;</text></clause><clause id="idb2f1604731e84232a4f3204ef0653ab5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fulfill the requirement under clause (i)—</text><subclause id="idaaa98310d0124a86a5d35ef570b11585"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by teaching or serving as a principal in a high-need school served by the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership and, if a teacher, teaching a subject or area that is designated as high-need by the partnership; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idbfb1ee8af54840589298018ea35106fc"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if there is no appropriate position available in a high-need school served by the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership, by teaching or serving as a principal in any other high-need school;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idb5ffe4d9fd7249059120843b35650b14"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provide to the eligible partnership a certificate, from the chief administrative officer of the local educational agency in which the resident is employed, of the employment required under clauses (i) and (ii) at the beginning of, and on completion of, each year or partial year of service;</text></clause><clause id="id669ef8b859e74a5c9bb73fc8f37307e1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>for teacher residents, meet the requirements to be a profession-ready teacher;</text></clause><clause id="id868e0ba5935d4454941e16b44aa843d1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for principal residents, meet the requirements to be a profession-ready principal;</text></clause><clause id="ida01bddb7006d43c88f76789a807e624d"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>for other educators, complete the preparation program and become fully certified in the State where the educator is employed; and </text></clause><clause id="id951436bacdeb45f98297b32ba27b820e"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>comply with the requirements set by the eligible partnership under subparagraph (D) if the applicant is unable or unwilling to complete the service obligation required by this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id411f7f3745ee479aaca7fe6536fb6192"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Repayments</header><clause id="idba6d21141cab4c958e89331e65f4a88f"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a teaching or principal residency program under this subsection shall require a recipient of a stipend or salary under subparagraph (A) who does not complete, or who notifies the partnership that the recipient intends not to complete, the service obligation required by subparagraph (C) to repay such stipend or salary to the eligible partnership (except that such repayment shall not include interest) in accordance with such other terms and conditions specified by the eligible partnership, as necessary.</text></clause><clause id="id0d2b0f174ac54c38852f47c5699f0101"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other terms and conditions</header><text>Any other terms and conditions specified by the eligible partnership may include reasonable provisions for prorated repayment of the stipend or salary described in subparagraph (A) or for deferral of a teaching resident's service obligation required by subparagraph (C), on grounds of health, incapacitation, inability to secure employment in a school served by the eligible partnership, being called to active duty in the Armed Forces of the United States, or other extraordinary circumstances.</text></clause><clause id="idfd88881e55a348fcb357604c6a23626b"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Use of repayments</header><text>An eligible partnership shall use any repayment received under this subparagraph to carry out additional activities that are consistent with the purposes of this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idababa0a132d34827a7191ed20a256b42"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Partnership grants for educator development</header><text>An eligible partnership that receives a grant under this section may carry out effective educator development programs for other educators besides teachers and principals based on the needs identified in subsection (b)(1) that may include the following activities:</text><paragraph id="id1d845393b2f4414197ce624d70e3c0e4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Implementing curriculum changes that improve, evaluate, and assess how well prospective and new educators develop instructional skills.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id969c15fec5f04884a4a9a3a3a48824f9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Preparing educators to use evidence-based research, where applicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idad8cd591ce1f41baa353f7c1fda01ed3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providing pre-service clinical experience.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida188a129106b46118bfb071f19569f79"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Creating induction programs for new educators.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida1bf7df10ae84f399248b260ec98fc3e"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Aligning recruitment and admissions goals and priorities with the hiring objectives of the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd2fc0f1aa5e74bf6b0876648e4ea5986"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Professional development and training for mentor educators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="IDC00F927879A84F5ABF132802849AB19F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Evaluation and reporting</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="ID824979086A4848C38C20E81BAFDE371F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the programs assisted under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID9663D5AF6FA048BFA8984B35E08CC403"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make publicly available a report detailing the Secretary's evaluation of each such program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID8D632197048B47A4BD17C3A80ABB2C16"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Consultation</header><paragraph id="IDA40642626F734543AF385CA55EA7DE13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Members of an eligible partnership that receives a grant under this section shall engage in regular consultation throughout the development and implementation of programs and activities carried out under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDDC23072FC3E84D3E94D73332BCB7C8B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regular communication</header><text>To ensure timely and meaningful consultation as described in paragraph (1), regular communication shall occur among all members of the eligible partnership, including the high-need local educational agency. Such communication shall continue throughout the implementation of the grant and the assessment of programs and activities under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID44C0782B18E2445DB9BC2DB9B61FB086"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Written consent</header><text>The Secretary may approve changes in grant activities under this section only if the eligible partnership submits to the Secretary a written consent to such changes signed by all members of the eligible partnership.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="IDA9555E27BFB14AEF8388A0FA3C029DA4"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit an eligible partnership from using grant funds to coordinate with the activities of eligible partnerships in other States or on a regional basis through Governors, State boards of education, State educational agencies, State agencies responsible for early childhood education, local educational agencies, or State agencies for higher education.</text></subsection><subsection id="IDCEB097CE822F4CFD9CB1A7FE4C44D66C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Funds made available under this section shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, and local funds that would otherwise be expended to carry out activities under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id6A863D8E0DA042AB89C0BFECBDC9BCB8"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Continuation of awards</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, from funds appropriated to carry out this part, the Secretary shall continue to fund any multiyear grant awarded under this part (as such provisions were in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>), for the duration of such multiyear grant in accordance with its terms.</text></subsection></section><section id="ID5302E87323CD44789C98B1320EC9588F"><enum>223.</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header><subsection id="ID06BCB660160D4DC98FC06838BFC16B60"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duration; number of awards; payments</header><paragraph id="IDE6C73F6407BC449FB5E48A1548E0F98A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A grant awarded under this subpart shall be awarded for a period of 5 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDA40C34DDED9F404E8B749FEDCC1E254A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Number of awards</header><text>An eligible partnership may not receive more than 1 grant during a 5-year period, except that such partnership may receive an additional grant during such period if such grant is used to establish a teacher or principal residency program if such residency program was not established with the prior grant. Nothing in this part shall be construed to prohibit an individual member, that can demonstrate need, of an eligible partnership that receives a grant under this title from entering into another eligible partnership consisting of new members and receiving a grant with such other eligible partnership before the 5-year period described in the preceding sentence applicable to the eligible partnership with which the individual member has first partnered has expired.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="IDFFC1B2F3664C4E76A86DC52D1CF568B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Peer review</header><paragraph id="ID7F0A99841F264BF5B06CE3E495FC1CA8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Panel</header><text>The Secretary shall provide the applications submitted under this subpart to a peer review panel for evaluation. With respect to each application, the peer review panel shall initially recommend the application for funding or for disapproval.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID189EAF17265149BB97EED805A7B45CDB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary, in funding applications under this subpart, shall give priority—</text><subparagraph id="id935ff2131c93403a94529fa7c6124156"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to eligible partnerships that include an institution of higher education whose teacher education program or educator development program has a rigorous selection process and demonstrated success in having a diverse set of candidates complete the program, and enter and remain in the profession; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDCA00C3F5C0C342BEAC62E729220300DF"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="IDA867F556817C45AEB5239C767DA54D99"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to applications from broad-based eligible partnerships that involve businesses and community organizations; or</text></clause><clause id="IDDE6FDBCDD6C748FF8704F7E7615B3E06" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to eligible partnerships so that the awards promote an equitable geographic distribution of grants among rural and urban areas.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID47E1DC4A65DA46558E4B3C0E23AEE13C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretarial selection</header><text>The Secretary shall determine, based on the peer review process, which applications shall receive funding and the amounts of the grants. In determining grant amounts, the Secretary shall take into account the total amount of funds available for all grants under this subpart and the types of activities proposed to be carried out by the eligible partnership.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID0D175425B7F54723B049AA82BD2DBDC3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matching requirements</header><paragraph id="IDAD90CE5969494BB680AA5A2E66F54BCA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each eligible partnership receiving a grant under this subpart shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 100 percent of the amount of the grant, which may be provided in cash or in-kind, to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID24D3039B3C0840848A14B89C26A58D82"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive all or part of the matching requirement described in paragraph (1) for any fiscal year for an eligible partnership if the Secretary determines that applying the matching requirement to the eligible partnership would result in serious hardship or an inability to carry out the authorized activities described in this subpart.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID28A1CCBA93D24672A88D83C883037D03"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on administrative expenses</header><text>An eligible partnership that receives a grant under this subpart may use not more than 2 percent of the funds provided to administer the grant.</text></subsection></section><section id="IDA0D4E26F70144C588EC3DA09191D8796"><enum>224.</enum><header>Accountability and evaluation</header><subsection id="idC9472BBB515C48DB824D0DC249057E7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligible partnership evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible partnership submitting an application for a grant under this subpart shall establish, and include in such application, an evaluation plan that includes strong and measurable performance objectives. The plan shall include objectives and measures for—</text><paragraph id="idf6877bbefd074897a661c569a1d9b55f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>program completion rates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id645F28E9F1A64238B3A8668E692D0F29"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">achievement for all prospective and new educators as measured by the eligible partnership;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id985CA71095314798878C7FB9F6C6FD5E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educator retention in the first 3 years;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idDB4C519AD26B4F30A3F4A1BF8F7020B3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pass rates for initial State certification or licensure of teachers or pass rates on valid and reliable teacher performance assessments; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idB7F2299DA0164F1C82EB2785BD5991B2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of profession-ready teachers, principals, and other educators—</text><subparagraph id="id9DC0C357DB3A469096811BD959314EB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hired by the high-need local educational agency or schools participating in the eligible partnership; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id53BB6DB4DFEC4909BFD427BAA967420A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hired by the high-need local educational agency or schools participating in the eligible partnership who are members of underrepresented groups;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id71568D024C1E45B29214D070E6AC64AE"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of profession-ready teachers hired by the high-need local educational agency or schools participating in the eligible partnership—</text><subparagraph id="id21539526F407459790F8DAAEA643BFEB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who teach high-need academic subject areas (such as reading, mathematics, science, and foreign languages, including less commonly taught languages and critical foreign languages); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id95C0092002744224B5384D7DE98691DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who teach in high-need areas (including special education, bilingual education, language instruction educational programs for English learners, and early childhood education);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0F0F11B53B96414CBD0F9E024B70B2A8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the percentage of profession-ready teachers and other educators hired by the high-need local educational agency who work in high-need schools, disaggregated by the elementary school and secondary school levels;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6D75A09BFEA74EF3BD5436E8A46DD2A0"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, the percentage of early childhood education program classes in the geographic area served by the eligible partnership taught by early childhood educators who are highly competent; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idEDBC9E488B3B43D0B7D807E198088F5F"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, the percentage of educators hired by the high-need local educational agency or schools participating in the eligible partnership that are trained to—</text><subparagraph id="idFF60C10BA9A54D388D686DEA2D064E37"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">integrate technology effectively into curricula and instruction, including technology consistent with the principles of universal design for learning; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7306614EB41844839327CE427C0D0223"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use technology effectively to collect, manage, and analyze data to improve teaching and learning for the purpose of improving student learning outcomes. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID86C5E93A136943C8A7B2815625B90BB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information</header><text>An eligible partnership receiving a grant under this subpart shall ensure that teachers, principals, school superintendents, faculty, and leadership at institutions of higher education located in the geographic areas served by the eligible partnership are provided information, including through electronic means, about the activities carried out with funds under this subpart.</text></subsection><subsection id="IDCDEF02A877F34C0885120EEA75FC41A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Revised application</header><text>If the Secretary determines that an eligible partnership receiving a grant under this subpart is not making substantial progress in meeting the purposes, goals, objectives, and measures of the grant, as appropriate, by the end of the third year of the grant the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="ID3BCD91D3C3DD425499FE8592F3926CDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall cancel the grant; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID07DB660E7D5940C2A1F98238FC6074B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may use any funds returned or available because of such cancellation under paragraph (1) to—</text><subparagraph id="ID2310809680E947E284A9F9A3C57E6ABA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increase other grant awards under this subpart; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID97A4E7B0E9E94D26A80F39643CF4A929"><enum>(B)</enum><text>award new grants to other eligible partnerships under this subpart.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID97D2687591BB49C6B26C2E37E36784AA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Evaluation and dissemination</header><text>The Secretary shall evaluate the activities funded under this subpart and report the findings regarding the evaluation of such activities to the authorizing committees. The Secretary shall broadly disseminate—</text><paragraph id="IDCCEC0B3AE20E448A933CC2F2C2168DE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>successful practices developed by eligible partnerships under this subpart; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID67DD3D5D0ADE499BB4362B157D18D10C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information regarding such practices that were found to be ineffective.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><subpart commented="no" id="ID83B5AB1C3C3D4E4B8727CCE4CAA7D07A"><enum>2</enum><header>Grants to support recruitment of new educators and diversity in the profession</header><section id="id35AC655246C94E5A8EDCB5286E93F341"><enum>231.</enum><header>Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins Centers of Excellence</header><subsection id="idf2a17ee0f6d94741a0b9a97c0c35b040"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this subpart is to strengthen and expand the recruitment, training, and retention of candidates into the teaching profession who are from underrepresented groups in such profession.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD91D66167E8C460D8D4B460EC4EA2E6F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible institution defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subpart, the term <term>eligible institution</term> means an institution of higher education that has a teacher or school leader preparation program that is accredited by the State and that is—</text><paragraph id="HF091AD2E807B4808A4F01ED2A995D7E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a part B institution (as defined in section 322);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD664229738974C4782235E6F6032C3A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a Hispanic-serving institution (as defined in section 502);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H136364409B8042B7BF73F16A90F5B545"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a Tribal college or university (as defined in section 316);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4561990997264A8E96170A7D86FDF28C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an Alaska Native-serving institution (as defined in section 317(b));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC9B5BFFD3604871B9FA79F7F73CF19F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian-serving institution (as defined in section 317(b));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A29091392E64F459BB49418D18CB2A5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a Predominantly Black Institution (as defined in section 318);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H935F0F1A53FE48528A9AAD29FA074E09"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an Asian-American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution (as defined in section 320(b));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6D2D3D024E447E796099E28955D5D9C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>a Native American-serving, nontribal institution (as defined in section 319);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70EE448F0A6B49D6AEEC0D314102B29C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a consortium of any of the institutions described in paragraphs (1) through (8); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5486EA7AD32448518CF72B4CA69B6E76"><enum>(10)</enum><text>an institution of higher education in partnership with an institution described in paragraph (1) through (8), provided that an institution described in paragraph (1) through (8) is the lead entity in the partnership. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCE8D9F60A7FD4A90ACE34305EBA48CBC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Augustus F. Hawkins Centers of Excellence</header><paragraph id="HEC26BA39F7014C4C8E96AC60D5713FEF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>From the amounts provided to carry out this subpart, the Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible institutions to establish centers of excellence.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HA0148B6665E74DFD99747759103E8D1F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible institution shall use a grant received under this subpart to ensure that programs offered at a center of excellence established by such institution prepare current and future teachers or school leaders to be profession-ready, and meet the applicable State certification and licensure requirements, including any requirements for certification obtained through alternative routes to certification, or, with regard to special education teachers, the qualifications described in section 612(a)(14) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1412">20 U.S.C. 1412(a)(14)(C)</external-xref>), by carrying out one or more of the following activities:</text><subparagraph id="id9920F92FE28444ECB05849054CEF63EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Implementing reforms within teacher or school leader preparation programs, which may include such preparation programs that prepare teachers or school leaders for early childhood education programs, to ensure that such programs are preparing teachers or school leaders who meet such applicable State certification and licensure requirements or qualifications, and are using evidence-based instructional practices to improve student academic achievement, by— </text><clause commented="no" id="HB06CA068A1F9461A9FE7C86A153180EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>retraining or recruiting faculty; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF7E30F5E228D4F238C3810EAC4FECD05"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>designing (or redesigning) teacher or school leader preparation programs that—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H59B1A89F5A4A4D7CAF536E79CEDAAE84"><enum>(I)</enum><text>prepare teachers or school leaders to serve in under-resourced schools and close student achievement gaps, and that are based on rigorous academic content, evidence-based research, and challenging State academic standards as described in section 1111(b)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(1)</external-xref>); and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA39AB49BCBAC4F2A9C44AEF3694BEAAF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>promote effective teaching skills.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HEDC4DAC45E404133AAFF96A60E30E96A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Providing sustained and high-quality preservice clinical experience, including the mentoring of prospective teachers by teacher leaders, substantially increasing interaction between faculty at institutions of higher education and new and experienced teachers, principals, school leaders, and other administrators at elementary schools or secondary schools, and providing support, including preparation time, for such interaction.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H97350FEBFE1C4428A78596B3CC0AFC62"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing and implementing initiatives to promote retention of teachers who meet such applicable State certification and licensure requirements or qualifications, and principals and other school leaders, including teachers of color, principals and other school leaders, including programs that provide—</text><clause commented="no" id="H0B3AC9D6E8BE4CCC855BC4E477FF1BE8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>teacher or principal and other school leader mentoring; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HAE0040E07ED34E349393E6881539947D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>induction and support for teachers and principals and other school leaders during their first three years of employment as teachers, principals, or other school leaders, respectively.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3F76EAEC0B994E44AEC90FE58EB68AD4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Awarding scholarships based on financial need to help students pay the costs of tuition, room, board, and other expenses of completing a teacher or other school leader preparation program, not to exceed the cost of attendance as defined in section 472.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9400089F5CB149CCAFB7BC05E9342996"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Disseminating information on effective practices for teacher or other school leader preparation and successful teacher or other school leader certification and licensure assessment preparation strategies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2F9C4D8802D64AB7A190D68DC3023131"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Activities authorized under section 222.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB6D610C4E9A445FBEF16DA5C4A1E55F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Any eligible institution desiring a grant under this subpart shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6E9180DFAA3460396AFB35C86836161"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on administrative expenses</header><text>An eligible institution that receives a grant under this subpart may use not more than 2 percent of the grant funds to administer the grant. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45C9F3EA0ACA47BEA3FFEF51758CC9D3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to carry out this subpart.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id7E9399E8755B438987E4C7E81A58E4CD"><enum>232.</enum><header>Recruitment and completion grants</header><subsection id="idD9E4C61AA8AD44248349E34B353734D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 221, the Secretary may award grants to institutions of higher education that have educator preparation programs in order to allow those programs to support the needs of populations that are underrepresented in the field of education, including first generation college students and students with disabilities, to ensure completion of the educator preparation program and entrance into the profession.</text></subsection><subsection id="idC333F784F67E464F8153D08C4E875F7D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An institution of higher education receiving a grant under this section may use grant funds to support students described in subsection (a) who are enrolled in educator preparation programs by providing services such as—</text><paragraph id="id94C2753C10A74A22975501D70AC69CE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">childcare for such enrolled students;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id433D411ABC7F47C98D9125C8C5BF4B44"><enum>(2)</enum><text>cohort support;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id68C229E71C754DD99F67C46287B7D4BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>programs that provide pathways from community colleges to baccalaureate programs in the field of education; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idEB026EBB6C9D400AAAC755D7CF9A9613"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">programs that pay for certification or licensure exams, including re-taking of exams as necessary and the additional preparation to ensure passage of the exams.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="idD84AD7CD6D13450F95217AAEF05735CB"><enum>233.</enum><header>Pipelines into educator preparation</header><subsection commented="no" id="ID5167C678D1D24047932F8BD2D2E82E51"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Education careers opportunity program</header><paragraph id="ID06A650B10E7647E29EDF1C888233F228"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority for grants</header><text>The Secretary may make grants to partner institutions or eligible partnerships to assist those institutions or partnerships in carrying out the activities described in paragraph (2) in order to assist individuals from underrepresented backgrounds, as determined in accordance with criteria prescribed by the Secretary, to undertake education to become an educator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ID511748CB590F45CDAB30617065D492FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorized expenditures</header><text>A partner institution or eligible partnership may use grant funds under this section to carry out one or more of the following:</text><subparagraph id="id001f89e2c29a4d58a6906a5db52887e0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Identifying, recruiting, and selecting individuals from underrepresented backgrounds for education and training as an educator.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDB02EC962EEF543C4BB9A87F5A37A3D01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Facilitating the entry of such individuals into an educator preparation program. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDE0019BD5722C44D1A1536872CB057D15"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Providing counseling, mentoring, or other services designed to assist such individuals in successfully completing an educator preparation program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID5D6E5DD931514930A8821774878DD84A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Providing, for a period prior to the entry of such individuals into the regular course of education of an educator preparation program, preliminary education designed to assist them in successfully completing such regular course of education in such program, or referring such individuals to institutions providing such preliminary education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID8CC6DA438B0F48DDAA95DF1748F75CD5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Publicizing existing sources of financial aid available to students in the educator preparation program or who are undertaking education necessary to qualify them to enroll in such a program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID7485BA18BC0A42D79E677B19EDDEC370"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Paying such scholarships as the Secretary may determine for such individuals for any period of an educator preparation program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDF20FEFA7F8C140D8BF55375E7FE2FB24"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Paying such stipends as the Secretary may approve for such individuals for any period of education in student-enhancement programs (other than regular courses), except that—</text><clause id="id64D8F7D3005743B6BEF3B0FD1A0A394F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such a stipend may not be provided to an individual for more than 12 months; and </text></clause><clause id="idC16F231E337243F8A197BE697C8BE30D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of law regarding the amount of stipends, such a stipend shall be in an amount determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDA63116A8AEAB48E3808A4D174E83A545"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Carrying out programs under which such individuals gain experience regarding a career as an educator through working at an elementary or secondary school.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID7DB67E68334E4DDD925B69DBB4EE5032"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Conducting activities to develop a larger and more competitive applicant pool for the relevant teacher preparation program and for local educational agencies and schools through partnerships with institutions of higher education, local educational agencies, and other community-based entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID34C68A774BAB416599D30FC689EEB5F8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>regular course of education in such program</term> includes a graduate program in education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="IDD8F12865DA034D87AA9B5581BCB0288F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Matching Requirements</header><text>The Secretary may require that a partner institution or eligible partnership that applies for a grant under this subsection, provide non-Federal matching funds, as appropriate, to ensure the institutional commitment of the entity to the projects funded under the grant. As determined by the Secretary, such non-Federal matching funds may be provided directly or through donations from public or private entities and may be in cash or in-kind, fairly evaluated, including plant, equipment, or services. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><subpart id="ID06A7F874CA0846F0B288CFBEDAA9AACE"><enum>3</enum><header>Capacity building grants</header><section id="id66BEE7B8C6894EA0B7378BDC8FE98793"><enum>241.</enum><header>School leader professional development</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 221, the Secretary may award grants to institutions of higher education that have educator preparation programs for school leaders in order to allow those programs to develop and support school leaders in one or more of the following areas: </text><paragraph id="id95114fafd147446d81e6b2cd3dc25393"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Culturally and linguistically responsive practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide02e25876d494167918e131c5ce72281"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Universal design for learning.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idacf91b5424e54b0ba4d912a1f56d3683"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Social and emotional learning.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id333cb737aa5c4469988640ffe1d6a725"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Trauma-informed instruction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb53aadb474a342efb30a0e878852136a"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Strengthening knowledge of child and youth development.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5ee63bf74d6a4e64b81728bd0ff2455d"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Creating a safe school environment to minimize and respond to violence in schools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc2f88f7203e9481aafb67097df768092"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Creating an inclusive school for educators, staff, and students, including through restorative justice training. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf01658c6b93446ecafa1aaecb456b9d9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Response to intervention and non-exclusionary, positive behavioral interventions and supports (including eliminating the use of adverse interventions such as seclusion and restraints).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf6f9cff859d540bc89a81b4137d3e822"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Differentiated and data-driven instruction, including—</text><subparagraph id="id5242c2768db7454881f4d6dc0d2bb9fb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the use of data to identify and address disparities in academic achievement, academic opportunities (including advanced coursework, dual enrollment, and career and technical education), and disciplinary rates among student subgroups; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7b7053b745354c218bf7cb27580f5e2c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>determining and using accommodations for instruction and assessments for students with disabilities and English learners.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id41bd700570f14e7ab257cdd63ad225e6"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Evidence-based anti-bias training.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id737ce95b84724524877c3d16aba4bf54"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Effective and equitable use of technology for digital and blended learning (including the appropriate use of technology and assistive technology for students with disabilities).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1740b2b335d94ce898bd7e914177d361"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Effective strategies to engage and collaborate with stakeholders to advance the learning of all students (including parents and families, other educational professionals, out-of-school time providers, and community members).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddfc2c4feb4244ba8842fc989f868bfce"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Other evidence-based strategies and practices that advance the academic achievement of all students, including students of color, English learners, students from low-income families, and students with disabilities.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="id6D806D760CD140B9830AB21155CBE84E"><enum>242.</enum><header>Faculty professional development and training</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may award grants to institutions of higher education that have educator preparation programs in order to allow those programs to develop and support faculty in a college, school, or department of education in— </text><paragraph id="idE9914A2A82704C3AB49F8306AF2D0CFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">culturally responsive pedagogy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id75D41A781B3F49B8AADB873353F78697"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">trauma-informed instruction; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idE1F5C784D1864D0597A68D8626D9E084"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">creating an inclusive climate for faculty, staff, and students, including restorative justice training; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2bcab486032f4124914cf8fc78b149c3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>strengthening knowledge of child and youth development.</text></paragraph></section><section id="id6FC4A7CF65054185B66E12AE4C93B496"><enum>243.</enum><header>Resiliency grants</header><subsection id="id7acbabe3ea834b2bb783e489670c7c09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may award grants, on a competitive basis, to institutions of higher education that have educator preparation programs, to enable those programs to carry out the activities described in subsection (b) or (c). Such grants shall be known as <quote>Resiliency Grants</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="ida93b79f161314385904855ec4d843940"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technology</header><text>An educator preparation program that receives a Resiliency Grant for technology shall use grant funds to—</text><paragraph id="id78C87315965440969E0B12217790B26E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support the preparation of profession-ready educators by expanding the use of technology in pre-service clinical and field experiences of students enrolled in educator preparation programs; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idA9E8A4F13EA44AD1A77FC3116311A4E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expand the use of technology for the in-class instruction of students in educator preparation programs; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1E53F12C8C964E5C9DDCE047E6422B7B"><enum>(3)</enum><text> conduct research on and analysis of technological tools in classroom settings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id01e6d11ab47047a08ba75c61f2a6c862"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure that technology is used in an equitable manner to enhance the learning and opportunities of students; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddbe2a880f0914947a9b2c724aa38b0a4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensure that educators are prepared to support the continuity of instruction in the event of national or local emergencies that disrupt in-person schooling. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idbe6700e4cba34a6ca9dcdb5528cac55b"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Educator workforce partnerships</header><paragraph id="id79516CB68296427D8E85CF3B77EC4262"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>An educator preparation program that receives a Resiliency Grant for educator workforce partnerships shall use grant funds to facilitate partnerships between the educator preparation program and at least one eligible entity in order to address shortages in certain subject matter fields in schools documented by the State educational agency where the educator preparation program is authorized to operate, by—</text><subparagraph id="id533838B51D7A441C8A51131F4E871BEB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expanding pathways for individuals to become profession-ready educators; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id613F731D45DD421F857BABB11F0C39EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>expanding pathways for currently practicing educators to earn supplemental credentials or licenses, which may include—</text><clause id="id8763b5411f8344c59c9531b4029aaa03"><enum>(i)</enum><text>certification in shortage areas or fields as identified by a State or local educational agency; or</text></clause><clause id="idf3e3cc6f69fd4e769b08d0b96c570a70"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nationally recognized, standards-based advanced certification; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id84082a8a7ad74fe386aebbd1c562eebd"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensuring that schools have adequate staffing to provide continuity of instruction in the event of national or local emergencies that disrupt in-person schooling. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="idCCDBE4B1284E49C1AD79368D403F8D3F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="idCAB2E45E3A0D4C2589CC91A6672E6566"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id917B4B8A0C7A4E4DB5D47FC59EEE46AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a 2-year institution of higher education, which may include a community college; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id270D1C9A7EC94703A58BCDA6141BE2AA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a 4-year institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id190cef1ba33b4f6aa61a48c96c116a1f"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall prioritize proposals that create degree pathways for the purpose of increasing the number of individuals from groups that have been historically underrepresented in the field of education who pursue and attain profession-ready educator credentials.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idE261774BCE1944DCA22EEFCDCFE089BD"><enum>244.</enum><header>Doctoral fellowships to prepare and diversify faculty in high-need areas at colleges of education</header><subsection id="idb95750e3b39f4e2d85486affdbc19895"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants by secretary</header><text>The Secretary may make grants to eligible institutions to enable such institutions to make doctoral fellowship awards to qualified individuals in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id1c134d3ccab349f08d6c4198293fd5af"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible institutions</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible institution</term> means an institution of higher education that offers a program of postbaccalaureate study leading to a doctoral degree.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc7be2904b7c9481d836fa0483ca658e8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An eligible institution that desires a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></subsection><subsection id="ide110c0c050ef4693b0fbde1bca4c64fa"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Types of fellowships supported</header><paragraph id="iddb44c203bb814033bb3ed341223094da"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible institution that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to provide doctoral fellowships to individuals who are preparing for the professorate, including individuals from groups that are underrepresented in the field of education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd049c7ae3ce747cfb2bd58c95da8ad63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Types of study</header><text>A doctoral fellowship provided under this section shall support an individual in pursuing postbaccalaureate study, which leads to a doctoral degree and may include a master’s degree as part of such study, related to teacher preparation and pedagogy in one of the following areas:</text><subparagraph id="ID900005D7B4434A88BECA06394C4C6EB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Science, technology, engineering, or mathematics, if the individual has completed a master's degree in mathematics or science and is pursuing a doctoral degree in mathematics, science, or education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID14C92CF5570947B7B88584CD617D2192"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Special or exceptional student education. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID34D58851CADD4BA58C3226813A5E7EE8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The instruction of English learners, including postbaccalaureate study in language instruction educational programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="IDCF14E6C500AD4BE183855DF209B63168"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Fellowship terms and conditions</header><paragraph id="ID464374AAD0194E15B7BF0EF8720AF447"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selection of fellows</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that an eligible institution that receives a grant under this section—</text><subparagraph id="IDD4C44324A84446B591F6898770AB6B87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall provide doctoral fellowship awards to individuals who plan to pursue a career in instruction at an institution of higher education that has a teacher preparation program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6005aa94493a41a7ba981096234696b6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in providing fellowship awards under this section, shall give priority to individuals who are from groups that are underrepresented in the higher education professoriate, including people of color, and people with disabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc9edec5e7cb94648a1bba79af8620305"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may not provide a doctoral fellowship to an otherwise eligible individual—</text><clause id="ID3437FB42A5624B1382616511C9FF5095"><enum>(i)</enum><text>during periods in which such individual is enrolled at an institution of higher education unless such individual is maintaining satisfactory academic progress in, and devoting full-time study or research to, the pursuit of the degree for which the fellowship support was provided; or</text></clause><clause id="ID15E1A38044B347469AF6D065FD3D488A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the individual is engaged in gainful employment, other than part-time employment related to teaching, research, or a similar activity determined by the institution to be consistent with and supportive of the individual's progress toward the degree for which the fellowship support was provided.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID1D17E04626564032BC95080224AA4851"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of fellowship awards</header><subparagraph id="ID35829DD49B7644BE82D50C30AD8489E7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible institution that receives a grant under this section shall award stipends to individuals who are provided graduate fellowships under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDE99FAC39BF2C44BC9B1098389107BBC8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Awards based on need</header><text>A stipend provided under this section shall be in an amount equal to the level of support provided by the National Science Foundation graduate fellowships, except that such stipend shall be adjusted as necessary so as not to exceed the fellowship recipient's demonstrated need, as determined by the institution of higher education where the fellowship recipient is enrolled.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ID5AB9A9473E5545159738586B0B0FD96A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Service requirement</header><subparagraph id="id2ef789db99f64fb381341790a274e9a8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Teaching required</header><text>Each individual who receives a doctoral fellowship under this section shall teach for one year at an institution of higher education that has a teacher preparation program or a teacher or school leader residency or induction program for each year of fellowship support received under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="IDCFEED0DC930A43C29EBC55148AD6F2BF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Institutional obligation</header><text>Each eligible institution that receives a grant under this section shall provide an assurance to the Secretary that the institution has inquired of and determined the decision of each individual who has received a graduate fellowship to begin employment, within three years of receiving a doctoral degree, at an institution of higher education that has a teacher preparation program, as required by this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID4EDE5BB9A6314E32A1B16F7EB254C1DC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Agreement required</header><text>Prior to receiving an initial graduate fellowship award, and upon the annual renewal of the graduate fellowship award, an individual selected to receive a graduate fellowship under this section shall sign an agreement with the Secretary agreeing to pursue a career in instruction at an institution of higher education that has a teacher preparation program in accordance with subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID8F249271ABAD491C91E4D1DBE6565373"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Failure to comply</header><text>If an individual who receives a graduate fellowship award under this section fails to comply with the agreement signed pursuant to subparagraph (C), the sum of the amounts of any graduate fellowship award received by such recipient shall, upon a determination of such a failure, be treated as a Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan under part D of title IV, and shall be subject to repayment (except that such loan shall have an interest rate of 0 percent) in accordance with terms and conditions specified by the Secretary in regulations under this subpart.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID8C259B431C3A4A81BB79AEBEB7ADC503"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Modified service requirement</header><text>The Secretary may waive or modify the service requirement of this paragraph in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary with respect to the criteria to determine the circumstances under which compliance with such service requirement is inequitable or represents a substantial hardship. The Secretary may waive the service requirement if compliance by the fellowship recipient is determined to be inequitable or represent a substantial hardship—</text><clause id="ID6CCAF89B166A4B2BA2346B12ECB0E2A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>because the individual is permanently and totally disabled at the time of the waiver request; or</text></clause><clause id="IDC21622B351904D46A00B0B145C740A84"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>based on documentation presented to the Secretary of substantial economic or personal hardship.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID80349F3640804A00B604EF7F7499D597"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Institutional support for fellows</header><text>An eligible institution that receives a grant under this section may reserve not more than ten percent of the grant amount for academic and career transition support for graduate fellowship recipients and for meeting the institutional obligation described in subsection (e)(3)(B).</text></subsection><subsection id="ID27C7FBFE4C75406EA442917D25C2FB6E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Restriction on use of funds</header><text>An eligible institution that receives a grant under this section may not use grant funds for general operational overhead of the institution.</text></subsection></section></subpart></part><part id="id43D62BD093F944BA8EC820C9B4B30E75" style="OLC"><enum>C</enum><header>National Activities</header><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="idCE0604647C324C8C9D359298DF0DA38C"><enum>251.</enum><header>National activities</header><subsection id="id09CC61D65E284731AB883DA5A110648D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a Center for Educator Preparation to provide technical assistance relating to educator preparation and to support research and demonstration activities.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="id9401CC5C13154B2499996C7B1EE28618"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National evaluation of educator quality enhancement</header><paragraph id="ided5800b5df684cbea049cbc7ecae257f"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim evaluation</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to Congress and make publicly available an interim report containing an evaluation of the effectiveness of the activities funded under this title in achieving the purposes of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb77e8c4bb2d64d02a0ff1b2f73be0d67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final evaluation</header><text>Not later than 6 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to Congress and make publicly available an interim report containing an evaluation of the effectiveness of the activities funded under this title in achieving the purposes of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></part><part commented="no" id="ID775FE4855DA74E278FC37AF0BF59A375"><enum>D</enum><header>General Provisions</header><section id="ID31F29F320DA94AC9843663E824B865E6"><enum>261.</enum><header>Limitations</header><subsection id="ID33126965154348009467996B11759DB8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal control prohibited</header><text>Nothing in this title shall be construed to permit, allow, encourage, or authorize any Federal control over any aspect of any private, religious, or home school, whether or not a home school is treated as a private school or home school under State law. This section shall not be construed to prohibit private, religious, or home schools from participation in programs or services under this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="IDD557995EFCBE4585BE7BB6FE047F2536"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No change in state control encouraged or required</header><text>Nothing in this title shall be construed to encourage or require any change in a State's treatment of any private, religious, or home school, whether or not a home school is treated as a private school or home school under State law.</text></subsection><subsection id="ID7FBACAAA0C9042798B73D1A24FEDA4A9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National system of teacher certification or licensure prohibited</header><text>Nothing in this title shall be construed to permit, allow, encourage, or authorize the Secretary to establish or support any national system of teacher certification or licensure.</text></subsection><subsection id="ID17865BAB57BF4B34A0B2E5F78A2D202C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this title shall be construed to alter or otherwise affect the rights, remedies, and procedures afforded to the employees of local educational agencies under Federal, State, or local laws (including applicable regulations or court orders) or under the terms of collective bargaining agreements, memoranda of understanding, or other agreements between such employees and their employers. </text></subsection></section></part></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="idE19E868BF17E4BB9B6B28EB9468C6D41"><enum>4.</enum><header>Cost of attendance</header><subsection id="id8313034D246042D79328259FF8C63900"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Section 472 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087ll">20 U.S.C. 1087ll</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id64A07F9E5C364A68AD75BAD1486E9533"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (12) and (13) as paragraphs (13) and (14), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id367ECE0E41744BFAA49FC31ED6DF3347"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (11) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5DC4B991DAFF4E539462D46A901C53C7"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id37344E5448D34FD28F22CCD57CE59266"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for a student enrolled in an educator preparation program, reasonable costs associated with clinical experiences related to that program; </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idA2F58DF3FF9F48D7B52A1A87FA412942"><enum>(b)</enum><header>FAFSA Simplification</header><text>Section 472 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087ll">20 U.S.C. 1087ll</external-xref>), as amended by title VII of division FF of the FAFSA Simplification Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="id70C0372ECBC2485D9720FEA999D6D520"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="id0078C080BD29476BBB10549BED95882D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (13) and (14) as paragraphs (14) and (15), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idFEBB85AE3B1944DB82891B5AFBB59B30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (12) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idEC367453E218492890B2804833AD03A5"><paragraph id="idBD026EF8DA37479CBE9645E3B984AC89"><enum>(13)</enum><text>for a student enrolled in an educator preparation program, reasonable costs associated with clinical experiences related to that program;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id74B807EFFEB44D98A5490469ED0B496A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>paragraphs (1) through (14)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (1) through (15)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id62743CE4745241198403450DE514A5D4"><enum>5.</enum><header>TEACH Grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart 9 of part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g">20 U.S.C. 1070g et seq.</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idea063b3c33c847e6a39074ed359ffb54"><subpart id="id0734F506D2644C459B59E98AB1922C2B" style="OLC"><enum>9</enum><header>Teach Grants</header><section id="id48051d6ec45f41ecb0b7df017907fd78"><enum>420L.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the purposes of this subpart:</text><paragraph id="ida3280593017a46d394fd333296ab13aa"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible institution</header><text>The term <term>eligible institution</term> means an institution of higher education, as defined in section 102, that the Secretary determines—</text><subparagraph id="idf7a714ef94f94fa8b2b57c887adbd446"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides teacher preparation and professional development services, including extensive clinical experience as a part of pre-service preparation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida7a59194cbfa4a94a00f7d84f92d2383"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is financially responsible and is not subject to heightened cash monitoring or provisional certification;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1c768bd983b44781bc57ea40d8303990"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides pedagogical course work, or assistance in the provision of such coursework, including the monitoring of student performance, and formal instruction related to the theory and practices of teaching; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id951dc459293d494fa6a8d159d6d9c233"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides supervision and support services to teachers, or assistance in the provision of such services, including mentoring focused on developing effective teaching skills and strategies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id1cac2946aca8410ab7a0200c62e810ef"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Post-baccalaureate</header><text>The term <term>post-baccalaureate</term> means a program of instruction for individuals who have completed a baccalaureate degree, that does not lead to a graduate degree, and that consists of courses required by a State in order for a teacher candidate to receive a professional certification or licensing credential that is required for employment as a teacher in an elementary school or secondary school in that State, except that such term shall not include any program of instruction offered by an eligible institution that offers a baccalaureate degree in education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5cf761b5cebb423e8d8078420438cdfe"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Teacher candidate</header><text>The term <term>teacher candidate</term> means a student or teacher described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of section 420N(a)(2).</text></paragraph></section><section id="idf1446474da844f42b885aa509687e38e"><enum>420M.</enum><header>Program established</header><subsection id="id683d5736bd1f4dbfad8bc82a584c0980"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authority</header><paragraph id="id6e67b5e56f274f17a0be2cb4e490c743"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payments required</header><text>The Secretary shall pay to each eligible institution such sums as may be necessary to pay to each teacher candidate who files an application and agreement in accordance with section 420N, and who qualifies under paragraph (2) of section 420N(a), a TEACH Grant in the amount of $8,000 for each year during which that teacher candidate is in attendance at the institution.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide2708159451a4f5bab0e206997e96807"><enum>(2)</enum><header>References</header><text>Grants made under paragraph (1) shall be known as <quote>Teacher Education Assistance for College and Higher Education Grants</quote> or <quote>TEACH Grants</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id66f35ed1ddc4422f877b43c3e813a393"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment methodology</header><paragraph id="idd9d387fc39614e0d98f16da5f1045b58"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prepayment</header><text>Not less than 85 percent of any funds provided to an eligible institution under subsection (a) shall be advanced to the eligible institution prior to the start of each payment period and shall be based on an amount requested by the institution as needed to pay teacher candidates until such time as the Secretary determines and publishes in the Federal Register with an opportunity for comment, an alternative payment system that provides payments to institutions in an accurate and timely manner, except that this sentence shall not be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary to place an institution on a reimbursement system of payment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id987ddc2e231e4020b79b4b2ec85729ad"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Direct payment</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be interpreted to prohibit the Secretary from paying directly to teacher candidates, in advance of the beginning of the academic term, an amount for which teacher candidates are eligible, in cases in which the eligible institution elects not to participate in the disbursement system required by paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idddf623a7c1d9488397bc72584e7ff2d1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Distribution of grants to teacher candidates</header><text>Payments under this subpart shall be made, in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary for such purpose, in such manner as will best accomplish the purposes of this subpart. Any disbursement allowed to be made by crediting the teacher candidate’s account shall be used for the full cost of attendance (as defined in section 472).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idc61cfc69908e4daf9f5ee95d838a8dc8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reductions in amount</header><paragraph id="ida56e24e8ab45427195d60e8c8183e7cb"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Part-time students</header><text>In any case in which a teacher candidate attends an eligible institution on less than a full-time basis (including a teacher candidate who attends an eligible institution on less than a half-time basis) during any year, the amount of a grant under this subpart for which that teacher candidate is eligible shall be reduced in proportion to the degree to which that teacher candidate is not attending on a full-time basis, in accordance with a schedule of reductions established by the Secretary for the purposes of this subpart, computed in accordance with this subpart. Such schedule of reductions shall be established by regulation and published in the Federal Register in accordance with section 482 of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida6bbdf1d99804ca98b770c4c09c6fb50"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No exceeding cost</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded under this subpart, in combination with Federal assistance and other assistance the student may receive, shall not exceed the cost of attendance (as defined in section 472) at the eligible institution at which that teacher candidate is in attendance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf00dc738b1344802b391a2786ec6e975"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Period of eligibility for grants</header><paragraph id="idb58751dcf9894d4e9883a4ff3d9bd9dc"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Undergraduate and post-baccalaureate students</header><text>The period during which an undergraduate or post-baccalaureate student may receive grants under this subpart shall be the period required for the completion of the first undergraduate baccalaureate or post-baccalaureate course of study being pursued by the teacher candidate at the eligible institution at which the teacher candidate is in attendance, except that—</text><subparagraph id="idb5353179ab194940b4c283428160e25d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any period during which the teacher candidate is enrolled in a noncredit or remedial course of study as described in paragraph (3) shall not be counted for the purpose of this paragraph; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5541aa90b33b45a38fdc817654d6bb56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the total amount that a teacher candidate may receive under this subpart for undergraduate or post-baccalaureate study shall not exceed $40,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id65798dc71b7a466b9ae6b5b52255608f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Graduate students</header><text>The period during which a graduate student may receive grants under this subpart shall be the period required for the completion of a master’s degree course of study pursued by the teacher candidate at the eligible institution at which the teacher candidate is in attendance, except that the total amount that a teacher candidate may receive under this subpart for graduate study shall not exceed $16,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida66e511a242d434198ad85cef6b5fdd4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Remedial course; study abroad</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to exclude from eligibility courses of study which are noncredit or remedial in nature (including courses in English language acquisition) which are determined by the eligible institution to be necessary to help the teacher candidate be prepared for the pursuit of a first undergraduate baccalaureate or post-baccalaureate degree or certificate or, in the case of courses in English language instruction, to be necessary to enable the teacher candidate to use already existing knowledge, training, or skills. Nothing in this section shall be construed to exclude from eligibility programs of study abroad that are approved for credit by the home institution at which the teacher candidate is enrolled.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id359d9b8304f24051bf4100c5dabee941"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Institutional eligibility</header><text>Notwithstanding subsections (a) and (b), an institution shall not be eligible to participate in the TEACH grant program under this subpart for a period of 3 years, and shall be required to submit an application to regain eligibility after that 3 year period, if for a period of 3 consecutive years, 50 percent or more of the TEACH grant recipients who are graduates of that institution have TEACH grants converted to loans under section 420N(c)(1).</text></subsection></section><section id="id6a6f02a83c9f41789ca9c7952bca7940"><enum>420N.</enum><header>Applications; eligibility</header><subsection id="id70011614f1994b75bf97f700896d63c7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Applications; demonstration of eligibility</header><paragraph id="ida01e2a0d25394bca99b57c18adb9d536"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Filing required</header><text>The Secretary shall periodically set dates by which teacher candidates shall file applications for grants under this subpart. Each teacher candidate desiring a grant under this subpart for any year shall file an application containing such information and assurances as the Secretary may determine necessary to enable the Secretary to carry out the functions and responsibilities of this subpart.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2fffa2f91c7342439281ae7e1212f0ba"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Demonstration of teach grant eligibility</header><text>Each application submitted under paragraph (1) shall contain such information as is necessary to demonstrate that—</text><subparagraph id="id52f134439d2d40989a8687b52988ab12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the applicant is an enrolled student—</text><clause id="ida62dbb13ea11456b8ff48cfc2afcd651"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the student is an eligible student for purposes of section 484; and</text></clause><clause id="idcb4fa352fd9e447ea933eb8b6765fb89"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the student is completing coursework and other requirements necessary to begin a career in teaching, or plans to complete such coursework and requirements prior to graduating; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida7d51424f8234aecade6e350988d552a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the applicant is a current or prospective teacher applying for a grant to obtain a graduate degree—</text><clause id="id4315edac50ee4cc28ef79911a4f63ba2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the applicant is a teacher or a retiree from another occupation with expertise in a field in which there is a shortage of teachers, such as mathematics, science, special education, English language acquisition, or another high-need subject;</text></clause><clause id="ida86cd47ec8ed4a16ba537f2446c9b708"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the applicant is or was a teacher who is using evidence-based alternative certification routes; or</text></clause><clause id="id1b63dc9e78f4442eb0efa36b1f52af6c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the applicant is a practicing teacher in another field and is pursuing an additional credential in a field in which there is a shortage of teachers, such as mathematics, science, special education, English language acquisition, or another high-need subject.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id262d0f5dfde3492383a04351c0973b51"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agreements To serve</header><text>Each application under subsection (a) shall contain or be accompanied by an agreement by the applicant that—</text><paragraph id="id48ad752f335d440f9e6777727535b7bd"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the applicant will—</text><subparagraph id="id774406833ef5442f9657e98a0a003f5f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serve as a full-time teacher for a total of not less than 4 academic years within 8 years after completing the course of study for which the applicant received a TEACH Grant under this subpart (referred to in this section as the <quote>service obligation window</quote>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id07c8d214317b43f88064c24b6b5714a7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>teach in a school described in section 465(a)(2)(A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf51d0d8a3cc24f59b7682090c6eee437"><enum>(C)</enum><text>teach in any of the following fields—</text><clause id="id83cfdc2593574db791c717b48db1a5d0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>mathematics;</text></clause><clause id="id298d0e67517c49dc98ea3aa4695f32e4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>science;</text></clause><clause id="idad418ccd4c5b41d29f7e3b2773ce9669"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a foreign language;</text></clause><clause id="id727208bce55c4eaa9f87526ff4f0d6e9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>bilingual education;</text></clause><clause id="idfc3e90d9e84f49338343502ed8fd8c19"><enum>(v)</enum><text>special education;</text></clause><clause id="idc1f842c1c0a146fab121f8323b9cf837"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>as a reading specialist;</text></clause><clause id="idcc37ee8a61fa4778a06e169356d50048"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>early childhood education; or</text></clause><clause id="id5a34d24f8981400e94a3d62d2c821fec"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>another field documented as high-need by the Federal Government, State government, or local educational agency, and approved by the Secretary; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcfe1ac5cbbe64763b7234c887b3db5c3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>submit evidence of such employment in the form of a certification by the chief administrative officer of the school upon completion of each year of such service;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id519b990597ed495b99968ac290bf7b43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the event that the applicant is determined to have failed or refused to carry out such service obligation, an amount (which shall be a pro-rated amount for partial service) of any TEACH Grants received by such applicant will be treated as a loan and collected from the applicant in accordance with subsection (c) and the regulations thereunder; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idad615e701bb849669d923b0a476f40fa"><enum>(3)</enum><text>contains, or is accompanied by, a plain-language disclosure form developed by the Secretary that clearly describes the nature of the TEACH Grant award, the service obligation, and the loan repayment requirements that are the consequence of the failure to complete the service obligation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd6daa037107e4dfc8b01a73afade8ae4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Repayment for failure To complete service</header><paragraph id="id71dfd2ed2e6d46a6afa3f420e33ca2ca"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If any recipient of a grant under this subpart fails or refuses to comply with some or all of the service obligation in the agreement under subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="id5a97b1f5d6e44adab4528f23c0d89982"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary shall determine the proportion of the total amount of time of the service obligation that the recipient has failed or refused to complete; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8fdd9e8837bb40199e751f29afd1e66b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary shall determine, on a pro-rated basis and based on the proportion described in subparagraph (A), the amounts of any TEACH Grants received by such recipient that shall, upon a determination of such a failure or refusal in such service obligation, be treated as a Federal Direct Stafford Loan under part D of title IV (except that such loan shall have an interest rate of 0 percent) and shall ensure that those amounts are subject to repayment, in accordance with terms and conditions specified by the Secretary in regulations under this subpart.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id02a319d0a973469da8879dcd5d0fe095"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Loan deferment</header><text>In the case of a TEACH grant recipient whose grant has been converted to a Federal Direct loan under part D in accordance with paragraph (1) and who is, at the time of such conversion, teaching in an elementary or secondary school that is not a school described in section 465(a)(2)(A), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="idD55D36E0B8F04FEDA79131915ED5A311"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issue that recipient a deferment for a period of not more than 3 years, during which time periodic installments on such loan need not be paid; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8A1D43B4770545878A62BF6A1C8BAD78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that such recipient is enrolled in the loan credit program under section 460, if eligible.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id49791fec1d0a48f7a9636edf9da6c887"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional administrative provisions</header><paragraph id="ide305a7e29e6a4b1e874f55bb602893ee"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Changes to school or designation</header><subparagraph id="id5f5761327cb74742905ead8e69e10dea"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Change of high-need designation field</header><text>If a recipient of an initial grant under this subpart has acquired an academic degree, or expertise, in a field that was, at the time of the recipient’s application for that grant, designated as high need in accordance with subsection (b)(1)(C)(viii), but is no longer so designated, the grant recipient may fulfill the service obligation described in subsection (b)(1) by teaching in that field.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfd2f50e1f74842db817180a874015aef"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Change of high-need designation field or school</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b), if a recipient of a grant under this subpart begins teaching at a school described in subsection (b)(1)(B) and in a field described in subsection (b)(1)(C) during the service obligation window, but such school or field later is no longer designated under subsection (b), the grant recipient may fulfill the service obligation described in subsection (b)(1) by continuing to teach in that school and field and completing the required period of service within the service obligation window.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9eee1ec9927040f89d5ae1ffbbe90bab"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extenuating circumstances</header><text>The Secretary shall establish, by regulation, categories of extenuating circumstances under which a recipient of a grant under this subpart who is unable to fulfill all or part of the recipient’s service obligation may be excused from fulfilling that portion of the service obligation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb375f7e867164f35942f80ee948dcd73"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Extension of service obligation window</header><text>The Secretary shall extend the service obligation window of a TEACH grant recipient for a period of not more than 3 additional years, if that recipient has experienced an event described in section 102(a) of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idfa04753e1d714a4eb61c462bf0e045aa"><enum>420O.</enum><header>Program period and funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There shall be available to the Secretary to carry out this subpart, from funds not otherwise appropriated, such sums as may be necessary to provide TEACH Grants in accordance with this subpart to each eligible applicant.</text></section><section id="idfe91a7ece790401cb0b53d3c1bf32131"><enum>420P.</enum><header>Reports to authorizing committees</header><subsection id="id20a625ef39244fa38301595b2e89eb70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title> and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the authorizing committees a report on TEACH grants with respect to the schools and students served by recipients of such grants. Such report shall take into consideration information related to—</text><paragraph id="ida3c33b4bdf984784a345269a988e0c9f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of TEACH grant recipients;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ideebd94529b44487db6395fdb9b07f14f"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the degrees obtained by such recipients;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2255700d473a43e4beb2bb3492f9fb17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the location, including the school, local educational agency, and State, where the recipients completed the service agreed to under section 420N(b) and the subject taught;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id664d299258854db4ad2a90132dd56710"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the duration of such service; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5a06db2475f84559b125f35df3ddbf61"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other data necessary to conduct such evaluation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id506d562138c548e88252aa99c018b8bb"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title> and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the authorizing committees a report containing information about the following in the period since the last report was submitted:</text><paragraph id="id1cdf82ccdf604241aaf4910b161ed948"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of TEACH grants converted to loans under section 420N(c)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf1409dad60ac4425886e705fbbc51067"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of such grant conversions that were reversed in accordance with section 420N(c)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id63277BBFFD7A4E1DB9FFD3D02312EEA7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The number of contacts or complaints to the Department of Education or the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (including through any ombudsman) received from a TEACH grant recipient, and the resolutions of those contacts or complaints.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id98FAFD8E6293453389D7BB4C5CC4794F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Demographic information about recipients of TEACH grants, including race, ethnicity, and gender. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id79b813e4e4234127b3bb2a18a0731b5e"><enum>420Q.</enum><header>Servicer accountability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to ensure accurate administrative oversight and appropriate penalties for third party servicers in order to ensure that—</text><paragraph id="idda2fedd7a9bb48a3a6031a20703393fa"><enum>(1)</enum><text>those servicers properly perform their contractual obligations with respect to this subpart; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfbb091c5ebe64e3aaec9df730c6190c8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>those servicers are held responsible with respect to the loss of benefits of TEACH grant recipients due to servicer failures.</text></paragraph></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="idc328eed5fde140e7a7230b9eb4044729"><enum>6.</enum><header>Loan forgiveness and cancellation for educators in high need schools or early childhood education programs</header><subsection id="id9288ebc7024643249f0160c196a1a97e"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enhanced teacher loan forgiveness under the FFEL program</header><text>Section 428J of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1078-10">20 U.S.C. 1078–10</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2ccc27ba459347268b91bda47ca8630b"><section id="id6f5cfa6617e542bb8104155e82cc900f"><enum>428J.</enum><header>Loan forgiveness for educators in high need schools or early childhood education programs</header><subsection id="id2a29976880c749e2ad69332fd302b74f"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this section to enhance student access to a well-prepared, diverse, and stable educator workforce by eliminating debt burdens for educators in return for service teaching and leading in high need schools or early childhood education programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="id24e61f8d6ccb48d9854f005e65336d1b"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall carry out a program, through the holder of the loan, of assuming, as required under subsection (c), the obligation to repay a covered loan for qualifying educators engaged in qualifying service. A qualifying educator may apply for the program under this section after the Secretary has begun carrying out the program.</text></subsection><subsection id="idb5cfa8c93cc24e85a975f287e0ce2b88"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Forgiveness of covered loans</header><paragraph id="id4240813e5fa64f34a7430e67087451bb"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Forgiveness of loans upon completion of qualifying service</header><subparagraph id="id3b9c7a5e82f149cc9fc31d3aa101a72b"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each qualifying educator who has completed 5 years of qualifying service (including any qualifying service, as defined under this section as in effect after the date of implementation of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, that may have been completed or performed before or after such date of implementation, or a combination of qualifying service), the Secretary shall assume the obligation to repay an amount equal to 100 percent of the aggregate of the loan obligations (including interest and fees) on all covered loans that are outstanding as of the date of completion of such fifth year of qualifying service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb0c95d7cb1c444f393d346a4650f6e66"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The years of qualifying service required under subparagraph (A) may be consecutive or nonconsecutive, and the qualifying educator may elect which years of qualifying service to use for purposes of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide8ab6ca908e24e6c93a175a03ecf4892"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Monthly loan forgiveness</header><text>Upon application by any qualifying educator who has a covered loan and who is engaged in qualifying service, and in addition to any loan forgiveness under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall enter into an agreement with such qualifying educator, under which—</text><subparagraph id="id462082965f004d8cb21dccc3553b55c3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service (for qualifying service that occurs after the date of implementation of this Act), the Secretary agrees to assume the obligation to repay the minimum monthly obligation on all covered loans of the qualifying educator, based on the repayment plan selected by the qualifying educator, for—</text><clause id="idf848b9d5a2b7456d98e8778c8a42db17"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each month of qualifying service; and</text></clause><clause id="idb0df48f876654b4b91cd195e61665edb"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any summer or other school or program year calendar breaks scheduled by a high need school or early childhood education program during a school or program year in which the qualifying educator is engaged in qualifying service;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id22cf9db363ff4c0b913b288125bfea7b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service, the assumption of the monthly loan obligation provided will serve as a monthly payment, considered paid in full by the qualifying educator, based on the repayment plan selected by the qualifying educator (which, if the qualifying educator chooses, shall include any income driven repayment plan); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd38b3e0249d84549a2c9eb9643a402b8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service, each monthly obligation that is repaid by the Secretary under this paragraph on a covered loan shall be deemed to be a qualifying monthly payment made by the qualifying educator for purposes of the loan forgiveness program under section 455(m), if applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd2881bba5184473a9239d673e0aaa939"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and make publicly available an application for qualifying educators who wish to receive loan forgiveness under this subsection. The application shall—</text><subparagraph id="ida4210041e342471ab197121736f7dc4b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be available for qualifying educators to file for loan forgiveness under paragraph (1) and for monthly loan forgiveness under paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id67ed688765cc49d7a1abd2022a5d19d7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include any certification requirements that the Secretary determines are necessary to verify qualifying service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4067f4dbb32242368824d38d231adfbe"><enum>(C)</enum><text>allow for the verification of the qualifying service—</text><clause id="id398a2f57fa9b4e34a11ba61dfed8a988"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of an early childhood educator or an elementary or secondary school teacher serving in a high need school, by a school leader or the administrator of a local educational agency, educational service agency, Bureau of Indian Education, Native Hawaiian education system, or State educational agency that serves the school (or the administrator’s designee);</text></clause><clause id="idabcd2380272c4324af62ec6095b49836"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of an early childhood educator serving in an early childhood education program, by the director of that program (or the director’s designee);</text></clause><clause id="id7fde9aee146a4757970af0f71fea5e5b"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of a school leader serving in a high need school, by the administrator of a local educational agency, educational service agency, Bureau of Indian Education, Native Hawaiian education system, or State educational agency that serves the school (or the administrator’s designee);</text></clause><clause id="id100f41b746914fd78e11dc1e65757d6a"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of a director of an early childhood education program, a leader of the entity overseeing the early childhood education program; and</text></clause><clause id="id2f75374968ab41fcb97514e3add67747"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in the case of a family child care provider or the director of an early childhood education program that operates as a standalone center-based program (for example, a case in which the center is not part of a larger company) that is an early childhood education program, by self-certification with supporting documents, such as a business license, a listing with a public Child Care Resources and Referral website, or proof of participation in a Federal child care or preschool subsidy program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf15d85e6db934a898e988c4c6b76a1dc"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Parent plus loans</header><subparagraph id="id4b16b7b5817d4f2ba3190d62928e0a26"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Parent plus loan on behalf of a student who is a qualifying educator</header><text>A borrower of a parent loan under section 428B issued on behalf of a student who is a qualifying educator shall qualify for loan forgiveness and any other benefits under this section for the qualifying service of the student in the same manner and to the same extent as the student borrower qualifies for such loan forgiveness and other benefits.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb425bca4390540de80c027a1bb1ce628"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Parent plus loan borrowed by a parent who is a qualifying educator</header><text>The borrower of a parent loan under section 428B issued on behalf of a student who is not a qualifying educator shall also qualify for loan forgiveness and any other benefits under this section for qualifying service if that parent borrower is engaged in qualifying service and meets the requirements of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb2b5e91764744bf8ba5a6f81cb42cba6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Recipients of prior forgiveness</header><text>A qualifying educator who received loan forgiveness under this section as in effect before the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>—</text><subparagraph id="id9d681cd0371a41069273d6c280e25480"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be eligible for loan forgiveness of covered loans in accordance with paragraph (1), including any remaining covered loans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id51b2d2951cfc4961a89ae3cb4ec40fda"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may count the service completed that qualified the qualifying educator for previous loan forgiveness as qualifying service for purposes of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5a72b10173104356819c2ed587581f9b"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition on requiring repayment</header><text>A qualifying educator shall not be required to repay any amounts paid under this subsection if that qualifying educator who engages in qualifying service ends the qualifying service before the end of a school or program year, or before the end of the 5-year period described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id02b8f66dca0e4d4a9815a08b0336aa78"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary is authorized to issue such regulations as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="ida5b60e8a794d468b8e492e573394f9e2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize any refunding of any repayment of a loan.</text></subsection><subsection id="idffd669c5bfec452e99acfaae5828a86d"><enum>(f)</enum><header>List</header><paragraph id="id661811e647f04dcfb71e6f8b12d050c7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="id89e1d2466a624751ad1dfe610bf2ad7b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as soon as practicable, produce and make publicly available a list of high need schools for purposes of this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id318ce374916146c49eab9d3f1ae17f7c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>annually update such list.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf701e5750292454abd2a0371b6c0cc9f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>List from previous year</header><text>If the list of high need schools in which a qualifying educator may perform qualifying service is not available before May 1 of any year, the Secretary may use the list for the year preceding the year for which the determination is made to make a determination about whether an individual meets the requirements for qualifying service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id8fc159a52dd143eb8796c0d18093ef71"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional eligibility provisions</header><paragraph id="id5f74ed63b07b491191280094a193b75a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Continued eligibility</header><text>Any qualifying educator who performs qualifying service in a school that—</text><subparagraph id="id0e8166cdce2f42f599dd1104358cfd2c"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a high need school in any school year during such service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idefa55019226e4d29ac4d843746c6b5d1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a subsequent school year fails to meet the definition of a high need school, may continue to serve in such school and shall be eligible for loan forgiveness pursuant to subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id22de9dbf267e4489a56337646f7b69d7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prevention of double benefits</header><text>No qualifying educator may, for the same service, receive a benefit under both this section and—</text><subparagraph id="id4325cd2c7cf240428822ce558bd6ad8c"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 428K; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb3e8d890881d45b28021b0b8d2a20226"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subtitle D of title I of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12601">42 U.S.C. 12601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0d6360dbb77d4616bfa68e347901ea30"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No penalty for promotions</header><text>Any qualifying educator who performs qualifying service in an early childhood education program or high need school and who is promoted to another position within that early childhood program or high need school after 1 or more years of qualifying service may continue to be employed in such position in such program or school and shall be eligible to count the period of employment in such position as qualifying service for loan forgiveness pursuant to subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idaeaa1ca5396b43c8b576a58508e8d64a"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id8b4e5bccc8544327ab7974c07e5f2b62"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school</header><text>The term <term>Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id33dbc3762ba94d18bda4e033cb4367eb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated by the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide06758f320cf4c94b7815f5c5233e2bf"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated pursuant to a grant under the Tribally Controlled Schools Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2501">25 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7a1c097868034864b701c1cda3a0d957"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated pursuant to a contract under the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id55e78d498a2343ce8784e4ada836ba5d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program</header><text>The term <term>Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idad5c6022767a41c6b8d75fe191f49be8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a program operating under a grant authorized by section 1139 of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2019">25 U.S.C. 2019</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida313fcb5068a4e38a2b9ed96542d1d33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early childhood education program operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education (including Family and Child Education programs at schools funded by the Bureau of Indian Education authorized under section 1121 of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2001">25 U.S.C. 2001</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idae2f0bee72c7448e80bc85079bdf38c2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered loan</header><text>The term <term>covered loan</term> means a loan made, insured, or guaranteed under this part.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id53dfd0d46d7f48cb9994c5ab5901db7a"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>early childhood education program</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idae06e380b9874aaa973eecd84ad2d122"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a high-need early childhood education program as defined in section 200;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id57354c508e9847d583cf5596267b14ac"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a Head Start program (including an Early Head Start program) carried out under the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0f0b6b7bd7734c83bdf453cb1ddd6a69"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an early childhood education program, as defined in section 103;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida6f5b4765551469b8ccb2cf0d66e6c91"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id97d17d0a1c5748b9ad31fec157b698eb"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian education system early childhood education program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide835175535654d2ea17745eca776e86a"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Tribal early childhood education program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id231a5697ac7c44ca971d0cbdeac89142"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (F).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2c6f09bbc9e947bd9467e452b4685f2f"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High need school</header><text>The term <term>high need school</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id96ba78f9fddc4c9899fb65506a1de6e9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school—</text><clause id="id0e5908ad0e6d443d9e3dbe2f0be4d142"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with respect to which the number of children meeting a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, exceeds 30 percent of the total number of children enrolled in such school; and</text></clause><clause id="idd3e601c4b86b465f9dce9e3d50fb33d5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that is served by a local educational agency that is eligible for assistance pursuant to part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf21ea6e44b094f9b8443c5cc67f02955"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school or location operated by an educational service agency in which the number of children meeting a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 exceeds 30 percent of the total number of children enrolled in such school or location;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0cdd349e3b3848c387e85bc51ae6175b"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school identified by the State for comprehensive support and improvement, targeted support and improvement, or additional targeted support and improvement, under section 1111 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id91f35032d74d4800887163a3b4822283"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id67418a479a864074809510faa93f599f"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school operated by a Tribal educational agency; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1d291994960f45439eedb19b0453b2cb"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian education system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idbbcc55a8a24d459699af3e105013c639"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> means the recognized governing body of any Indian or Alaska Native Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, component band, or component reservation, individually identified (including parenthetically) in the list published most recently as of the date of enactment of this subtitle pursuant to section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3cf9ab778ae246cdb407e29202490669"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian education system</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiian education system</term> means an entity eligible to receive direct grants or enter into contracts with the Secretary under section 6205 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7515">20 U.S.C. 7515</external-xref>) to carry out the authorized activities under that section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idabaf3456dcb149989f2ab9987dc92c5c"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Qualifying educator</header><text>Subject to subsection (i), the term <term>qualifying educator</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idf752169c0a62448196e300bdf8eb5260"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school teacher who—</text><clause id="idb1088c5f778a4fdf9567ceaa7a721422"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has obtained full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment; and</text></clause><clause id="idab480d2271ab4c799912c209553edbf6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not had such certification or licensure requirements waived on an emergency, temporary, or provisional basis;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf773a96e55004ab59f6f7100319b8299"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early childhood educator who provides care or instruction to children;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbcb7d59b54154a83bc7f255a5ac607de"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a school leader of an elementary or secondary school who—</text><clause id="id87a7183b3aac40559e22e685120d5612"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has obtained full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment; and</text></clause><clause id="idfb4643ae1a5e444385e25fd4857fa485"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not had such certification or licensure requirements waived on an emergency, temporary, or provisional basis; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idadc79654422649ecaf43707d462ea490"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an early childhood education program director (including a family child care provider).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7604d2df7a7a49c287bdff24a8562e06"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Qualifying service</header><subparagraph id="id2b7c09076fd5420ab24a099a9b0ecfe0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the term <term>qualifying service</term> means—</text><clause id="id5668cee55e964f198b8d3ceee4bbf3de"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a qualifying educator described in subparagraph (A) or (C) of paragraph (8), employment as a full-time qualifying educator in a high need school; and</text></clause><clause id="id3ebd695c069c4903bfccadd353340e51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a qualifying educator described in subparagraph (B) or (D) of paragraph (8), employment as a full-time qualifying educator in an early childhood education program (including school-based programs).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id70e78b8c20d242deafe523ed899deeea"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>In the case of a qualifying educator who is unable to complete a full school or program year of service, that year may still be counted toward the required qualifying service period under paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (c) if—</text><clause id="id5548e2e5fc7a490cbe528d5f39399a67"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the qualifying educator completed at least one-half of the school or program year;</text></clause><clause id="idef6cebc681944a609786ecf740a95c1f"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the employer considers the qualifying educator to have fulfilled the contract requirements for the school or program year for the purposes of salary increases, tenure, and retirement; and</text></clause><clause id="id0042decff16c41aa935ae1165609690c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the qualifying educator was unable to complete the school or program year because—</text><subclause id="id28388346602d4ecdbe8aae8581687c7c"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the qualifying educator returned to postsecondary education, on at least a half-time basis, in an area of study directly related to the performance of the qualifying service;</text></subclause><subclause id="id5052fe0595f449b894ec715cebc8e3e4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the qualifying educator experienced a condition described in section 102 of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="id0a1223b14c5c44249dfdf581b9e5e5e9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the qualifying educator was called or ordered to Federal or State active duty status, or Active Service as a member of a Reserve Component of the Armed Forces named in section 10101 of title 10, United States Code, or service as a member of the National Guard on full-time National Guard duty, as defined in section 101(d)(5) of title 10, United States Code; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idea5d473574fd474f8169e9411ff518b5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the qualifying educator resides in or is employed in a disaster area, as declared by any Federal, State, or local official in connection with a national emergency.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id753fa3683c764d5c9b08fab3e2c8a0bb"><enum>(10)</enum><header>School leader</header><text>The term <term>school leader</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3f698cd26cd74b4996e9412aafb2859c"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Tribal early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>Tribal early childhood education program</term> means any of the following programs:</text><subparagraph id="id57cf3fb5102c45c3b2b7ca2f8fa5955e"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An American Indian or Alaska Native Head Start or Early Head Start program carried out under the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4faf16f2ab2a482b9e3ee0fcb95cb1bf"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A Tribal child care and development program carried out under the Child Care and Development Block Grant of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858">42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2706fd2a9329413bbe4ddeab59f52c02"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A program serving children from birth through age 6 that—</text><clause id="idd54bd16af7dd4ca59824728e2c133e8c"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receives funding support from the Native American language preservation and maintenance program carried out under section 803C of the Native American Programs Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2991b-3">42 U.S.C. 2991b–3</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="ide895fc0dc8b94623b62db679983f060d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a Tribal prekindergarten program;</text></clause><clause id="id58849d695bcd4f8f9d89850a8bd6cf6d"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is a program authorized under section 619 or part C of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act; or</text></clause><clause id="id5ba2d569c5a0467baba03070b3bd12cb"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is a center-based or group-based early childhood learning or development program that the Secretary determines shall be included under this definition, after receiving a request from an Indian Tribe.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id61887aa8ec5e45a7a77a425d8825101b"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Tribal educational agency</header><text>The term <term>Tribal educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term (without respect to capitalization) in section 6132(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd760294c03104e37a2cbff27fcd6ee6d"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Year</header><text>The term <term>year</term>, when applied to service as a qualifying educator, means a school or program year as defined by the Secretary or the Secretary of Health and Human Services, as applicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id25acb723ffe84e38851854db52fa124a"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>An educator that provides instruction or curricular development in an Alaska Native, American Indian, or Native Hawaiian language or a Native American language as defined in the Native American Languages Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2902">25 U.S.C. 2902</external-xref>) shall be considered to be a qualifying educator regardless of whether the educator has achieved full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id4adaed73b6944f8db30bda5f43e4075c"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enhanced teacher loan cancellation under the direct loan program</header><text>Section 460 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087j">20 U.S.C. 1087j</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2a17956f598547dbb5e9ef26e57a8bde"><section id="idc951bdd4daa949afbbc13d5340f90710"><enum>460.</enum><header>Loan cancellation for educators</header><subsection id="id50a1e739096e4e9ab3aab878995be591"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this section to enhance student access to a well-prepared, diverse, and stable educator workforce by eliminating debt burdens for educators in return for service teaching and leading in high need schools or early childhood education programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="id5531ee15909d43bba2290dda92e42d0a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall carry out a program of canceling, as required under subsection (c), the obligation to repay a covered loan for qualifying educators engaged in qualifying service. A qualifying educator may apply for the program under this section after the Secretary has begun carrying out the program.</text></subsection><subsection id="idac347221739d44d6856fdf01e7c61aea"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cancellation of covered loans</header><paragraph id="id616eabc621a84410b4cb67e9349625d3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cancellation of loans upon completion of qualifying service</header><subparagraph id="id91013e82c1ed40c18d40d7d8974ff049"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each qualifying educator who has completed 5 years of qualifying service (including any qualifying service, as defined under this section as in effect after the date of implementation of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, that may have been completed or performed before or after such date of implementation, or a combination of qualifying service), the Secretary shall cancel an amount equal to 100 percent of the aggregate of the loan obligations (including interest and fees) on all covered loans that are outstanding as of the date of completion of such fifth year of qualifying service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idda34fb478fa945e9a00baf7d68a9ffed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The years of qualifying service required under subparagraph (A) may be consecutive or nonconsecutive, and the qualifying educator may elect which years of qualifying service to use for purposes of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id907b6badcb884eda8e2b8fd0043b4692"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Monthly loan cancellation</header><text>Upon application by any qualifying educator of a covered loan who is engaged in qualifying service, and in addition to any loan cancellation under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall enter into an agreement with such qualifying educator, under which—</text><subparagraph id="id06066da95aca40ec9cec2fc5f8afa61a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service (for qualifying service that occurs after the date of implementation of this Act), the Secretary agrees to cancel the minimum monthly obligation on all covered loans of the qualifying educator based on the repayment plan selected by the qualifying educator (which, if the educator chooses, shall include any income driven repayment plan), for—</text><clause id="id3b9da381b0bb456f945a0684cb03a250"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each month of qualifying service; and</text></clause><clause id="id73b1a744b94c42f2a18bf986051c5466"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any summer or other school or program year calendar breaks scheduled by a qualifying school or early childhood education program during a school or program year in which the qualifying educator is engaged in qualifying service;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb6a17593f6db460d938e09a7ca2fdd5d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service, interest shall not accrue on the qualifying educator’s covered loans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id29238ed17971421dab4d5cd4807f8c06"><enum>(C)</enum><text>during the period of qualifying service, each monthly obligation that is cancelled by the Secretary under this paragraph on a covered loan shall be deemed to be a qualifying monthly payment made by the qualifying educator for purposes of the loan forgiveness program under section 455(m), if applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf3073e0020c4409ba3a7e87f3a8cb45f"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and make publicly available an application for qualifying educators who wish to receive loan cancellation under this subsection. The application shall—</text><subparagraph id="id27496882b0194c1587387ff6f065f5d6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be available for qualifying educators to file for loan cancellation under paragraph (1) and for monthly loan cancellation under paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8b8f74c1e0464f24acb2f4e00cbd1048"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include any certification requirements that the Secretary determines are necessary to verify qualifying service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idec72872476a4413b9aeedf42bd3eea01"><enum>(C)</enum><text>allow for the verification of the qualifying service—</text><clause id="id4b5b3390cec748a6bfb3705c472acef3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of an early childhood educator or an elementary or secondary school teacher serving in a high need school, by a school leader or the administrator of a local educational agency, educational service agency, Bureau of Indian Education, Native Hawaiian education system, or State educational agency that serves the school (or the administrator's designee);</text></clause><clause id="id76aa5050952e409e88e2a395cf45b90e"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of an early childhood educator serving in a early childhood education program, by the director of that program (or the director’s designee);</text></clause><clause id="id2b90b5979cc4453c821dbb1bbfd8c995"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of a school leader serving in a high need school, by the administrator of a local educational agency, educational service agency, Bureau of Indian Education, Native Hawaiian education system, or State educational agency that serves the school (or the administrator's designee);</text></clause><clause id="id479b085d16f24d5e809b630201a7cebe"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of a director of an early childhood education program, a leader of the entity overseeing the early childhood education program; and</text></clause><clause id="ided753d72b5e64e2dada1474dc91cdd67"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in the case of a family child care provider or the director of an early childhood education program that operates as a standalone center-based program (for example, a case in which the center is not part of a larger company) that is an early childhood education program, by self-certification with supporting documents, such as a business license, a listing with a public Child Care Resources and Referral website, or proof of participation in a Federal child care or preschool subsidy program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf6d001d6687849dbb1e099649aa96795"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loans</header><subparagraph id="id46a340171da046af8cf5b0c10e3f5135"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loan on behalf of a student who is a qualifying educator</header><text>A borrower of a parent Federal Direct PLUS Loan issued on behalf of a student who is a qualifying educator shall qualify for loan forgiveness and any other benefits under this section for the qualifying service of the student in the same manner and to the same extent as the student borrower qualifies for such loan forgiveness and other benefits.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idacef8e76c362417ab09e0876e581af88"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loan borrowed by a parent who is a qualifying educator</header><text>The borrower of a parent Federal Direct PLUS Loan issued on behalf of a student who is not a qualifying educator shall also qualify for loan forgiveness and any other benefits under this section for qualifying service if that parent borrower is engaged in qualifying service and meets the requirements of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id91c11d7f21ea44299485fc1716947fa4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Recipients of prior loan cancellation</header><text>A qualifying educator who received loan cancellation under this section as in effect before the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>—</text><subparagraph id="idee2d2717098d41a599743dd5caa50b8a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be eligible for loan cancellation of covered loans in accordance with subsection (c)(1), including any remaining covered loans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2f84e65496d1464699af68b1955d407d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may count the service completed that qualified the qualifying educator for previous loan cancellation as qualifying service for purposes of subsection (c)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id733230d51c2e4db79e00316bc54d1641"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition on requiring repayment</header><text>A qualifying educator shall not be required to repay any amounts paid under this subsection if that qualifying educator who engages in qualifying service ends the qualifying service before the end of a school or program year, or before the end of the 5-year period described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idfa35487e8dbf477685037e8c7cbcc964"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary is authorized to issue such regulations as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id5bc2aea265a74e25ad6c8948ef1d6c47"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize any refunding of any canceled loan.</text></subsection><subsection id="id9453a0d088e14cbdbf5fd00d1bbb9008"><enum>(f)</enum><header>List</header><paragraph id="id07271ffa60aa40bbb4235011c04c312c"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="idf95362f14c2a4932a70b728572cce738"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as soon as practicable, produce and make publicly available a list of high need schools for purposes of this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ebc28a6a1334bd892b49e7c88c15f75"><enum>(B)</enum><text>annually update such list.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="iddb01b029cbec4339be04dd93f7516b67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>List from previous year</header><text>If the list of high need schools in which a qualifying educator may perform qualifying service is not available before May 1 of any year, the Secretary may use the list for the year preceding the year for which the determination is made to make a determination about whether an individual meets the requirements for qualifying service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id8df0083ddd0645adbf7cd27ba9d81071"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional eligibility provisions</header><paragraph id="ide18de9348dcc4c46b0f320a646b8aa3a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Continued eligibility</header><text>Any qualifying educator who performs qualifying service in a school that—</text><subparagraph id="idca634f7e621f4585aba6b5437c15337f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a high need school in any school year during such service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id27d179024c4e4754929db185e1ffcfde"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a subsequent school year fails to meet the definition of a high need school, may continue to serve in such school and shall be eligible for loan cancellation pursuant to subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd19757f0c2dd42ba9ea5762db3b78e74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prevention of double benefits</header><text>No qualifying educator may, for the same service, receive a benefit under both this section and—</text><subparagraph id="idcabc439513aa4d54a38e922cd4287f86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 428K; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0faf51a977234ad48f539d7d10e2b613"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subtitle D of title I of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12601">42 U.S.C. 12601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id576c2bf3d810452bae6f4c64cd25323a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No penalty for promotions</header><text>Any qualifying educator who performs qualifying service in an early childhood education program or high need school and who is promoted to another position within that early childhood program or high need school after 1 or more years of qualifying service may continue to be employed in such position in such program or school and shall be eligible to count the period of employment in such position as qualifying service for loan cancellation pursuant to subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id10c71174ea6e4f1ea8c64deb4c91133d"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id72f10f9670f34ca9bc066ac826942be4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school</header><text>The term <term>Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id308b50ddd9d34afbaaff9c9fd2d3f9f4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated by the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb610710e6d4a4860be08f86edb04af8d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated pursuant to a grant under the Tribally Controlled Schools Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2501">25 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3de3a1f7f99043ac9a1f8b870f2ba4ca"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school or dormitory operated pursuant to a contract under the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfe24c016dad9487e92bf79356371990f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program</header><text>The term <term>Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id6a0380eca2b24ecbb73f3b815c1c7c26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a program operating under a grant authorized by section 1139 of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2019">25 U.S.C. 2019</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id40eb2862cf394453b6d37136a5977e78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early childhood education program operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education (including Family and Child Education programs at schools funded by the Bureau of Indian Education authorized under section 1121 of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2001">25 U.S.C. 2001</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id3d2a2c18be794f54b88b2be5611f2328"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered loan</header><text>The term <term>covered loan</term> means a loan made, insured, or guaranteed under this part.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb9ea3417cf2b4ca4b474e207d67652eb"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>early childhood education program</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id51ce4708d8f041a39fb3b4f910266182"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a high-need early childhood education program as defined in section 200;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd328aa9f36ee44ffb3bf8e16178053ee"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a Head Start program (including an Early Head Start program) carried out under the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idae95f0479be94f68ad0cb61110eab96e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an early childhood education program, as defined in section 103;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idda091deaca5f41c0b9da2faf83846f69"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a Bureau of Indian Education early childhood development program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5b67c483b17d4971b0c44b2bd00fa7db"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian education system early childhood education program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0d272ac693464c12b83483008e2e875b"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Tribal early childhood education program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd720c47543574dfaa7757460eb705fdb"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (F).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id47024113e2ac43d1aa2d0c84af67e5ec"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High need school</header><text>The term <term>high need school</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id44af740420bd42fb90d1dd0bc7c7d4ea"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school—</text><clause id="idb69cb6c1812042ad84ac02fc2c678bfc"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with respect to which the number of children meeting a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, exceeds 30 percent of the total number of children enrolled in such school; and</text></clause><clause id="idc730182a1849411d994d0bab7a7ab49b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that is served by a local educational agency that is eligible for assistance pursuant to part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1e14b33ab0ea4455b9b105cd414cf278"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school or location operated by an educational service agency in which the number of children meeting a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 exceeds 30 percent of the total number of children enrolled in such school or location;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id66b5a0866a98439e8637750550ea317e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a public elementary or secondary school identified by the State for comprehensive support and improvement, targeted support and improvement, or additional targeted support and improvement, under section 1111 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida803a95973a949fc9aa86b6bedcfee62"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a Bureau of Indian Education funded elementary or secondary school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idec36d76c3b6a4a6e82ce2c33cfeccd52"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school operated by a Tribal educational agency; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide94e728e36ed47e8bddfcd06194196dc"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian education system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7d14db7ee23a429aa1257a073bb11f49"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> means the recognized governing body of any Indian or Alaska Native Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, component band, or component reservation, individually identified (including parenthetically) in the list published most recently as of the date of enactment of this subtitle pursuant to section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9de8d319aeb94a81bb3cbbc37f7cb738"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian education system</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiian education system</term> means an entity eligible to receive direct grants or enter into contracts with the Secretary under section 6205 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7515">20 U.S.C. 7515</external-xref>) to carry out the authorized activities under that section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id92087a5ea7b9462b82cfeda6e3168a29"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Qualifying educator</header><text>Subject to subsection (i), the term <term>qualifying educator</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id83b6600bb01442dbb249725cfb25c380"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an elementary or secondary school teacher who—</text><clause id="id897d7b3d5be54bdba7ba200ccaad7c07"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has obtained full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment; and</text></clause><clause id="iddadf823e1f9540618ab34ca30b471abc"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not had such certification or licensure requirements waived on an emergency, temporary, or provisional basis;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd34522c2ecb74eb482dd5756e45c9780"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early childhood educator who provides care or instruction to children;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida02d74507e5844a08aa883b2b737063c"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a school leader of an elementary or secondary school who—</text><clause id="ide42c8469bd9c4ca9ad707512d6cf5fe9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has obtained full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment; and</text></clause><clause id="id68ba462fcf56489db5e67889e99ce227"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not had such certification or licensure requirements waived on an emergency, temporary, or provisional basis; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf5915f2723e545b192ab8971455361c0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an early childhood education program director (including a family child care provider).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfef27b02a9bd46c18051f716205df192"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Qualifying service</header><subparagraph id="id7dc98b56f6ca4342939097a5e6468362"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the term <term>qualifying service</term> means—</text><clause id="id2c32e6a1d8d84051bc05a9ce326ef08a"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a qualifying educator described in subparagraph (A) or (C) of paragraph (8), employment as a full-time qualifying educator in a high need school; and</text></clause><clause id="id60539ec44eee4473802713d730121688"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a qualifying educator described in subparagraph (B) or (D) of paragraph (8), employment as a full-time qualifying educator in an early childhood education program (including school-based programs).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0dc88f7da60a4f68bb5e5456dd669a92"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>In the case of a qualifying educator who is unable to complete a full school or program year of service, that year may still be counted toward the required qualifying service period under paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (c) if—</text><clause id="id013d6550a4e545229d4ed669e17ff568"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the qualifying educator completed at least one-half of the school or program year;</text></clause><clause id="idb9c8817b48824113a7ffb0ecb0a53a5d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the employer considers the qualifying educator to have fulfilled the contract requirements for the school or program year for the purposes of salary increases, tenure, and retirement; and</text></clause><clause id="idd35e9ef15f7944aa94f6f398c0e45a54"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the qualifying educator was unable to complete the school or program year because—</text><subclause id="id02bd1a9abb8d466d94522ce3baa338cf"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the qualifying educator returned to postsecondary education, on at least a half-time basis, in an area of study directly related to the performance of the qualifying service;</text></subclause><subclause id="idac7020856d1c40f18fc1aa8bea3681f0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the qualifying educator experienced a condition described in section 102 of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="idf382468805d14de4bde0c2cef42d9d2a"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the qualifying educator was called or ordered to Federal or State active duty status, or Active Service as a member of a Reserve Component of the Armed Forces named in section 10101 of title 10, United States Code, or service as a member of the National Guard on full-time National Guard duty, as defined in section 101(d)(5) of title 10, United States Code; or</text></subclause><subclause id="id912696f119934f0babd0c529b98140a4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the qualifying educator resides in or is employed in a disaster area, as declared by any Federal, State, or local official in connection with a national emergency.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id781f4972d943484190d053d590170d0d"><enum>(10)</enum><header>School leader</header><text>The term <term>school leader</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9beab632086846c2abf3918706d39bfe"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Tribal early childhood education program</header><text>The term <term>Tribal early childhood education program</term> means any of the following programs:</text><subparagraph id="id10e5e82bc24b4ab792cad5ff9d896e93"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An American Indian or Alaska Native Head Start or Early Head Start program carried out under the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida2dc6ce7b5f14d80a01c7a04f4f54c7a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A Tribal child care and development program carried out under the Child Care and Development Block Grant of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858">42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd836d7cf326343298fef7a0e71f6958e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A program serving children from birth through age 6 that—</text><clause id="id33b2e15c6ff74c4ea903399976c5f118"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receives funding support from the Native American language preservation and maintenance program carried out under section 803C of the Native American Programs Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2991b-3">42 U.S.C. 2991b–3</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="id50d7c5bd8b1441319f7cde0aa512a2c2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a Tribal prekindergarten program;</text></clause><clause id="idcf263d6ae165468499068fc917f31d1b"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is a program authorized under section 619 or part C of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act; or</text></clause><clause id="id24c2f69321494a8f87e8634e9f0e6c42"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is a center-based or group-based early childhood learning or development program that the Secretary determines shall be included under this definition, after receiving a request from an Indian Tribe.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5a836ccce6f84d209c09e63267f22cf3"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Tribal educational agency</header><text>The term <term>Tribal educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term (without respect to capitalization) in section 6132(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id76ba17965c3c4ec580fa57bac5cbf2dd"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Year</header><text>The term <term>year</term>, when applied to service as a qualifying educator, means a school or program year as defined by the Secretary or the Secretary of Health and Human Services, as applicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida429c23e09534e4eacc0c465503d5766"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>An educator that provides instruction or curricular development in an Alaska Native, American Indian, or Native Hawaiian language or a Native American language as defined in the Native American Languages Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2902">25 U.S.C. 2902</external-xref>) shall be considered to be a qualifying educator regardless of whether the educator has achieved full State or Tribal certification and licensure requirements for such employment.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id1aef714fb4d545feb363839e269883d1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date; program name</header><paragraph id="idccc6c894e2fb426eaee6a36fb0b55e17"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall take effect on the day that is 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf5de5617736e441d99ee73e2ab9d8dc6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program name</header><text>The programs under section 428J and 460 of the Higher Education Act of 1965, as amended by subsections (a) and (b), shall be known as <quote>Educator Loan Forgiveness Programs</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id5a5f32abe8ad4f13954b47a179644728"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 455(m)(4) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e(m)(4)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 428J, 428K, 428L, or 460</quote> and inserting <quote>section 428K or 428L</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="id9EA0D72142F14629B03A657B6ECFFE15"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress a report containing information about the impact of the amendments made under this section, which shall include data on the participation rate of eligible borrowers, the dollar amount of benefits to participants, and the performance of servicers.</text></subsection></section><section id="id639620cbc83548d0acc00d5a8b475b3b"><enum>7.</enum><header>Loan credit for educators</header><subsection id="id85120E62428C4488B233B2B851CEE9A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Loan credit for educators</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part D of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087a">20 U.S.C. 1087a et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id915cae5c20244cf3911320802f577c4b"><section id="idDADFCB0090874E20A1274BA70EDF9A4C"><enum>461.</enum><header>Loan credit for eligible educators</header><subsection id="id7D81A9C946A24B43BE8B883AB64361A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this section to encourage individuals to enter and continue in the education profession.</text></subsection><subsection id="id7f45b9dd6623410e8ae074454397bb9b"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>Beginning not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall carry out a program of applying monthly credits in accordance with subsection (c) for covered loans for any new borrower on or after October 1, 1998, who is an eligible educator or who has a covered loan on behalf of an eligible educator in accordance with subsection (d)(1)(B).</text></subsection><subsection id="id2ca0efd7c2d2442d809f75b02f55af51"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualified loan amounts</header><paragraph id="id42cb2cac4d19424c9340a716a4636061"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="id387A8DC691F5454AB8D10F6FCF1C7851"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Amount of credit</header><text>For every eligible educator enrolled in an income contingent or income-based repayment plan (including plans under section 493C or section 455(d)(1)(D)), the Secretary shall apply a monthly credit for each month of covered service (including past covered service on or after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>) to the balance of interest and principal due on any covered loan for that eligible educator in an amount that, when added to the monthly payment required from the borrower, would be equal to the monthly payment amount that would repay the borrower’s original balance and accrued interest on the basis of a 10-year amortization schedule. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idDC6677CF8EAD4E679847333BA7F27773"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered service</header><text>With respect to monthly credits described in subparagraph (A), <term>covered service</term> means full-time employment as an educator beginning on or after the date of enactment of the <short-title>EDUCATORS for America Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="IDA5F4E7083AD9483C83E41F41E1412B7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prevention of double benefits</header><text>No borrower may, for the same voluntary service, receive a benefit under both this section and—</text><subparagraph id="id8A7CB93EFACB486B9034DBD8332A40FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 428K; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ID1AE8B9A1552142B687A779F4E0E11E0B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subtitle D of title I of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12601">42 U.S.C. 12601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ID032A9A21DC8F4E48A6AA39F77C9858AE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="id395A3057CEBE411EB083074FCF00A12C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered loan</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6c83388565bf43998d59b0dd1469425d"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered loan</term> means a loan that is not in default that is—</text><clause id="id99F044052E004E95BA0D9D6F1C2395E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a Federal Direct Stafford Loan, a Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan, or a Federal Direct PLUS Loan (which may include a loan to the parent of a dependent student), under this part; or</text></clause><clause id="idF427D71FFF6E4E29BDD5395D398F214A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a loan amount for a Federal Direct Consolidation Loan only to the extent that such loan amount was used to repay a Federal Direct Stafford Loan, a Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan, or a Federal Direct PLUS Loan (which may include a loan to the parent of a dependent student) under this part.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idFFFFC544DA81424882B79E75CB40104B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loans</header><clause id="idF091ABD7B8D04B9EACEFC4CD77C354D5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loan on behalf of a student who is an eligible educator borrower</header><text>A borrower of a parent Federal Direct PLUS Loan issued on behalf of a student who is an eligible educator shall qualify for monthly credit and any other benefits under this section for the covered service of the student in the same manner and to the same extent as the student borrower qualifies for such monthly credit and other benefits.</text></clause><clause id="id79FC7932573C4637BECBFB962A0CAF47"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Parent PLUS loan borrowed by a parent who is an eligible educator</header><text>The borrower of a parent Federal Direct PLUS Loan issued on behalf of a student who is not an eligible educator shall also qualify for the monthly credit and any other benefits under this section for covered service if that parent borrower is engaged in covered service and meets the requirements of this section. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id900B343B31B44410BFA8A81D20CC32AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible educator</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible educator</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="id8F0ADE2BD3E64D4BBE15CC5B958B0B51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is employed on a full-time basis as an educator, as defined under section 200; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idDD734EB8EE8F4EF2B2FE8576381AFD56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not simultaneously receiving monthly loan cancellation benefits under section 460.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id49ED4D9C5163489B9105BF57A559900D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Year</header><text>For the purpose of this section, the term <term>year</term> where applied to service as a teacher means an academic year as defined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="idF9B6F8D7F36E44658020E78C93D8A82B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress a report containing information about the impact of the amendment made under subsection (a), which shall include data on the participation rate of eligible borrowers, the dollar amount of benefits to participants, and the performance of servicers.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

