<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-HEY23903-XSR-14-NR3"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S2047 IS: Military Housing Readiness Council Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 2047</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S366">Ms. Warren</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S324">Mrs. Shaheen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S361">Ms. Hirono</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend title 10, United States Code, to create a Department of Defense Military Housing Readiness Council to enhance oversight and accountability for deficiencies in military housing, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military Housing Readiness Council Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id4c796b50d44a42e384ed8de7dc6e4a49"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Defense Military Housing Readiness Council</header><subsection id="id9bcf73c5a4ba409d8b4abdf0449f8673"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/88">chapter 88</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1781c">section 1781c</external-xref> the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2982854bd0d44f6cae63e4eb5122147e"><section id="ida79a84e75f99476e94cc6ba0d5e4f906"><enum>1781d.</enum><header>Department of Defense Military Housing Readiness Council</header><subsection id="ida6f0d87b8a3548dea0bf1ab5d1fd26a2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is in the Department of Defense the Department of Defense Military Housing Readiness Council (in this section referred to as the <quote>Council</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="id61bf84ff926d4a91a42becb850fdcd99"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Members</header><paragraph id="id96ec1404169d43f0888e5c63c0be8e98"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Council shall be composed of the following members:</text><subparagraph id="idb5fd93f9733d4354ab4ea20c1ec413c2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment, who shall serve as chair of the Council and who may designate a representative to chair the Council in the absence of the Assistant Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9453846287bd47f199e5687f6a45d1ac"><enum>(B)</enum><text>One representative of each of the Army, Navy, Air Force, Marine Corps, and Space Force, each of whom shall be a member of the armed force to be represented and not fewer than two of which shall be from an enlisted component.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc0bf2ff9178c4ad89d1a3da149d81749"><enum>(C)</enum><text>One spouse of a member of each of the Army, Navy, Air Force, Marine Corps, and Space Force on active duty, not fewer than two of which shall be the spouse of an enlisted member. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8e2876f69d3c4a4fb4c1ca781bd94640"><enum>(D)</enum><text>One professional from each of the following fields, each of whom shall possess expertise in State and Federal housing standards in their respective field:</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idcdf70b150db64a8bbb0db5340202606b"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Plumbing.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id857550bbf7d842578c32f5cd715da895"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Electrical.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idac170e9303f74e428b811fa4c9717870"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC).</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id772ced7f346240fc94ab4de583733df7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Certified home inspection.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbbb50c1dd6fd4369aefcf5cf52be05bc"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Roofing.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id81cfdaaf17534b4dbfc65841b3e16476"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Structural engineering.</text></clause><clause id="id2717dc51a46b43b685a691ed46c578ef"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Window fall prevention and safety. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id810f23fdaa09479281b978b84671ca85"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Two representatives of organizations that advocate on behalf of military families with respect to military housing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1697c44d969e485190878744117905ed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Secretary of Defense among representatives of the International Code Council.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4880cc8a4e254b80b573c17a24fd82cd"><enum>(G)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Secretary of Defense among representatives of the Institute of Inspection Cleaning and Restoration Certification.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id528d5d8a5c014c6797ba7d04d96317bb"><enum>(H)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Secretary of Defense among representatives of a voluntary consensus standards body that develops construction standards (such as building, plumbing, mechanical, or electrical).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb7b017bcba954164b6cd79aeebb4cb92"><enum>(I)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Secretary of Defense among representatives of a voluntary consensus standards body that develops personnel certification standards for building maintenance or restoration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6d66950e2ab84e9fa9aeba50fe7d59e9"><enum>(J)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Chair of the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate who is not described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D) and is not a representative of an organization specified in subparagraph (E), (F), (G), (H), or (I).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0d9de461bded443cb2de97c05eae9475"><enum>(K)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Ranking Member of the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate who is not described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D) and is not a representative of an organization specified in subparagraph (E), (F), (G), (H), or (I).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7e98242d18e7491bafe8a8a22c90139f"><enum>(L)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Chair of the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives who is not described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D) and is not a representative of an organization specified in subparagraph (E), (F), (G), (H), or (I).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ebaca3dae1d400bb7236b9b42354328"><enum>(M)</enum><text>One individual appointed by the Ranking Member of the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives who is not described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D) and is not a representative of an organization specified in subparagraph (E), (F), (G), (H), or (I).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfc2268331cff40f6a5d7db13496f557f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>The term on the Council of the members specified under subparagraphs (B) through (M) of paragraph (1) shall be two years and may be renewed by the Secretary of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id603697a25a2a4c0fa51dcdcdc145805b"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Attendance by landlords</header><text>The chair of the Council shall extend an invitation to each landlord for one representative of each landlord to attend such meetings of the Council as the chair considers appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idddaeb8e3bdfc4ba99bafbbd35eabb209"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Additional requirements for certain members</header><text>Each member appointed under paragraph (1)(D) may not be affiliated with—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide651c7c738124812a18d6a87fcf993a5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any organization that provides privatized military housing; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5d22369fb1d64af7979c22b64c1a19e0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Department of Defense.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id49e25d1ed8914972a0accfaef4899171"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Council shall meet two times each year.</text></subsection><subsection id="idd55c31e7be9e49939bae159425e841f5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The duties of the Council shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="id68a4d9ca9094461ca41c377f0e0c46df"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To review and make recommendations to the Secretary of Defense regarding policies for privatized military housing, including inspections practices, resident surveys, landlord payment of medical bills for residents of housing units that have not maintained minimum standards of habitability, and access to maintenance work order systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddd416f83324642de9a977c5dde035eea"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To monitor compliance by the Department of Defense with and effective implementation by the Department of statutory and regulatory improvements to policies for privatized military housing, including the Military Housing Privatization Initiative Tenant Bill of Rights developed under section 2890 of this title and the complaint database established under section 2894a of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idae46bdc696ce40328e22703533d7e2cb"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To make recommendations to the Secretary of Defense to improve collaboration, awareness, and promotion of accurate and timely information about privatized military housing, accommodations available through the Exceptional Family Member Program of the Department, and other support services among policymakers, providers of such accommodations and other support services, and targeted beneficiaries of such accommodations and other support services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0ffe8d23bb5945008629db6f74577110"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public reporting</header><paragraph id="idef37d0ed20af46718ad4a80d74dc643e"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Availability of documents</header><text>Subject to section 552 of title 5 (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>), the records, reports, transcripts, minutes, appendices, working papers, drafts, studies, agenda, and other documents made available to or prepared for or by the Council shall be available for public inspection and copying at a single location in a publicly accessible format on a website of the Department of Defense until the Council ceases to exist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id77732822d4b84962b14b6d459ea69d21"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minutes</header><subparagraph id="id7807fe04e76b476f9459fce0e8fb7995"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Detailed minutes of each meeting of the Council shall be kept and shall contain—</text><clause id="id082fb8574ae14c5f88ef60fc0d107686"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a record of the individuals present;</text></clause><clause id="id126930959f784722b5a0c3671ef2fb6f"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a complete and accurate description of matters discussed and conclusions reached; and</text></clause><clause id="id1a06df9455f047c2ab6e1269cd6808ed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>copies of all reports received, issued, or approved by the Council.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id17e0db74541a45028e66b874dda278c0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>The chair of the Council shall certify the accuracy of the minutes of each meeting of the Council.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0755cdfdcbcc4075925526c4ce2164c9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><paragraph id="id0f18e17ff51d4209a94adea8f5a1e5f3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than March 1 each year, the Council shall submit to the Secretary of Defense and the congressional defense committees a report on privatized military housing readiness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id182c72bca73847a5b21bd2cba5cd3eea"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report under this subsection shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="idda63a3be9eac4ed68676b213bc5581e3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An assessment of the adequacy and effectiveness of the provision of privatized military housing and the activities of the Department of Defense in meeting the needs of military families relating to housing during the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbfe0c452aea948c8b936ca9d6bbd9a10"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of activities of the Council during the preceding fiscal year, including—</text><clause id="id8cc261d399774578bf0e9931ceb99cc0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>analyses of complaints of tenants of housing units;</text></clause><clause id="id4fd134dfc5104487bd5620d129a4420d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>data received by the Council on maintenance response time and completion of maintenance requests relating to housing units;</text></clause><clause id="id2c82a8eaefaa4a66a36bafd41db21857"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>assessments of dispute resolution processes;</text></clause><clause id="idfc6075cddc0046d59d360ee092a8f2af"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>assessments of overall customer service for tenants;</text></clause><clause id="idbd405784594e49c19adbb18ef70bb0be"><enum>(v)</enum><text>assessments of results of housing inspections conducted with and without notice; and</text></clause><clause id="id1d55faef5e9e49fb9a0f9002e02f2090"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any survey results conducted on behalf of or received by the Council.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida67fc3a8f30040f3b8a67870dcab8e4f"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Recommendations on actions to be taken to improve the capability of the provision of privatized military housing and the activities of the Department of Defense to meet the needs and requirements of military families relating to housing, including actions relating to the allocation of funding and other resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5b1a10f35d43459ba4ab721ab41159df"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Each report under this subsection shall be made available in a publicly accessible format on a website of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf2272fa597694681ab0bb55a2cd4a4c2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="idc53d54950a344fc8baead9b5380f1ea6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Landlord</header><text>The term <term>landlord</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2871 of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idba6963d200a44d64b19033d89a0584b2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privatized military housing</header><text>The term <term>privatized military housing</term> means housing provided under subchapter IV of chapter 169 of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id3be9a3438928469aaecdf580045473e1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such subchapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1781c the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idF32C1B7F7F1948D89B457B56872DDF0A"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">1781d. Department of Defense Military Housing Readiness Council.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

