<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MCG23097-78N-HV-L01"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S464 IS: No Tax Subsidies for E-Cigarette and Tobacco Ads Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 464</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230216">February 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S324">Mrs. Shaheen</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S341">Mr. Blumenthal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S307">Mr. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S322">Mr. Merkley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S259">Mr. Reed</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S253">Mr. Durbin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFI00">Committee on Finance</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to deny the deduction for advertising and promotional expenses for tobacco products and electronic nicotine delivery systems.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="id37CE245E2A144B88BD32FA3DFC811730"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Tax Subsidies for E-Cigarette and Tobacco Ads Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id8D9B72D3E5164AE5BEEFA68C42A4BA1F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disallowance of deduction for advertising and promotional expenses for tobacco products and electronic nicotine delivery systems</header><subsection id="idEFBA57D965B141029623D6D9F280E653"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part IX of subchapter B of chapter 1 of subtitle A of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idA6E277D0E4B04608BF9C9EE7DFD915DB"><section id="id0D3C6EDA0156494885B148661B88E5BC"><enum>280I.<?LEXA-Enum 280I.?></enum><header>Disallowance of deduction for direct-to-consumer advertising of tobacco products and electronic nicotine delivery systems</header><subsection id="idB9B6541BE875449A9D30E009479D3F2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No deduction shall be allowed under this chapter for expenses relating to direct-to-consumer advertising of tobacco products (including electronic nicotine delivery systems) for any taxable year.</text></subsection><subsection id="id7B678130CD764750BAA78A9F1F16314B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Direct-to-Consumer advertising</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>direct-to-consumer advertising</term> means any dissemination, by or on behalf of a sponsor of a tobacco product (including an electronic nicotine delivery system product), of an advertisement which—</text><paragraph id="idA8D1E73D83BB4837B523F0C2DFB50D03"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is in regard to such tobacco product (including an electronic nicotine delivery systems product), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idE0D9BC713EA447F5B5D3FBC39553FB41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is primarily targeted to the general public, including through—</text><subparagraph id="id476CCE12AE944F858E5BD7EB8C949E92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publication in journals, magazines, other periodicals, and newspapers,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id03A8A5F0105843999F0C06FBD5F67675"><enum>(B)</enum><text>broadcasting through media such as radio, television, and telephone communication systems, direct mail, and billboards, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8720001706FE4590B451EBF973E63631"><enum>(C)</enum><text>dissemination on the internet or through digital platforms (including social media, mobile media, web applications, digital applications, mobile applications, and electronic applications).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idF1E21E0D724E4E8DB8BE15509FEE4728"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tobacco product</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>tobacco product</term> means any product described in section 201(rr) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321(rr)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="idED71C26DEFF945EEA6F47C4567447B88"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Electronic nicotine delivery system</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>electronic nicotine delivery system</term>—</text><paragraph id="idb133191652774d53ae537eee888c48a9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means any electronic device that delivers nicotine, flavor, or another substance via an aerosolized solution to the user inhaling from the device (including e-cigarettes, e-hookah, e-cigars, vape pens, advanced refillable personal vaporizers, and electronic pipes) and any component, liquid, part, or accessory of such a device, whether or not sold separately, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id71a7d4ddaa024fef87997017566ce109"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not include a product that—</text><subparagraph id="id96c0a94d08fd411ea50da8abd46feacf"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is approved by the Food and Drug Administration for sale as a tobacco cessation product or for another therapeutic purpose, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id40ae22eab2e34e40bce089c5b9f8c991"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is marketed and sold solely for a purpose described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id8449FEC2D4DD43199B6939F268C7BF0B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for such part IX of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding after the item relating to section 280H the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="id2fa9a907-1420-4ec7-a6b9-dc916f078872"><toc><toc-entry idref="id0D3C6EDA0156494885B148661B88E5BC" level="section">Sec. 280I. Disallowance of deduction for direct-to-consumer advertising of tobacco products and electronic nicotine delivery systems.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id5989EA6032C74C01A77FBE2109F3B5E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred after the date of the enactment of this Act, in taxable years ending after such date.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

