<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-HEN23326-ML9-JL-16X"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1401 IS: Federal Prison Oversight Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1401</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230502">May 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S414">Mr. Ossoff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S397">Mr. Braun</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S253">Mr. Durbin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To establish an inspections regime for the Bureau of Prisons, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Prison Oversight Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id2ce0a4ab8b9541c2aa5e5f85e1ac434a"><enum>2.</enum><header>Creation of an inspections regime for the Bureau of Prisons</header><subsection id="id46ea48fc3c40450d81f1b4c92c213b4d"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 413 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8de7b4a609e74af8b9a371cda5d6c3d8"><subsection id="id1a7c1e70049c4a76b6f2344e90acea91"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inspections regime</header><paragraph id="id4a57d5e6aa8a4befaebc7329ab74e208"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="id118bfc2fe89e4b1ebccca99a554570e2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Bureau</header><text>The term <term>Bureau</term> means the Bureau of Prisons.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1b5ee4bdbdcd4dc7b73a2355d4294181"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered facility</header><text>The term <term>covered facility</term>—</text><clause id="id2D003C25106B4CCEA4EDD190D220A650"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means a correctional facility operated by the Bureau; and</text></clause><clause id="id0EFF3C5F9B5D45E4BAFA99D2F05FFC28"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not include a State, local, Tribal, or territorial facility.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id853e1bfcd0474a17a3ec096ce7e7432a"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Family member</header><text>The term <term>family member</term> includes a grandparent, parent, sibling, spouse or domestic partner, child, aunt, uncle, cousin, niece, nephew, grandchild, or any other person related to an individual by blood, adoption, marriage, civil union, or a romantic or fostering relationship.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id96113CC6616E496286A7C060181ABC14"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Inspector General</header><text>The term <term>Inspector General</term> means the Inspector General of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1f49247bb02346e28ddc681d126d7f18"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Ombudsman</header><text>The term <term>Ombudsman</term> means the Ombudsman established under paragraph (3)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida1b5a25c3e37466faf65390d8e07e8cb"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Representative of an incarcerated person</header><text>The term <term>representative of an incarcerated person</term> includes paid or unpaid legal counsel or any other person or entity chosen by an incarcerated person to represent the interests of the incarcerated person.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id895ffaa25a3648dcadbf5b417d9ad99b"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Sexual abuse</header><text>The term <term>sexual abuse</term> has the meaning given that term in section 115.6 of title 28, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor thereto).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4baacb93852940a6a0ef82dcfa453acf"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The term <term>staff</term> means employees and contractors of the Bureau.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id29A91C8597F740B68A4601FF97F1FC67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inspections of covered facilities by the Inspector General</header><subparagraph id="idC24C16181CFC4BB5B70EE72FFB987BC2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment of inspections regime</header><clause id="idF59E8259631E4C6398C227F5D036FA5E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Inspector General shall conduct periodic inspections of covered facilities pursuant to the requirements of this subsection. </text></clause><clause id="id7373B69F6D9B4368971D2ECCEABAF248"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Access to covered facilities</header><text>The Attorney General shall ensure that the Inspector General has access to any covered facility, including the incarcerated people, detainees, staff, bargaining unit representative organization, and any other information that the Inspector General determines is necessary to carry out the provisions of this subsection.</text></clause><clause id="id47453F51F50B44F29BC8C7BFBE3097AC"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Notice of inspections</header><text>An inspection of a covered facility under this subsection may be announced or unannounced.</text></clause><clause id="id48aaa94bd5004fa4a5eabe1f4aed767f"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Community input</header><text>In developing the inspections regime under this subsection, the Inspector General is encouraged to consult formerly incarcerated people, family or representatives of incarcerated people, and community advocates. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id54a9ded99b024233b851486f34f925dd"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inspection criteria</header><text>An inspection of a covered facility under this subsection may include an assessment of the following:</text><clause id="idbf33d7b63be04db4a7a10341b2d21174"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The policies, procedures, and administrative guidance of the facility.</text></clause><clause id="idd23a8406036448cfa71187499106f528"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The conditions of confinement.</text></clause><clause id="idb1d4d26f55384610973d164f9fe71051"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Working conditions for staff.</text></clause><clause id="idac93fcf9587542358cc0f79d536fc3a4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The availability of evidence-based recidivism reduction programs and productive activities, as such terms are defined in section 3635 of title 18, and the application of earned time credits pursuant to section 3632 of title 18.</text></clause><clause id="id07a3ba6039a74642ae2dfc0b4a0bb618"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The policies and procedures relating to visitation.</text></clause><clause id="id4be59032938842d9a7f609941ccb031a"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The policies and practices relating to classification and housing.</text></clause><clause id="id3232e9bb97014fdf8dfff7055e8810a7"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The policies and practices relating to the use of single-cell confinement, administrative segregation, and other forms of restrictive housing.</text></clause><clause id="id80af1f22e7de44d8853323dac4a4de01"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The medical facilities and medical and mental health care, programs, procedures, and policies, including the number and qualifications of medical and mental health staff and the availability of gender-appropriate and trauma-responsive care for incarcerated people.</text></clause><clause id="id1ebbafb5c3614801b11213c2d8ce8d9c"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Medical services and mental health resources for staff.</text></clause><clause id="id955878444a6e43c694a8127191e060c0"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Lockdowns at the facility.</text></clause><clause id="id62c5b7e1397d41fbad50b37419323759"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Credible allegations of incidents involving excessive use of force, completed, attempted, or threatened violence, including sexual abuse, or misconduct committed against incarcerated people.</text></clause><clause id="id210650d0ea2a4c97b7b525f06c82c2c6"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Credible allegations of incidents involving completed, attempted, or threatened violence, including sexual violence or sexual abuse, committed against staff.</text></clause><clause id="id3743e1d3cb834009a35c552e9bbdecc0"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Adequacy of staffing at the covered facility, including the number and job assignments of staff, the ratio of staff to inmates at the facility, the staff position vacancy rate at the facility, and the use of overtime, mandatory overtime, and augmentation.</text></clause><clause id="idfeb3da4dec294cc59e27901bfd53510b"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>Deaths or serious injuries of incarcerated people or staff that occurred at the facility.</text></clause><clause id="ida563d768f9cb4e67bdeb413bad04994e"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>The existence of contraband that jeopardizes the health or safety of incarcerated people or staff, including incident reports, referrals for criminal prosecution, and confirmed prosecutions.</text></clause><clause id="idb18429e7ccaa43589d82f12b507f745b"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>Access of incarcerated people to—</text><subclause id="id4BE18237976744B5909D5A2C65ACEA55"><enum>(I)</enum><text>legal counsel, including confidential meetings and communications;</text></subclause><subclause id="idD8666563946049DCA55FA472AF27F3BB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>discovery and other case-related legal materials; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idA4DEDAF41FBC42A3804516E0224A85D8"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the law library at the covered facility.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id8dc0d2a8d6f743a19e036567a03f98e2"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>Any aspect of the operation of the covered facility that the Inspector General determines to be necessary over the course of an inspection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3558d4b2e787483e9ea1f583fedadd7f"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inspection schedule</header><text>An inspection of a covered facility under this subsection shall be conducted on a schedule based on the combined risk score of the covered facility as described in subparagraph (E) and the following considerations:</text><clause id="id0a92653b769b4da0a47a0b6b84501ecf"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Higher risk facilities shall receive more frequent inspections.</text></clause><clause id="id78e3bc468b454dccbad54048429253e1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Inspector General shall reevaluate the combined risk score methodology and inspection schedule periodically and may alter 1 or both to ensure that higher risk facilities are identified and receiving the appropriate frequency of inspection.</text></clause><clause id="id71a41de432524fe6a7ad233a4ab1c32a"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A determination by the Inspector General that 1 or more of the criteria listed in subparagraph (B) should be inspected, with regard to a covered facility or group of covered facilities. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb27589be1a6943298c8e8affb7c038ba"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Report</header><clause id="id7EB4BC05FCF24A7283BF4A5CD95D24C2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon completion of an inspection of a covered facility under this subsection, or a group of inspections that assess the same or similar issues at more than 1 facility, the Inspector General shall produce a report to be made available to the Attorney General, the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate, the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives, employee representative organizations, and the public, that addresses 1 or more of the following topics:</text><subclause id="id123025f3bd0e4770bef08a42ff3b21b6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>A characterization of the conditions of confinement and working conditions, including a summary of the inspection criteria reviewed under clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (B).</text></subclause><subclause id="ida8145be34d73415b907169491a026802"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Recommendations made to the covered facility to improve safety and conditions within the facility, including recommendations regarding staffing.</text></subclause><subclause id="id3c37ba1e484a4ee78faeb39528a083da"><enum>(III)</enum><text>A recommended timeline for the next inspection and assessment, which shall not limit the authority of the Inspector General to perform additional inspections and assessments, announced or unannounced.</text></subclause><subclause id="idda2c0642ed134aa8a49a9f73eedc59b2"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Any other issues or matters identified during the inspection of the facility or facilities.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idD94A3356E3C04B40BC6690C8B173000D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Consultation with stakeholders</header><text>In developing the recommendations described in clause (i), the Inspector General may consult with stakeholders, including employee representative organizations. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbac44724df504733ab512a6fd987f85e"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Risk score</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Federal Prison Oversight Act</short-title>, the Inspector General shall establish methodology and protocols for determining the combined risk score of a covered facility, which—</text><clause commented="no" id="id37D41D57C1CB4CAFA077B1E41160F13D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be delivered to the <committee-name committee-id="SSJU00">Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and</text></clause><clause id="idB880E04F125B42558BD0FA284F779823"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may be based on—</text><subclause id="id3fc2db0ff7274b3997675e92fdc5c143"><enum>(I)</enum><text>frequency and duration of lockdowns;</text></subclause><subclause id="id1ebe794a972f408fb41a46b1a881d179"><enum>(II)</enum><text>availability of programming;</text></subclause><subclause id="id55e76e29e460479fa9bf213e9dac5cfe"><enum>(III)</enum><text>staffing levels;</text></subclause><subclause id="id29246c6d085c434da970f005e9f9eeac"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>access to adequate physical and mental health resources;</text></subclause><subclause id="id6d8da7f947f3484187697e9827bec5e7"><enum>(V)</enum><text>incidences of physical assault, neglect, or sexual abuse;</text></subclause><subclause id="id16894e072f9b4d08a591fed2355610a7"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>opportunity to maintain family ties through phone calls, video calls, mail, email, and visitation;</text></subclause><subclause id="id37bc6f7c548344088722a8f9cce9ca2f"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>adequacy of the nutrition provided;</text></subclause><subclause id="idacc3c0aa2d6a4c01bffc047abc0f79de"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>amount or frequency of staff discipline cases;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide585fca0fcea4016b76afaab5797d002"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>amount or frequency of misconduct by people incarcerated at the covered facility; </text></subclause><subclause id="idC225AD237D584EA1981878E273FBDDE1"><enum>(X)</enum><text>access of incarcerated people to—</text><item id="id21066443BEB94A5897056755BA25039D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>legal counsel, including confidential meetings and communications;</text></item><item id="idEC94A6FFCA0B401A875EFD2C4845A2F7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>discovery and other case-related legal materials; and</text></item><item id="idE66007F06AA24FD682AD49F373266F23"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the law library at the covered facility; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="idb15956a49eae465fb1270e6915fed3c9"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>other factors as determined by the Inspector General.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide40213b2d0464ef3b7384affaa227bd0"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Bureau response to report</header><clause id="idfef420fa775f4c6dabfe54ac0331ed74"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which the Inspector General issues a report under subparagraph (D), the Bureau shall respond in writing to the inspection report, which shall include a corrective action plan. </text></clause><clause id="id6C0C181654B848568762549327F37BED"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Each response and action plan described in clause (i) shall be made available to the public on the website of the Inspector General.</text></clause><clause id="idd4ba55946eeb4096811c93b5a3cf8a8e"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Compliance with corrective action plan</header><text>The Inspector General may conduct additional inspections or investigations, announced or unannounced, to monitor the compliance of the Bureau with a corrective action plan described in clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5a3321027d074131ae189c57872a2756"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The authority in this paragraph is consistent with and does not supersede, conflict with, or otherwise alter the authority provided to the Inspector General under section 406. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb44291a3076046b1887908852ed3a8c0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ombudsman</header><subparagraph id="id811f5ed13dfe4b058feaa3fbf599001b"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Federal Prison Oversight Act</short-title>, the Attorney General shall establish in the Department of Justice an Ombudsman who may—</text><clause id="id3970aadcc7cb427f8b4fa64c351eb9dd"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receive a complaint from an incarcerated person, a family member, a representative of an incarcerated person, staff, or others regarding issues that may adversely affect the health, safety, welfare, or rights of incarcerated people or staff, including—</text><subclause id="idce50f45cea774081a7410663ef15ea90"><enum>(I)</enum><text>abuse or neglect;</text></subclause><subclause id="idc6e956c02b5747f4b6dfb7e3c462d87d"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the conditions of confinement, including the availability of health care;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide67df943d5894c5a943171473b6dcf30"><enum>(III)</enum><text>working conditions of staff;</text></subclause><subclause id="id7c0ea19bf7e64d2d89f46154460f5b1f"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>decisions, administrative actions, or guidance of the Bureau, including those relating to prison staffing;</text></subclause><subclause id="id51a7bfd12477453eaf32fd27801f2001"><enum>(V)</enum><text>inaction or omissions by the Bureau, including failure to consider or respond to complaints or grievances by incarcerated people or staff promptly or appropriately;</text></subclause><subclause id="ida84755a0bd3d439ebbf50e383138ef73"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>policies, rules, or procedures of the Bureau, including gross mismanagement; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id2edc86683c7d49e1bfe99ea4e9a128ee"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>alleged violations of non-criminal law by staff or incarcerated people that may adversely affect the health, safety, welfare, or rights of any person;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idae8efafb7eeb423989d4749a958760f0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>refer a complainant and others to appropriate resources or Federal agencies;</text></clause><clause id="id6e61448b7ae24a829b4e93623842ecdb"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>make inquiries and recommend actions to appropriate entities on behalf of a complainant, the Ombudsman, or others; and</text></clause><clause id="ideae0936a4b0f48bd97c136091aa427fa"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>decline to investigate or take any action with respect to any complaint and, in any case in which the Ombudsman declines to investigate or take any action, shall notify the complainant in writing of the decision not to investigate or take any action and the reasons for the decision.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5428c0540e5d409794f4e5efd8e6579a"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitations on authority</header><text>The Ombudsman—</text><clause id="idf431ac9ce00746349946dc625a0b3ce3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may not investigate—</text><subclause id="idb15cfb439587474e94066e234142b146"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any complaints relating to the underlying criminal conviction of an incarcerated person;</text></subclause><subclause id="id576a20942cbb4b12ab9dec91a3ff7673"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a complaint from staff that relates to the employment or contractual relationship of the staff member with the Bureau, unless the complaint is related to the health, safety, welfare, working conditions, gross mismanagement of a covered facility, or rehabilitation of incarcerated people; or</text></subclause><subclause id="idb2eb9de8eff84b86b2e4ad949ce33676"><enum>(III)</enum><text>any allegation of criminal or administrative misconduct, as described in subsection (b)(2), and shall refer any matter covered by subsection (b)(2) to the Inspector General, who may, at the discretion of Inspector General, refer such allegations back to the Ombudsman or the internal affairs office of the appropriate component of the Department of Justice; and </text></subclause></clause><clause id="idae632a4351b24ea1a9f6eef7bc4731f1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may not levy any fees for the submission or investigation of complaints.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf1e2c6c216fb4730bf5cffbaa5bc9d8e"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Decision on the merits of a complaint</header><text>At the conclusion of an investigation of a complaint, the Ombudsman shall—</text><clause id="id63bdf8b6c4ae4878ae6644df43dc22eb"><enum>(i)</enum><text>render a decision on the merits of each complaint;</text></clause><clause id="idf112d16557c546fa98dbae2233723971"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>communicate the decision to the complainant, if any, and to the Bureau; and</text></clause><clause id="id44351cf1f9da4f7fb6a838103c59b45e"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>state the recommendations and reasoning of the Ombudsman if, in the opinion of the Ombudsman, the Bureau or any employee thereof should—</text><subclause id="iddf22e187502943beb8f29e34f8b2351c"><enum>(I)</enum><text>consider the matter further;</text></subclause><subclause id="id04f11b18656047d68f137daec7593194"><enum>(II)</enum><text>modify or cancel any action;</text></subclause><subclause id="idf4b5ff280c564338a90132e20be42e13"><enum>(III)</enum><text>alter a rule, practice, or ruling;</text></subclause><subclause id="id010b25a4ea244f42a5568e3abe7ade9f"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>explain in detail the administrative action in question; or</text></subclause><subclause id="id775e17d70470441d8c7bffda1ae4b6d8"><enum>(V)</enum><text>rectify an omission.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id40fe55f63fcb43618f56ac8f1a4f1026"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Actions following a decision by the ombudsman</header><clause id="id03267a5fbb6548329e58956387fabb22"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Request for information about actions taken</header><text>If the Ombudsman so requests, the Bureau shall, within the time specified, respond to any inquiry or request for information from the Ombudsman and inform the Ombudsman about any action taken on the recommendations provided by the Ombudsman or the reasons for not complying with any request for information or recommendations.</text></clause><clause id="id6452cc6d8eac4a0a850713297ab76396"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Reporting of continuing issues</header><text>If the Ombudsman believes, based on an investigation conducted by the Ombudsman, that there has been or continues to be a significant health, safety, welfare, working conditions, or rehabilitation issue, the Ombudsman shall report the finding to the Attorney General, the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></clause><clause id="idc09fa89d87d74b1482c8dda09d43b5b6"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Monitoring of internal disciplinary actions of the bureau</header><text>In the event that the Bureau conducts an internal disciplinary investigation or review of 1 or more staff members of the Bureau as a result of an investigation by the Ombudsman, the Ombudsman may monitor the internal disciplinary action to ensure a fair and objective process.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id6b15169725ff48d486949120e0f66fe2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Inspector General and Ombudsman access to Bureau of Prisons facilities</header><subparagraph id="id6c43c877f4114c3e8136a77b540c7df6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon demand, in person or in writing and with or without prior notice, the Inspector General and the Ombudsman shall be granted access to all Bureau facilities, which shall include—</text><clause id="id41f1bb32158d45f8b799b04b98084981"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all areas that are used by incarcerated people, all areas that are accessible to incarcerated people, and access to programs for incarcerated people at any time of day; and</text></clause><clause id="id147167501b0e4dccbc2eb22d1a03055d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the opportunity to—</text><subclause id="idf095647d18f249a6a6542cf5ecf4329b"><enum>(I)</enum><text>conduct private and confidential interviews with any incarcerated person, staff, employee representative organization, or other person; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id9a9c7a5a3ae74ce5b56ac706b65ae553"><enum>(II)</enum><text>communicate privately and confidentially, both formally and informally, with incarcerated people or staff by telephone, mail, electronic communication, and in person, which shall not be monitored or recorded by or conducted in the presence of staff.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8ca1263ffa1d44fb9feaf3d33620153c"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Purpose of visits</header><text>Access to Bureau facilities under subparagraph (A) is for the purposes of—</text><clause id="id9346073a2a9e40ef8f7b7f4fcb4809e3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conducting announced or unannounced inspections by the Inspector General as described in paragraph (2), including inspections to monitor the compliance of the Bureau with a corrective action plan described in paragraph (2)(F)(i);</text></clause><clause id="idfdd7324aa8304f438bb42ca7243e9598"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conducting an investigation or other activity by the Ombudsman as described in paragraph (3); and</text></clause><clause id="id21c0dfd7c946442a881206ca49816e86"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>inspecting, viewing, photographing, and video recording all areas of the facility that are used by incarcerated people or are accessible to incarcerated people.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id142aa0a014fd4931b7ecfd8f95ed9c03"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Access to documents</header><clause id="id7f6258169ed64c9595045bf1912f4553"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Inspector General and the Ombudsman have the right to access, inspect, and copy all relevant information, records, or documents in the possession or control of the Bureau that either the Inspector General or the Ombudsman considers necessary in an inspection, investigation, or other activity, and the Bureau shall assist the Inspector General and the Ombudsman in obtaining the necessary releases for those documents that are specifically restricted or privileged for use by the Bureau.</text></clause><clause id="iddb5d942d80da41939acff3825efe146c"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Production of records</header><text>Following notification from the Inspector General or the Ombudsman with a written demand for access to Bureau records, the Bureau shall provide access to the requested documentation in a manner consistent with section 552a (commonly known as the <quote>Privacy Act of 1974</quote>)—</text><subclause id="id5486dbaf4a7a4a63bbace69629473e07"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not later than 20 business days after receipt of the written request; or</text></subclause><subclause id="iddddec4be0ba54d38b7a6786515543bdc"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of records pertaining to the death of an incarcerated person or staff, threats of bodily harm including sexual or physical assaults, or the denial or delay of necessary medical treatment, not later than 5 business days after receipt of the written request, unless the Inspector General or the Ombudsman consents to an extension of that time frame.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id13c21067413a4a97ae1aeca38780d03b"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Minimize disruption of operations</header><text>The Inspector General and the Ombudsman shall—</text><clause id="id500e671cf13c47a39feb5e4f296e941b"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop procedures— </text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide10618c420e3426bb45b137d05f9b0d2"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to ensure that the Inspector General has access to, and the right to review and investigate, any allegations received by the Ombudsman to ensure that the Inspector General may carry out the authorities provided to the Inspector General under this chapter; and </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4009ac0c76354ca4a1defea894dfcc7c"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that may provide that the Inspector General and the Ombudsman will determine certain categories of allegations that are not necessary for the Inspector General to review prior to the Ombudsman proceeding; </text></subclause></clause><clause id="id1743cd65de35426db41cb414d41398a9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>work with the Bureau to minimize disruption to the operations of the Bureau due to inspections, investigations, or other activity; </text></clause><clause id="id1525799d3d494b8fb8e6f92b79cde640"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>comply with the security clearance processes of the Bureau, provided these processes do not impede the activities described in this subsection; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfd2742d3eea846838973772b00daac53"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>limit the public release of any photographs or video recordings that would jeopardize— </text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id406aaccf527a4c0b87c4a05ef7acd857"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the safety, security, or good order of a covered facility or the Bureau; or </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id804e1f2b577646a38c11d54e7e280e87"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">public safety. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id548003701fc046968c4a321a90830a55"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The authority in this paragraph is consistent with and does not supersede, conflict with, or otherwise alter the authority provided to the Inspector General under section 406. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida6a995c4c5914a3fa96fd7f5bc8e3c6c"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><subparagraph id="id5ec37959f2234bf7847140105cccd73a"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Correspondence and communication with the Inspector General and the Ombudsman, including communication regarding an issue described in section 4051 of title 18 is confidential and shall be protected as privileged correspondence in the same manner as legal correspondence or communications.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id60cf9bddc16849ce8333e0003909abd8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), the Inspector General and the Ombudsman shall establish confidentiality procedures for all information maintained by the respective office to ensure that, to the greatest extent practicable, before, during, or after an investigation—</text><clause id="id5c4d4b45b4a24aa5a766482dea613ee2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>staff are not aware of the identity of a complainant; and</text></clause><clause id="id0056d24c4c484519b8dbd750aca5e6c6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other incarcerated people are not aware of the identity of a complainant.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1a9f1390bd7d4ad281281c6c6674a828"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Inspector General and the Ombudsman may disclose identifying information for the sole purpose of carrying out an investigation and as otherwise authorized under section 407(b). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id53ea1adebfba4dbeb43dce92850e6b11"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Filing complaints</header><subparagraph id="id3967a4abeda44ce0841ad331665d83a8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Filing complaints on behalf of an incarcerated individual</header><clause id="idf70064347c1b40ae81030d0bbeefcba3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Online form</header><text>The Ombudsman shall create a secure online form to be made available on the website of the Ombudsman where the family members, friends, and representatives of incarcerated people can submit complaints and inquiries on issues identified in paragraph (3)(A)(i) on behalf of an individual incarcerated at a covered facility.</text></clause><clause id="id1b940f9f943148baaf860d840b582480"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Telephone hotline</header><text>The Ombudsman shall create a telephone hotline through which family members, friends, and representatives of incarcerated people can call to file complaints and inquiries on issues identified in paragraph (3)(A)(i) on behalf of an individual incarcerated at a covered facility.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7e5044e110fc43b3a99581f1b68c83cc"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Filing complaints by an incarcerated individual</header><clause id="id817ade7e64d04cb39d731e3ffb431acd"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Internal private submission</header><text>The Bureau shall provide multiple internal ways for incarcerated individuals in covered facilities to privately submit to the Ombudsman complaints and inquiries on issues identified in paragraph (3)(A)(i).</text></clause><clause id="idc235b2d0da9d40229ecd58c06d52c5a8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Submission via independent entity</header><text>The Bureau shall also provide not less than 1 process for incarcerated individuals in covered facilities to submit complaints and inquiries on issues identified in paragraph (3)(A)(i) to a public or private entity or office that is not part of the Bureau and that is able to receive and immediately forward complaints and inquiries to the Ombudsman, allowing the incarcerated individual to remain anonymous upon request.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idced70ebec052418e8c8f1747bcc8ed6e"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Determination</header><clause id="ide3bfb4ab23fe4438b293ebcf623d19c1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Confirmation of receipt</header><text>Not later than 5 business days after submission of a complaint or inquiry under subparagraph (A) or (B), the Ombudsman shall confirm receipt.</text></clause><clause id="idb02859b5cacd4700b358bcad7271476d"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>Not later than 15 business days after issuing the confirmation under clause (i), the Ombudsman shall make a determination as to whether any action is warranted and notify the complainant of the determination.</text></clause><clause id="id855c12b6081b49bb8371fc38ee00cce8"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Statement regarding decision</header><text>If the Ombudsman has determined action is unwarranted under clause (ii), the Ombudsman shall provide a written statement explaining the decision to the complainant.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddade3571fade49928ce765343b1c59ed"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Public education</header><text>The Ombudsman shall coordinate with the Bureau to educate incarcerated people, representatives of incarcerated people, and the public about the existence and functions of the Ombudsman. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id810af3b404bd425485aebc014eaa3f76" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Administrative exhaustion</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed as a necessary administrative remedy required for exhaustion under section 7(a) of the Civil Rights of Institutionalized Persons Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1997e">42 U.S.C. 1997e(a)</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id63b9995cfbe74a1a8bc1eb449d1be2b2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Prohibition on retaliation</header><subparagraph id="idf236e632c70144089b42b59c3d88e059"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Bureau and staff of the Bureau shall not discharge, retaliate against, or in any manner discriminate against any complainant or any person or entity that has instituted or caused to be instituted any proceeding, investigation, or inspection under or related to this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id74f9e4b02e1d435eb414699625684cf5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Investigation</header><text>Any alleged discharge of, retaliation against, or discrimination against a complainant, entity, or person because of a complaint, investigation, or inspection may be considered by the Ombudsman as an appropriate subject of an investigation or other activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7aa027ad0bf1448aa8bc4a94e6ba7c40"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Due process protections</header><subparagraph id="idAE75684F33DD44FE999BA3388E9D9753"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General and the Inspector General shall ensure that implementation of this subsection is consistent with section 552a (commonly known as the <quote>Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) and all other applicable laws, and respects appropriate due process protections for staff.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id165239C5FD2D4CD79D89CDAB4F63A736"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to modify, supersede, or otherwise affect the authority of the Inspector General to access all records, reports, audits, reviews, documents, papers, recommendations, or other materials, as authorized by section 406(a). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idca65bee0f3964e078b7cee5018a620ce"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Percentage of annual appropriation for the bureau of prisons</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the amount allocated to the Inspector General and the Ombudsman to carry out the activities described in this subsection should equal an amount between 0.2 percent and 0.5 percent of the annual appropriation for the Bureau.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="idCE241BA17FFC42C99CAF5A2CCAA0305C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text>This Act, and the amendments made by this Act, shall take effect on the date that is 90 days after the date on which appropriations are made available to the Inspector General of the Department of Justice and the Department of Justice for the specific purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

