<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-DAV23172-V8S-2R-K9C"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S435 IS: Ensuring Military Readiness Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 435</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230215">February 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S350">Mr. Rubio</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S396">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S417">Mr. Budd</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S412">Mr. Tuberville</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S397">Mr. Braun</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To provide requirements related to the eligibility of individuals who identify as transgender from serving in the Armed Forces. </official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="id1939678E1B584A0E910BFDB653F0B50F"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Military Readiness Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="idF5E16A5B48C94074B6FF6A1A332B7293"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitations on military service by individuals who identify as transgender</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall prescribe regulations regarding service of individuals who identify as transgender as follows:</text><paragraph id="id3D4B3B6891BA479F8880099DDAFABF4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Persons who identify as transgender with a history of diagnosis of gender dysphoria are disqualified from military service except under the following limited circumstances:</text><subparagraph id="id237bb99aa6954c85b797217b2544fe39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Individuals may serve in the Armed Forces if they have been stable for 36 consecutive months in their biological sex prior to accession.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id36904eff1d0946a3aa4079d846c72374"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Members of the Armed Forces diagnosed with gender dysphoria after entering into service may be retained if they do not undergo gender transition procedures and remain deployable within applicable retention standards for their biological sex. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id743663AB01B3490F8281377DB6761735"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Members of the Armed Forces serving as of the date of the enactment of this Act who have been diagnosed with gender dysphoria may continue to serve only in their biological sex, irrespective of any changes previously made to their gender marker in the Defense Enrollment Eligibility Reporting System (DEERS), and receive medically necessary treatment for gender dysphoria. Such treatment may not include gender transition procedures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="iddb75ba48916847aaa488a715c6e01d16"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Persons who identify as transgender who seek or have undergone gender transition are disqualified from military service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id051b02ff062944b68a1f9284f94b0818"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Persons who identify as transgender without a history or diagnosis of gender dysphoria, who are otherwise qualified for service and meet all physical and mental requirements, may serve in the Armed Forces in their biological sex.</text></paragraph></section><section id="idB4EE2689F5F94B42A2DD0815FF96BAC4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Revised regulations regarding gender markings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall prescribe regulations updating the Defense Enrollment Eligibility Reporting System (DEERS) to require the gender markers for members of the Armed Forces to match their biological sex, irrespective of any previous changes allowed. </text></section><section id="id529CDCBB77B74AF8BEBCF88E11359F32"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="idE98792E37C6A4E0E9048CD4210D0B02D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cross-sex hormones</header><text>The term <term>cross-sex hormones</term> means testosterone or other androgens given to biological females at doses that are profoundly larger or more potent than would normally occur naturally in healthy biological females, or estrogen given to biological males at doses that are profoundly larger or more potent than would normally occur naturally in healthy biological males. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9039b61fd7fc417cb1d33018b27c99b0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Gender</header><text>The term <term>gender</term> means the psychological, behavioral, social, and cultural aspects of being male or female.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0c2a452de4234a81ae39461750954667" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gender dysphoria</header><text>The term <term>gender dysphoria</term> means a marked incongruence between one’s experienced or expressed gender and biological sex. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idC7B58DB4AB7348D4A5D796DB95BE92D1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Gender transition</header><text>The term <term>gender transition</term> means the process by which a person goes from identifying with and living as a gender that corresponds to his or her biological sex to identifying with and living as a gender different from his or her biological sex, and may involve social, legal, or physical changes. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id14373E9FD5C94929991BAB03DFE24E93"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Gender transition procedures</header><text>The term <term>gender transition procedures</term>—</text><subparagraph id="idA91A5840B8F7456C8E403DB1C47AB4C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text><clause id="id7B19515EA89443D8AF526C9EEDC187EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any medical or surgical intervention, including physician's services, inpatient and outpatient hospital services, or prescribed drugs related to gender transition, that seeks to alter or remove physical or anatomical characteristics or features that are typical for the individual’s biological sex or to instill or create physiological or anatomical characteristics that resemble a sex different from the individual’s birth sex, including medical services that provide puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or other mechanisms to promote the development of feminizing or masculinizing features (in the opposite sex); and</text></clause><clause id="idC2044D1A22CC45BE9DEDC2F6D2672948"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>genital or non-genital gender transition surgery performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idAD574BDC6C604641BCA9B631A243C10C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text><clause id="id4456F09D18D84A95BF5779B3A59E3D4F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>services to those born with a medically verifiable disorder of sex development, including a person with external biological sex characteristics that are irresolvably ambiguous, such as those born with 46 XX chromosomes with virilization, 46 XY chromosomes with undervirilization, or having both ovarian and testicular tissue;</text></clause><clause id="id790A11098795426E9CB7D82F5CCF5254"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>services provided when a physician has otherwise diagnosed a disorder of sexual development, in which the physician has determined through genetic or biochemical testing that the person does not have normal sex chromosome structure, sex steroid hormone production, or sex steroid hormone action for a biological male or biological female; or</text></clause><clause id="id5F4BB8ACE0144021BD68F474A159249D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the treatment of any infection, injury, disease, or disorder that has been caused by or exacerbated by the performance of gender transition procedures, whether or not the gender transition procedure was performed in accordance with State and Federal law or whether or not funding for the gender transition procedure is permissible.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4C84CD46E8854F6C8C5A556A9C04F2C6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gender transition surgery</header><text>The term <term>gender transition surgery</term> means any medical or surgical service that seeks to surgically alter or remove healthy physical or anatomical characteristics or features that are typical for the individual’s biological sex in order to instill or create physiological or anatomical characteristics that resemble a sex different from the individual’s birth sex, including genital or non-genital gender reassignment surgery performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5B0CFC6AD6EB4B479DABADD2B880922A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Genital gender transition surgery</header><text>The term <term>genital gender transition surgery</term> includes surgical procedures such as penectomy, orchiectomy, vaginoplasty, clitoroplasty, or vulvoplasty for biologically male patients or hysterectomy, ovariectomy, reconstruction of the fixed part of the urethra with or without a metoidioplasty or a phalloplasty, vaginectomy, scrotoplasty, or implantation of erection or testicular prostheses for biologically female patients, when performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id99D1469481304203BD043A92A637E6F3"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Non-genital gender transition surgery</header><text>The term <term>non-genital gender transition surgery</term>—</text><subparagraph id="id0C585C2531EA46E7A416363DA2D20CA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes, when performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition—</text><clause id="idD8A5DB80674F48CA878689ADA873CAF6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>surgical procedures such as augmentation mammoplasty, facial feminization surgery, liposuction, lipofilling, voice surgery, thyroid cartilage reduction, gluteal augmentation (implants or lipofilling), hair reconstruction, or various aesthetic procedures for biologically male patients; or</text></clause><clause id="idF6F57FE0CE4A4761B94E4DE337ACA4EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>subcutaneous mastectomy, voice surgery, liposuction, lipofilling, pectoral implants or various aesthetic procedures for biologically female patients; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id98041c23b34349bb8b3ac03705091cb3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include any procedure undertaken because the individual suffers from a physical disorder, physical injury, or physical illness that would, as certified by a physician, place the individual in imminent danger of death or impairment of major bodily function unless surgery is performed, unless the procedure is for the purpose of a gender transition. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id97D9BEECE4C248AD87A2494B50B5CB24"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Puberty-blocking drugs</header><text>The term <term>puberty-blocking drugs</term> means, when used to delay or suppress pubertal development in children for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition—</text><subparagraph id="id4598C6142ED540E2BF58C56E27EFB3D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogues or other synthetic drugs used in biological males to stop luteinizing hormone secretion and therefore testosterone secretion; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6D512E3D39924CF990F349F3375A0E5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>synthetic drugs used in biological females that stop the production of estrogen and progesterone. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4A931BA80D0D4B4C929DFB17A98B4CF1"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Sex; birth sex; biological sex</header><text>The terms <term>sex</term>, <term>birth sex,</term> and <term>biological sex</term> refer to the biological indication of male and female in the context of reproductive potential or capacity, such as sex chromosomes, naturally occurring sex hormones, gonads, and non-ambiguous internal and external genitalia present at birth, without regard to an individual’s psychological, chosen, or subjective experience of gender.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

