<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MCC23A98-194-0P-03N"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S2532 IS: To require the Secretary of Defense to submit an annual report on certain out-of-cycle or premature personnel transfers.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 2532</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S221">Mrs. Feinstein</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Defense to submit an annual report on certain out-of-cycle or premature personnel transfers.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="idb7e980b0240441f9bf5856b3f6bd6519" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Reports on certain out-of-cycle and premature personnel transfers</header><subsection id="id731f064eac054b5ca359e43e6092c31b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than December 1, 2025, and each December 1 thereafter, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees, and any other committee of Congress the Secretary considers appropriate, a report detailing the number and nature of out-of-cycle or premature personnel transfers carried out during the preceding fiscal year for individuals described in subsection (b) as a result of such individuals, or the dependents of such individuals, being affected by—</text><paragraph id="id83805f3860c444849867cccd630bbdb2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sexual assault;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1c18f442c0154cffa4f2c4b7932d82f7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>sexual harassment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id11f17b1f57dc440295bf7ca7b629ccd5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>humanitarian or compassionate requests;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6cfe748a62fb447e9489c7047b701def"><enum>(4)</enum><text>discrimination, harassment, bullying, reprisals, or threats based on the race, color, national origin, religion, sex (including gender identity), or sexual orientation of such individuals or dependents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7ce55fb0397246fc84e61857b2aeec04"><enum>(5)</enum><text>medical issues, including lack of access to care for such individuals or dependents at their current duty location; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5ac2a799cb284e669519c36dcc78e26c"><enum>(6)</enum><text>child custody arrangements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id72e093b632f34fc08a4f36735655255a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Individual described</header><text>An individual described in this subsection is an individual who is—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc50bf792dd8645e7b2ad68fc2f6792c3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Armed Forces on active duty;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd6c0b8f316714538bedbc40a954a7534"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Armed Forces in a reserve component; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc78b5bf4790a4e1f911d2f4bf350f990"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the National Guard; or </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7ac2ff2ce25d4fafa846731a08c427e8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a civilian employee of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idc0c218d158d7478e8f6359e8344ac722"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) shall include the following for the preceding fiscal year:</text><paragraph id="id21c07c18fad840af820e4e8f8d90fa76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The total number of personnel transfers for each reason described in paragraphs (1) through (6) of subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id57a25079acb44127b496b8d5eaf7e5de"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Demographic information of each individual involved in such a transfer, including the age, gender, and military rank or civilian pay grade of the individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id771f543bed214a22b7f3d8ff5c81aebe"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An analysis of the geographic distribution of such transfers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2772378e1f4f45b7a7ca1baf110d6e58"><enum>(4)</enum><text>For each such transfer, the branch or component of the Department of Defense to which the individual concerned was transferred.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida457b898bcf0486caa5279948fadc050"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of any trend or pattern identified in the data, including recurring issues or areas of concern.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5741846f26cc4bc1a1c45a75b9df48cf"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An estimate of the total cost of such transfers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6c5548f5390a4ef189137c649c5db97f"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex, as necessary to protect sensitive information.</text></subsection><subsection id="id747572f0739b4f3fadba09724ac7d70f"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text>To ensure the privacy of military personnel, personally identifiable information shall not be included in any report under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc9f460cbcbc84c92b5986da7b0736b28"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make each report required by subsection (a) available to the public on the internet website of the Department of Defense.</text></subsection><subsection id="id71262d34c22c41429c75c536915a5f0e"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="idae9673e4a5514c9b8cd48843e7f4287a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Out-of-cycle or premature</header><text>With respect to a personnel transfer, the term <term>out-of-cycle or premature</term> means an assignment action taken in advance of the originally scheduled or anticipated rotation date of the personnel concerned.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id30b7167b442e49fd93d3c6d783d578f2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Personnel transfer</header><text>The term <term>personnel transfer</term> includes a permanent change of duty station, temporary duty assignment, reassignment, permanent change of assignment, and any other movement of military personnel within the Department of Defense. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

