<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MCC23017-WTY-T9-VXR"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 S356 IS: Syria Detainee and Displaced Persons Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 356</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S324">Mrs. Shaheen</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S293">Mr. Graham</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S306">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S323">Mr. Risch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To amend the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 to modify the establishment of a coordinator for detained ISIS members and relevant displaced populations in Syria, and for other purposes. </official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Syria Detainee and Displaced Persons Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="idB1DA6A8780ED48498694EBEFDA8B462C" changed="not-changed"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of establishment of coordinator for detained ISIS members and relevant populations in Syria</header><subsection id="idFAC6084E0EC8450C86EAFD3A074C1D45" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="id75413697-3c01-4d2b-9d04-5fe71c55552c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means— </text><subparagraph id="id3e481b7d-74d5-46d6-a529-ff6ad2d79fc8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd7497a3c-8a33-41a7-80d4-edfd1e6948bb" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Financial Services, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9650a615-e065-44f8-90a9-d8f4cab85d53" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">ISIS member</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>ISIS member</term> means a person who was part of, or substantially supported, the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id95c34b2e-f676-489a-b311-c85bb2b5f62c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Senior Coordinator</header><text>The term <term>Senior Coordinator</term> means the coordinator for detained ISIS members and relevant displaced populations in Syria designated under subsection (a) of section 1224 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; 133 Stat. 1642), as amended by subsection (d). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id02822cca-8847-4657-80a9-4e36c1b822b2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><paragraph id="idf9bb709e-c693-45e0-88ba-d5569dc36b25" changed="not-changed"><enum/><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="id5a551be8-1e37-458d-8875-e814156c836e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ISIS detainees held by the Syrian Democratic Forces and ISIS-affiliated individuals located within displaced persons camps in Syria pose a significant and growing humanitarian challenge and security threat to the region;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idccefc1c3ccc24946951701cdc465db31" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the vast majority of individuals held in displaced persons camps in Syria are women and children, approximately 50 percent of whom are under the age of 12 at the al-Hol camp, and they face significant threats of violence and radicalization, as well as lacking access to adequate sanitation and health care facilities; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id30936f33-d651-4dc8-9b4a-358f67a761a9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>there is an urgent need to seek a sustainable solution to such camps through repatriation and reintegration of the inhabitants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide4df5e2e-467a-4aa7-84bb-7086f5fd2009" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the United States should work closely with international allies and partners to facilitate the repatriation and reintegration efforts required to provide a long-term solution for such camps and prevent the resurgence of ISIS; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida91aa254-1e4e-4046-bfb2-6955e41cbf6c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>if left unaddressed, such camps will continue to be drivers of instability that jeopardize the long-term prospects for peace and stability in the region.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id17dd0d77-93ac-4234-a65d-87d4622ef7a0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that—</text><paragraph id="idb2a45287-3ecf-4b84-8817-f6123c20be5f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ISIS-affiliated individuals located within displacement camps in Syria, and other inhabitants of displacement camps in Syria, be repatriated and, where appropriate, prosecuted, or where possible, reintegrated into their country of origin, consistent with all relevant domestic laws and applicable international laws prohibiting refoulement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id545b21c6-17cd-4961-8242-693d3760f6f3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the camps will be closed as soon as is practicable. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6206e916-ed18-40e0-ba47-f4c89542639a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Modification of establishment of coordinator for detained ISIS members and relevant displaced populations in Syria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1224 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; 133 Stat. 1642) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id99e6b0ba-74da-40cf-8bb1-07ee64ce52b2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idef2420c0-0227-4353-81b6-55ceabf1b3f7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subsection (b) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id79a4abbf-4823-429f-a75f-da809e43b838" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="id9591fbc6-4e7a-4553-816f-194bd73c594e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><paragraph id="id293a71e1-6a48-407f-927f-f05abc0cd5d1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of State, the Director of National Intelligence, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, and the Attorney General, shall designate an existing official to serve within the executive branch as senior-level coordinator to coordinate, in conjunction with other relevant agencies, matters related to ISIS members who are in the custody of the Syrian Democratic Forces and other relevant displaced populations in Syria, including—</text><subparagraph id="id80022f5a-cb9f-422a-b53d-1d14211d8f31" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by engaging foreign partners to support the repatriation and disposition of such individuals, including by encouraging foreign partners to repatriate, transfer, investigate, and prosecute such ISIS members, and share information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ec3239a-5951-4d5b-a39c-0f3ce7de1da9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordination of all multilateral and international engagements led by the Department of State and other agencies that are related to the current and future handling, detention, and prosecution of such ISIS members; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3411f633-5544-495f-8e2f-dbbdcd08feb5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the funding and coordination of the provision of technical and other assistance to foreign countries to aid in the successful investigation and prosecution of such ISIS members, as appropriate, in accordance with relevant domestic laws, international humanitarian law, and other internationally recognized human rights and rule of law standards;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7e156ac8-5453-4e37-a3bb-4a64f446b650" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>coordination of all multilateral and international engagements related to humanitarian access and provision of basic services to, and freedom of movement and security and safe return of, displaced persons at camps or facilities in Syria that hold family members of such ISIS members;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5d8dd28a-71d4-4523-a783-1dda951a5504" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>coordination with relevant agencies on matters described in this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0d1b9bf3-2afe-4ac3-8b3d-385e2ec31cf5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other matter the President considers relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide9abe415-cc3c-46e9-8cd0-2713dba5412a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>If, on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Syria Detainee and Displaced Persons Act</short-title>, an individual has already been designated, consistent with the requirements and responsibilities described in paragraph (1), the requirements under that paragraph shall be considered to be satisfied with respect to such individual until the date on which such individual no longer serves as the Senior Coordinator.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="id87f54b75-3caf-4233-91b1-e5cc692bdc54" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>subsection (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a)</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4E84FA8706B74D6EA14F10D848F5DC34" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by striking <quote>subsection (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a)</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id676DC303F0D44D6EA895E33B2D636F49" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (e), by striking <quote>January 31, 2021</quote> and inserting <quote>January 31, 2025</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id27a1efc4-345e-497b-a072-7c8aacf81d85" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text><subparagraph id="id5c4876b3-75ef-4b32-a93a-cc06a932efad" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4eb1d8f7-fd9c-451f-9712-26294f4bdb69" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following new paragraph (2):</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2359076f-5b79-4b6c-87af-bc6fe1ed2850" changed="not-changed"><paragraph id="id5f12ca2c-ae53-483a-a38e-6d4ab7b80238" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Senior Coordinator</header><text>The term <term>Senior Coordinator</term> means the individual designated under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id183b372a-8e72-4fe2-a365-ab817a829fbc" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7a668bd9-dd55-4fe4-8b4c-4c709a7d7f40" changed="not-changed"><paragraph id="id2190ee6c-40e2-4f2e-b311-811229411016" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Relevant agencies</header><text>The term <term>relevant agencies</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id88a80efa-c3b7-4ee7-9f25-eaced8ef73e7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id163b4626-c33c-4ea2-9616-3beb935b23ae" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of Defense;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8842671c-506f-48eb-87b0-2bc202e60e1a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of the Treasury;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida695386b-92bb-4611-9b14-d879ee25226c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Justice;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idabe4a14f-7e26-4271-b54f-531bd9ce8c20" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the United States Agency for International Development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idef442e5b-2972-43c1-bf4d-43fe53a35e63" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Office of the Director of National Intelligence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9ba63604-137c-411c-a57c-1c364d542d51" changed="not-changed"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any other agency the President considers relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idbb95cb9d-178c-4d45-a4c0-01339fa7147c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (c) through (f) as subsections (b) through (e), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id331f8483-5590-406f-985e-a6d85c8a4fda" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Strategy on ISIS-Related detainee and displacement camps in Syria</header><paragraph id="id986e846b-2dea-4786-8088-026dd94d656b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, and the Attorney General, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress an interagency strategy with respect to ISIS-affiliated individuals and ISIS-related detainee and other displaced persons camps in Syria.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id32ec421a-76ff-45d8-b8ef-65a5255384c6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="id22f560a4-de8e-4636-99ae-b5afbf4415bd" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>methods to address—</text><clause id="iddcf913d3-8193-4e26-a7a6-2c9feb14989c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>disengagement from and prevention of recruitment into violence, violent extremism, and other illicit activity in such camps;</text></clause><clause id="ide5c607a1-5abe-4473-932c-e25df395d33c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>efforts to encourage and facilitate repatriation and, as appropriate, investigation and prosecution of foreign nationals from such camps, consistent with all relevant domestic and applicable international laws;</text></clause><clause id="id8bd981ea-8028-4e97-9c6f-8f589a47683f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the return and reintegration of displaced Syrian and Iraqi women and children into their communities of origin; </text></clause><clause id="id30f77ac9-f143-40ef-9b35-c1c8dae634e0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>international engagement to develop processes for repatriation and reintegration of foreign nationals from such camps;</text></clause><clause id="id2912ba09-e78e-4232-8f45-292c857e1e08" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>contingency plans for the relocation of detained and displaced persons who are not able to be repatriated from such camps;</text></clause><clause id="id182da2f2-882c-4059-8272-e9f068464be5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>efforts to improve the humanitarian conditions in such camps, including through the delivery of medicine, psychosocial support, clothing, education, and improved housing; and</text></clause><clause id="ide633b14b-6818-48b5-a03a-f929d62ab487" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>assessed humanitarian and security needs of all camps and detainment facilities based on prioritization of such camps and facilities most at risk of humanitarian crises, external attacks, or internal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id58cf7b5941d44b3682a5d8fdb887862c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of—</text><clause id="id8fef2245fa234cc2ba3adec5e6e5176b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>rehabilitation centers in northeast Syria, including humanitarian conditions and processes for admittance and efforts to improve both humanitarian conditions and admittance processes for such centers and camps, as well as on the prevention of youth radicalization; and</text></clause><clause id="idb973435509f64ccdb51d4c3d19e56370" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>processes for being sent to, and resources directed towards, rehabilitation centers and programs in countries that receive returned ISIS affiliated individuals, with a focus on the prevention of radicalization of minor children; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id076b0c34-b92c-4cce-87b5-fd1991c51e0e" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a plan to improve, in such camps—</text><clause id="idfa6c1e07-a11f-4a48-a90f-bc70fb00e9ed" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>security conditions, including by training of personnel and through construction; and</text></clause><clause id="id497beb6c-038b-438b-afa9-4c69884de8a4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>humanitarian conditions; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id506fdaa0-2294-42ad-bdce-d6fb080b9e2d" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a framework for measuring progress of humanitarian, security, and repatriation efforts with the goal of closing such camps; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idaa97c78c-57b5-4ca4-ba56-90b4b9695e60" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other matter the Secretary of State considers appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idF769C3C5EDAD4E69AC5DB8D3EC42F7D8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex that is transmitted separately.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id3e1f01a8-83ba-41b6-a1e6-3f6fa4886fd2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual interagency report</header><paragraph id="idad2f0c5f-8211-4913-a6e7-0ef0780c14c8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and not less frequently than annually thereafter through January 31, 2025, the Senior Coordinator, in coordination with the relevant agencies, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a detailed report that includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="id9c8f7549-8c44-41a1-98a8-f4b7acb5ccd2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A detailed description of the facilities and camps where detained ISIS members, and families with perceived ISIS affiliation, are being held and housed, including—</text><clause id="id1420f14c-2ee9-4180-bacc-f87ce2f8b13b" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of the security and management of such facilities and camps;</text></clause><clause id="id68bcf588-b9bf-4edf-b3d5-00fd807ca197" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an assessment of resources required for the security of such facilities and camps; </text></clause><clause id="idda814e26-2646-4183-a2a3-bccddd232030" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an assessment of the adherence by the operators of such facilities and camps to international humanitarian law standards; and</text></clause><clause id="id4e98ed9b437544c5ad347dcb0ffc196c" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an assessment of children held within such facilities and camps that may be used as part of smuggling operations to evade security at the facilities and camps. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide93e4487-690f-485a-9b8a-4c88ead0078f" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of all efforts undertaken by, and the resources needed for, the United States Government to address deficits in the humanitarian environment and security of such facilities and camps. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc07a879b-43da-4687-9daf-72e8fecdba13" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of all multilateral and international engagements related to humanitarian access and provision of basic services to, and freedom of movement and security and safe return of, displaced persons at camps or facilities in Iraq, Syria, and any other area affected by ISIS activity, including a description of—</text><clause id="ided5e59b8-7fc3-412b-bca8-113363d38e82" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>support for efforts by the Syrian Democratic Forces to facilitate the return and reintegration of displaced people from Iraq and Syria;</text></clause><clause id="id465a472c-220b-4f94-b908-d005df07ff65" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>repatriation efforts with respect to displaced women and children and male children aging into adults while held in these facilities and camps;</text></clause><clause id="id82c8854d-4c63-4f34-ad09-af145cf96e39" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any current or future potential threat to United States national security interests posed by detained ISIS members or displaced families, including an analysis of the al-Hol camp and annexes; and</text></clause><clause id="id46847bda-9528-44d7-973f-e38b740a48d6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>United States Government plans and strategies to respond to any threat identified under clause (iii).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0E37FC2EDF57410DAE86DEE314BE1450" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The number of individuals repatriated from the custody of the Syrian Democratic Forces.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id653726c3-8985-426a-ad74-a76098f47201" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An analysis of factors on the ground in Syria and Iraq that may result in the unintended release of detained or displaced ISIS members, and an assessment of any measures available to mitigate such releases.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4bb13448-cfc1-4240-ac2f-d56af576a06a" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A detailed description of efforts to encourage the final disposition and security of detained or displaced ISIS members with other countries and international organizations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddd1a3269d5bd429b831972acc9dc3c20" changed="not-changed"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A description of foreign repatriation and rehabilitation programs deemed successful systems to model, and an analysis of the long-term results of such programs. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id45be908e-0bcf-4ce7-a131-c842ac927de7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A description of the manner in which the United States Government communicates regarding repatriation and disposition efforts with the families of United States citizens believed to have been victims of a criminal act by a detained or displaced ISIS member, in accordance with section 503(c) of the Victims' Rights and Restitution Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20141">34 U.S.C. 20141(c)</external-xref>) and section 3771 of title 18, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5e0bca8e-25b7-4bdc-867b-cc5b620db4e6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>An analysis of all efforts between the United States and partner countries within the Global Coalition to Defeat ISIS or other countries to share related information that may aid in resolving the final disposition of ISIS members, and any obstacles that may hinder such efforts.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id90631a1b-c9b7-458a-82ae-5edf651380b9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Any other matter the Coordinator considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id73953250-2c44-4851-9367-f9fc61144dcd" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex that is transmitted separately. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id89B56EB60BCB48B193A06FA8F803801F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section, or an amendment made by this section, may be construed—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4D83A5D3AD6F466EA5715EF565DC2D64" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to limit the authority of any Federal agency to independently carry out the authorized functions of such agency; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idA1A023E9A5FA4074841C231009EC55B7" changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to impair or otherwise affect the activities performed by that agency as granted by law. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

