<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MDM23763-S0F-C8-HJ9"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 S1651 IS: Western Balkans Democracy and Prosperity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1651</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S324">Mrs. Shaheen</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S318">Mr. Wicker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S308">Mr. Cardin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S253">Mr. Durbin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S390">Mr. Van Hollen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To encourage increased trade and investment between the United States and the countries in the Western Balkans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="idfc4c3b63e57e43c18c4e74ab70fe9bf5"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="idF3C275F2387A40FD91B5285D5763F978"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Western Balkans Democracy and Prosperity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="id5B54223515C945C298369A3FAD2B6EF2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="idfc4c3b63e57e43c18c4e74ab70fe9bf5">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id6bef32171e774ceaa1c9931f9cd36ae4">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id0f7c6b0dab234c0ba8a8ff2257f4ddb7">Sec. 3. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idf9a71ac3aa5f455885a9f6e766bbe7c7">Sec. 4. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id228DB61BA9114085952E90CD892365E9">Sec. 5. Codification of sanctions relating to the Western Balkans.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id7ed384aa12f4452785f6c5cadb32d7c0">Sec. 6. Congressional review of certain actions relating to sanctions imposed with respect to the Western Balkans.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idBC5669DE7A634CAFB1DE4E255E300BF7">Sec. 7. Democratic and economic development and prosperity initiatives.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idde1305c6d5054559aa4d02532e6e273d">Sec. 8. Countering malign influence and promoting cross-cultural engagement.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id25e66cc11ad44196a202f2724912d73c">Sec. 9. Peace Corps in the Western Balkans.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id56ca8f8e3e7e4f55a068d4ebf1876d3f">Sec. 10. Balkans Youth Leadership Initiative.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idaeae170d11b94ba080afb80db249c4bc">Sec. 11. Supporting cybersecurity and cyber resilience in the Western Balkans.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id87486a0b37fd40a2b2f67a7136265174">Sec. 12. Sense of Congress regarding an interim agreement.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id5D8EAB28F6F54BB6B3E71AA89D34AC3A">Sec. 13. Sunset.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="id6bef32171e774ceaa1c9931f9cd36ae4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="id50cc61ca1b924545a387bd236e9f222d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Western Balkans countries (the Republic of Albania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, the Republic of Kosovo, Montenegro, the Republic of North Macedonia, and the Republic of Serbia) form a pluralistic, multi-ethnic region in the heart of Europe that is critical to the peace, stability, and prosperity of Europe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id12935b69a22248cca51208ae5de7abb3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Continued peace, stability, and prosperity in the Western Balkans is directly tied to opportunities for democratic and economic advancement available to the citizens and residents of those 6 countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id762b2cbb065a43ca978de41bb7899a63"><enum>(3)</enum><text>It is in the mutual interest of the United States and the 6 countries of the Western Balkans to promote stable and sustainable economic growth and development in the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9ca3ff0270b94c108b4313c4d944b885"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The reforms and integration with the European Union pursued by countries in the Western Balkans have led to significant democratic and economic progress in the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id19bd27144258426fa32d86b9d5e720d5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Despite economic progress, rates of poverty and unemployment in the Western Balkans remain higher than in neighboring European Union countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id07d78a9e2e004b91b3f6e50d83092fed"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Out-migration, particularly of youth, is affecting demographics in each Western Balkans country, resulting in negative population growth in all 6 countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4a95b670274346deae412b64915e3b95"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Creating an enabling environment for transparent, accountable, and market-oriented investment and creating employment opportunities in the Western Balkans, especially for youth, can provide powerful tools for economic development and for encouraging broader participation in a political process that increases prosperity for all. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id09D624C1B9574E0EB225A99C1A34E4BB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Offering opportunities for inclusive, transparent economic growth and merit-based employment to people living in the Western Balkans will encourage higher levels of trade and direct investment and support positive economic and political developments occurring throughout the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id705bb0fe52a346269e3875b7dda263b5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Existing regional economic efforts, such as the Common Regional Market and the Open Balkan initiative, when aligned with European Union standards, norms, and regulations, have the potential to improve the economic conditions in the Western Balkans, while promoting inclusion and transparency. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idce71c032c8f3427d8b69b0a8b453b583"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The Department of Commerce, through its Foreign Commercial Service, plays an important role in promoting and facilitating opportunities for United States trade and investment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id13c57275990f412b822005f32bfc3562"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Corruption continues to plague the Western Balkans and represents one of the greatest impediments to further economic and political development in the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idce556af90cef49568b81f0c8588ac844"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Disinformation campaigns targeting the Western Balkans threaten the credibility of Western democratic institutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2a27993d727f4082818a628b498c91c9"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Vulnerabilities to corrosive capital, malign economic influence, interference, and economic coercion are acutely present in Western Balkans economies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id700d74d1d0d742ec88db2c2cd1580c72"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Vulnerability to cyberattacks or attacks on information and communication technology infrastructure increases risks to the functioning of government and the delivery of public services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3efeec4d7ec74bff866b66d2ea99c1f1"><enum>(15)</enum><text>United States Cyber Command plays a critical role in defending the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id119854a7db474d29a2775f9f0a1d901e"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Securing domestic and international cyber networks and electronic infrastructure is a national security priority for the United States, which is exemplified by offices and programs across the Federal Government that support cyber security, including—</text><subparagraph id="ida35051c5b6604f93a699565c16d5a5bf"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security’s Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id13ca7d0db0c44116a557c611af077a42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of State’s Bureau of Cyberspace and Digital Policy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id99985754a5fe4a73a6db99f53cc7bb2a"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the United States Agency for International Development’s Digital Strategy; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5c53c4fe455c4291a9fe548a9fa1246c"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Energy’s CyberForce Program. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf987b3a9ddba42db9e9608a0e0950d45"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Corruption and disinformation proliferate in political environments marked by autocratic control or partisan conflict.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id20667d0789b2408a98c91263e66e0e35"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Dependence on Russian sources of oil and natural gas for the countries of the Western Balkans ties their economies and politics to the Russian Federation and inhibits their aspirations for European integration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd8e2c7ab57a64702a276fd9a79c9d42d"><enum>(19)</enum><text>The reliance of the Western Balkans on fossil fuels for energy sources causes damage to the environment and to human health, while inhibiting economic development in the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfb86b82181bb4ccd91dbe346268db888"><enum>(20)</enum><text>Reducing the reliance of the Western Balkans on Russian natural gas supplies is in the national interest of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddea46138ecc944f48a5f8da00b2ff054"><enum>(21)</enum><text>The growing influence of China in the Western Balkans could also have a deleterious impact on strategic competition, democracy, and economic integration with Europe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id63dac602c93142ad9a53c43870f0b8fd"><enum>(22)</enum><text>The United States International Development Finance Corporation plays an important role in the pursuit of United States policy goals focused on economic development.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6dcb741beb1a4120987186b62c8bd109"><enum>(23)</enum><text>In March 2022, President Biden launched the European Democratic Resilience Initiative to bolster democratic resilience, advance anti-corruption efforts, and defend human rights in Ukraine and its neighbors in response to Russia’s war of aggression.</text></paragraph></section><section id="id0f7c6b0dab234c0ba8a8ff2257f4ddb7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is a sense of Congress that the United States should—</text><paragraph id="id5ebeef828464411d8f1e70cbb3bda81a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encourage increased trade and investment between the United States and allies and partners in the Western Balkans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf900fbf799e245e494ea41541b7caed0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expand United States assistance to regional integration efforts in the Western Balkans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id06c7e03946764c6389aebec761591d27"><enum>(3)</enum><text>strengthen and expand regional economic integration in the Western Balkans, especially enterprises owned by and employing women and youth;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf4bc2e3a466747ef80f4401c02b4243c"><enum>(4)</enum><text>work with allies and partners committed to improving the rule of law, energy resource diversification, democratic and economic reform, and the eradication of poverty in the Western Balkans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9c34ce511e5f4406936c740f832769ef"><enum>(5)</enum><text>increase United States trade and investment with the Western Balkans, particularly in ways that—</text><subparagraph id="id6c71ce16e36249758e0c2612fb43cb00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>decrease dependence on Russian energy sources and fossil fuels; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCAFBFC71575A4C39BD442115E7278727"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increase energy diversification, efficiency, and conservation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id01b332a097884b38ad794e30cbd6e548"><enum>(C)</enum><text>facilitate the transition to cleaner and more reliable sources of energy, including renewables;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id688d6ce70e9b4decb0815a749f366ed7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>support the efforts of countries of the Western Balkans to develop—</text><subparagraph id="id8900d459d4ab4a2bb5ee2bc4aad15bb8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strong civil societies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9f051fe94a27422d840e0662abbbd76f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>public-private partnerships and dialogue in policy development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id063b0098bf264801afb2b45c7b6786e0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>independent media;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7e7142e585634ff0b8fd8248aedaddfc"><enum>(D)</enum><text>transparent, accountable, citizen-responsive governance, including expanded representation for women and youth in democratic spaces; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id343eb90e2b6c4ccb8136794c01ab5907"><enum>(E)</enum><text>political stability;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id25590e8c32834e90ad12643a3f85630a"><enum>(7)</enum><text>support the expeditious accession of the Western Balkans countries to the European Union and to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (referred to in this section as <quote>NATO</quote>) for those that desire and meet the criteria for membership; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd10967d154304dc487897af4c206868f"><enum>(8)</enum><text>support—</text><subparagraph id="ide13074cb98c241d7b68d11bb40c6389d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintaining the full European Union Force (EUFOR) mandate in Bosnia and Herzegovina as being in the national security interests of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbd9537a1f85a42179faa00fe9682af38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>encouraging NATO and the European Union to review their mission mandates and posture in Bosnia and Herzegovina to ensure they are playing a proactive role in establishing a safe and secure environment, particularly the defense environment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida9f6f7f9e8934752a4a5a8a5dfc9a3e4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>using the voice of the United States in NATO to encourage alliance planning and support of an international military force to maintain a safe and secure environment in Bosnia and Herzegovina, especially if Russia blocks reauthorization of the mission in the United Nations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idBF542F8B7FD24FD3B7403EADC378FCFD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a strengthened NATO headquarters in Sarajevo;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id097b5658e15a4fc18bc02f4472018987"><enum>(9)</enum><text>continue security cooperation with the Republic of Albania, Montenegro, and the Republic of North Macedonia through the auspices of NATO and through continued bilateral cooperation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd495dc1709d144b49962db780f57bb8c"><enum>(10)</enum><text>continue to support Montenegro’s ongoing accession negotiations with the European Union, including by providing assistance to Montenegro to help the country promptly meet European Union membership criteria;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id506b200fa302425e820706d4ab8b8eaa"><enum>(11)</enum><text>continue to support the applications of the Republic of North Macedonia and the Republic of Albania for European Union membership by supporting improvement of their respective abilities to meet democracy benchmarks required for accession;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id59ea88c6e0b148b092d33d7cc6d12fac"><enum>(12)</enum><text>continue to support the overarching mission of the Open Balkan initiative provided the initiative remains inclusive of all Western Balkans countries and remains aligned with the objectives and standards laid out by the European Union for requirements for accession to the European Union; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8d64cf9deae6409ca4c3b321771e4af8"><enum>(13)</enum><text>continue to support the pursuit by Bosnia and Herzegovina of European Union candidate status by encouraging meaningful advancement of its reform agenda;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id75365dffdb524c3c91a32df47edc89a5"><enum>(14)</enum><text>continue to support the cultural heritage, and recognize the languages of the Western Balkans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id441eabfcf0cf428db735f3d352e058ea"><enum>(15)</enum><text>coordinate closely with the European Union, the United Kingdom, and other allies and partners on sanctions designations and work to align efforts as much as possible to demonstrate a clear commitment to upholding democratic values;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idee3cd3acad9f42118fc6c38c2597eef0"><enum>(16)</enum><text>expand bilateral security cooperation with NATO-aspirant Western Balkan countries, particularly efforts focused on regional integration and cooperation, including through the Adriatic Charter, done at Tirana May 2, 2003;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcf7494f37adc4c10ad448a184fb0364f"><enum>(17)</enum><text>increase efforts to combat Russian disinformation campaigns and any other malign, destabilizing, or disruptive activities targeting the Western Balkans through engagement with government institutions, political stakeholders, journalists, civil society organizations, and industry leaders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id452af4e624ea49ccbd5ca2621d3846d4"><enum>(18)</enum><text>develop a series of cyber resilience standards, consistent with the Enhanced Cyber Defense Policy and Readiness Action Plan endorsed at the 2014 Wales Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization to expand cooperation with partners and allies, including in the Western Balkans, on cyber security and ICT infrastructure defenses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1c91c4304062482f9507415ccf7c645d"><enum>(19)</enum><text>articulate clearly and unambiguously the United States commitment to supporting democratic values and respect for international law as the sole path forward for the countries of the Western Balkans; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id74629d6b26ec4cda84079034775c5614"><enum>(20)</enum><text>support the mission of the Peace Corps to promote world peace and friendship by helping the people of interested countries to meet their need for trained men and women, which provides an invaluable opportunity to connect the American people with the people of the Western Balkans. </text></paragraph></section><section id="idf9a71ac3aa5f455885a9f6e766bbe7c7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="id2F3F80D560DE4E6BB8BDF6E87FB3EC8E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idF11553D6B2974ADDB2973A2935D24B76"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id238507865FE5423D93C84265CA92C30B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id94BE97E1CD724EB9B9C8AB7C48C9CA0B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3B23E589C87447E894C027F87CDE77FE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9df5285bb7084294b256a3a485dceb64"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Western balkans</header><text>The term <term>Western Balkans</term> means the region comprised of the following countries:</text><subparagraph id="id5e5dd21b811c4aa3b987c2b40bdc77ae"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Republic of Albania.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id45eece0c5acc41178acfbcc72fde426b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Bosnia and Herzegovina.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id00f778462d7d405fbdd7563c423ca041"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Montenegro.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0cd738d2c6734c8588adda42d4c5c0bb"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Republic of Kosovo.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9ba96e04c1f0475ca2a1164adf65e3dc"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Republic of North Macedonia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1904d23209604083a8641fe13489062f"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Republic of Serbia.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4bda0628bcb5418a99e03caef2a8d8a2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Western balkans country</header><text>The term <term>Western Balkan country</term> means any country listed in subparagraphs (A) through (F) of paragraph (2). </text></paragraph></section><section id="id228DB61BA9114085952E90CD892365E9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Codification of sanctions relating to the Western Balkans</header><subsection id="id26e62127b1a745cdb5d490bf83c481b7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each sanction imposed through Executive orders described in subsection (b), including each sanction imposed with respect to a person under such an Executive order, as of the date of the enactment of this Act, shall remain in effect, except as provided in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="id9afe67433650437ba9f0e7577784a610"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive orders specified</header><text>The Executive orders specified in this subsection are—</text><paragraph id="id58bd540b30bb4d4885a3233688783c8d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Executive Order 13219 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property of persons who threaten international stabilization efforts in the Western Balkans), as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6056fa57152940498cf5532e831dc937"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Executive Order 14033 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and suspending entry into the United States of certain persons contributing to the destabilizing situation in the Western Balkans), as in effect on such date of enactment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide5510a2419884bfa813b32d909d9815e"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination of sanctions</header><text>The President may terminate the application of a sanction described in subsection (a) with respect to a person if the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that—</text><paragraph id="idd9dcff1d08874cf099ac671cbf04018d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such person—</text><subparagraph id="id6216E1AA3D464FCFA750E13701C6B4B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not engaging in the activity that was the basis for such sanctions; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idA3ACDAE58D604419AE4DC5973B1533A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has taken significant verifiable steps toward stopping such activity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9da30c99012042bd87b4b9d2ffb73d20"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the President has received reliable assurances that such person will not knowingly engage in activity subject to such sanctions in the future. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id7ed384aa12f4452785f6c5cadb32d7c0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Congressional review of certain actions relating to sanctions imposed with respect to the Western Balkans</header><subsection id="id92d0de0d51a04525954a3a92b73f4c1a"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="id8F1B95F01CA04BAFBFF4F89257839B34"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered congressional committees and leadership</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered congressional committees and leadership</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idce14cd0de88d486ca972b35a1b83356d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3ECDAEEECC7E421EABC205A7B749790D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idA01637A6489D48578852D68395B1B554"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Majority Leader of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7CF01C7BC7B243BAB7AB69F531337606"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Minority Leader of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7df33350753c467293ae6cc62b83bc72" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idFD40151AD8244F00AE21C9DAE55ABAA3"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6DA7E91275FA4FF3B03E6FD38514147C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Speaker of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3AFA0CAD1CAF44B1BC9E5E807D1592D0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Majority Leader of the House of Representatives; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idC1DD2471207443C68E319067082695B8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Minority Leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id10b11f0cf75f42a1b29e7c6c693ce14e"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Joint resolution of approval</header><text>The term <term>joint resolution of approval</term> means only a joint resolution of either House of Congress—</text><subparagraph id="id2ca3f7aa46814f6ba4a90cb45f2c0036"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the title of which is as follows: <quote>A joint resolution approving the President’s proposal to take an action relating to the application of certain sanctions with respect to the Western Balkans.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab9e2df003c84c399c0d32b4156a1b06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the sole matter after the resolving clause of which is the following: <quote>Congress approves of the action relating to the application of sanctions imposed with respect to the Western Balkans proposed by the President in the report submitted to Congress under section 6(b)(1) of the Western Balkans Democracy and Prosperity Act on _____ relating to ______.</quote>, with the first blank space being filled with the appropriate date and the second blank space being filled with a short description of the proposed action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0a8099792525476fa00dc32cf2bb1c87"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval</header><text>The term <term>joint resolution of disapproval</term> means only a joint resolution of either House of Congress—</text><subparagraph id="id7e1d12ad28fb4dd2a5cef86ba8942b7b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the title of which is as follows: <quote>A joint resolution disapproving the President’s proposal to take an action relating to the application of certain sanctions with respect to the Western Balkans.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3069ef92c8e4433283a033535f65c2d9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the sole matter after the resolving clause of which is the following: <quote>Congress disapproves of the action relating to the application of sanctions imposed with respect to the Western Balkans proposed by the President in the report submitted to Congress under section 6(b)(1) of the Western Balkans Democracy and Prosperity Act on _____ relating to ______.</quote>, with the first blank space being filled with the appropriate date and the second blank space being filled with a short description of the proposed action. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide8d8712ce32a4044971544cdfd4b2c7c"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Submission to Congress of proposed action</header><paragraph id="ida26b4ed3a21f4b788076f5207a7050e5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, before taking any action described in paragraph (2)(A), the President shall submit a report to the covered congressional committees and leadership that includes—</text><subparagraph id="idB500DD08BEB64C098B0A46F4757AF4CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the proposed action; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idEE2FE0CB45E846A8B1A495074AF9A762"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a justification for the proposed action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7079ee10c5154fdcba086d0a44ce1cb6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Actions and sanctions described</header><subparagraph id="id4c7c746094644701baea45768040719c"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Actions described</header><text>An action described in this subparagraph is—</text><clause id="idc384e0faa5094705b203c3d2b60f0ff0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an action to terminate the application of any sanction described in subparagraph (B);</text></clause><clause id="idbdad1d6b412f4be38af4188e11cc82e5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to a sanction described in subparagraph (B) imposed by the President with respect to a person, an action to waive the application of such sanction with respect to that person; or</text></clause><clause id="id57ebceaeec8d45f3adfbb60185986e2c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a licensing action that significantly alters the foreign policy of the United States with respect to the Western Balkans.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbbc34978caf34b7d9903e5313a000622"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>A sanction described in this subparagraph is a sanction imposed under—</text><clause id="id90362a647e1247468034e1d1e048d205"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Executive Order 13219 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property of persons who threaten international stabilization efforts in the Western Balkans), as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text></clause><clause id="id7fb9923f53904d51a67e2a4b771a6075"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Executive Order 14033 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and suspending entry into the United States of certain persons contributing to the destabilizing situation in the Western Balkans), as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5cbe4bdf1ca3425c87b98ca4dba6e9e0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Type of action</header><text>Each report submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) with respect to an action described in paragraph (2)(A) shall include a description of whether the action—</text><subparagraph id="idb5b46a5becfb4dc4ac83301ec9dc24fc"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not intended to significantly alter the foreign policy of the United States with respect to the Western Balkans; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8661909c80e64a13a8a955be2df723ae"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is intended to significantly alter the foreign policy of the United States with respect to the Western Balkans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id96b62773ba054f3db5f7e30d5dad1dab"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Inclusion of additional matters</header><subparagraph id="id00c8ccf51e7a4a8dab40e350d05a9e38"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Additional matters</header><text>Each report submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) that relates to an action that is intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with respect to the Western Balkans, as determined pursuant to paragraph (3)(B), shall include a description of—</text><clause id="id056d56fb70d94f8b96e386023bdc5068"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the intended significant alteration to such foreign policy;</text></clause><clause id="id66b200f2f78f49caaae26da18beacb60"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the anticipated effect of the action on the national security interests of the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="id3cd01c56c9444b82834d2de15db11a23"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the policy objectives for which the sanctions affected by the action were initially imposed.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9d14e3c68fc246b78e4b71ae82ebd5d3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requests from banking and financial services committees</header><text>The <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> or the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives</committee-name> may request the submission to such committee of the matters specified in clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (A) with respect to a report submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) that relates to an action that is not intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with regard to the Western Balkans, as determined pursuant to paragraph (3)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idac9bec4c0e5a4154b56705c433bcc7b1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Period for review by Congress</header><paragraph id="id2feb651338a54b8a9c92343167ca58e7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), during the 90-legislative day period beginning on the date on which the President submits a report pursuant to subsection (b)(1)—</text><subparagraph id="ida9674bad30584d208e13cf62fbd0addd"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a report that relates to an action that is not intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with regard to the Western Balkans, as determined pursuant to subsection (b)(3)(A), the <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives</committee-name> should, as appropriate, hold hearings and briefings and otherwise obtain information in order to fully review the report; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idefe7d4aca00746eba5a5a19d3ee22315"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a report that relates to an action that is intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with regard to the Western Balkans, as determined pursuant to subsection (b)(3)(B), the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name> should, as appropriate, hold hearings and briefings and otherwise obtain information in order to fully review the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb6e9c3f866034ed9a81ddf9b826be260"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The period for congressional review under paragraph (1) of a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) shall be 120 calendar days if the report is submitted on or after July 10 and on or before September 7 in any calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id36ffe0b68ea44a9893ba69b322ddc0aa"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on actions during initial congressional review period</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during the congressional review period described in paragraph (1) of a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) proposing an action described in subsection (b)(2), including any additional period for such review as applicable under the exception provided in paragraph (2), the President may not take that action unless a joint resolution of approval with respect to such action has been enacted in accordance with subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idebdd25ef46124cd1a80dc772ef435b95"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on actions during presidential consideration of a joint resolution of disapproval</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if a joint resolution of disapproval relating to a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) proposing an action described in subsection (b)(2) passes both Houses of Congress in accordance with subsection (d), the President may not take such action until the date that is 12 days after the date on which such joint resolution of disapproval has been passed by both Houses of Congress.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idadb6473e256e4674b51aae54f50f6671"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limitation on actions during congressional reconsideration of a joint resolution of disapproval</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if a joint resolution of disapproval relating to a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) proposing an action described in subsection (b)(2) passes both Houses of Congress in accordance with subsection (d), and the President vetoes such joint resolution, the President may not take such action until 10 days after the date of the President’s veto.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide98e9f752b45440c9015643617063ee6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Effect of enactment of a joint resolution of disapproval</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if a joint resolution of disapproval relating to a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) proposing an action described in subsection (b)(2) is enacted in accordance with subsection (d), the President may not take such action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id20e95a176eaf4b2cabc0b96a9324c297"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Joint resolutions of disapproval or approval</header><paragraph id="id4e70818ae432459cbad7eeddc1768434"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Introduction</header><text>During the 90-legislative day period described in subsection (c)(1), including any additional period applicable under the exception provided in subsection (c)(2), a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval may be introduced—</text><subparagraph id="id9ab8a3441d90402daa330abb04aab9f6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the Senate, by the Majority Leader (or designee) or the Minority Leader (or designee); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idafffcd70ac8d490ab7a68cbf764e3413"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the House of Representatives, by the Majority Leader or the Minority Leader.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida919b255a3884a3fa5ae8537d1ad6431"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Floor consideration in house of representatives</header><text>If a committee of the House of Representatives to which a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval has been referred does not report the joint resolution to the House of Representatives within 10 days after the date of referral, such committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the joint resolution.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2a5c99e4c2ef44de83314398ad6c4b8f"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consideration in senate</header><subparagraph id="idbcf9d8e8e01344999f16d945cbec0ceb"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Committee referral</header><text>A joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval introduced in the Senate shall be—</text><clause id="id3703ee61d54f41ac98e3bc4470822a38"><enum>(i)</enum><text>referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> if the joint resolution relates to a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) that relates to an action that is not intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with regard to the Russian Federation, as determined pursuant to subsection (b)(3)(A); and</text></clause><clause id="id5eb0848000324146805738dba4cbfe93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name> if the joint resolution relates to a report submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) that relates to an action that is intended to significantly alter United States foreign policy with respect to the Russian Federation, as determined pursuant to subsection (b)(3)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3c7c166c60b7496993cf1c31f6d2b15b"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting and discharge</header><text>If the committee to which a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval was referred does not report the joint resolution to the Senate within 10 days after the date of referral of the joint resolution, such committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the joint resolution and the joint resolution shall be placed on the appropriate calendar.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id133f021869cc4d228f6ecefcb01ed705"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Proceeding to consideration</header><text>Notwithstanding Rule XXII of the Standing Rules of the Senate, it is in order at any time after the <committee-name committee-id="SSBK00">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> or the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>, as the case may be, reports a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval to the Senate or has been discharged from consideration of such a joint resolution (even though a previous motion to the same effect has been disagreed to) to move to proceed to the consideration of the joint resolution, and all points of order against the joint resolution (and against consideration of the joint resolution) are waived. The motion to proceed is not debatable. The motion is not subject to a motion to postpone. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is agreed to or disagreed to shall not be in order.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd4d7333229264fe6899186145cfcb70e"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rulings of the chair on procedure</header><text>Appeals from the decisions of the Chair relating to the application of the rules of the Senate, as the case may be, to the procedure relating to a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval shall be decided without debate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id800762814c0e429da6cd83102c493bef"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Consideration of veto messages</header><text>Debate in the Senate of any veto message with respect to a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval, including all debatable motions and appeals in connection with the joint resolution, shall be limited to 10 hours, to be equally divided between, and controlled by, the Majority Leader of the Senate and the Minority Leader of the Senate, or their designees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5adbd4b640ff452e9a880d2a9b12617b"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rules relating to senate and house of representatives</header><subparagraph id="idd3209cf16ce047218687c02a4b80a436"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Treatment of senate joint resolution in house of representatives</header><text>In the House of Representatives, the following procedures shall apply to a joint resolution of approval or a joint resolution of disapproval received from the Senate (unless the House has already passed a joint resolution relating to the same proposed action):</text><clause id="id1670c1f546134cb789df9102ddf12280"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The joint resolution shall be referred to the appropriate committees.</text></clause><clause id="id5efc681e319c4dd9be92b0d3d970438e"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If a committee to which a joint resolution has been referred has not reported the joint resolution within 2 days after the date of referral, such committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the joint resolution.</text></clause><clause id="ida6f310735f194a089b5bc422641d0dba"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Beginning on the third legislative day after each committee to which a joint resolution has been referred reports the joint resolution to the House of Representatives or has been discharged from further consideration thereof, it shall be in order to move to proceed to consider the joint resolution in the House of Representatives. All points of order against the motion are waived. Such a motion shall not be in order after the House has disposed of a motion to proceed on the joint resolution. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on the motion to its adoption without intervening motion. The motion shall not be debatable. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is disposed of shall not be in order.</text></clause><clause id="ida7f5cbd2a26a43179db79746bed882ba"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The joint resolution shall be considered as read. All points of order against the joint resolution and against its consideration are waived. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on the joint resolution to final passage without intervening motion except 2 hours of debate equally divided and controlled by the sponsor of the joint resolution (or a designee) and an opponent. A motion to reconsider the vote on passage of the joint resolution shall not be in order.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2314d6facf2f45dda53670a69765feec"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of house of representatives joint resolution in senate</header><clause id="id3b84f4d3bbab4d178a612771af73ae3d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>If, before the passage by the Senate of a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval, the Senate receives an identical joint resolution from the House of Representatives, the following procedures shall apply:</text><subclause id="id48a7c335de8b4cb1bcffeb14ea0a65ee"><enum>(I)</enum><text>That joint resolution shall not be referred to a committee.</text></subclause><subclause id="id76e8af10606d477c9005b6c6df10703e"><enum>(II)</enum><text>With respect to that joint resolution—</text><item id="id64e4a2807fe94c48892cb66d9a761030"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the procedure in the Senate shall be the same as if no joint resolution had been received from the House of Representatives; but</text></item><item id="id1b2a2a4699ee4c77ac7130fcd6ff0225"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the vote on passage shall be on the joint resolution from the House of Representatives.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="id95097a7799964bb5abed4b5f8f219e36"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If, following passage of a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval in the Senate, the Senate receives an identical joint resolution from the House of Representatives, that joint resolution shall be placed on the appropriate Senate calendar.</text></clause><clause id="id43a04432c91c4e2494f88d881914485a"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>If a joint resolution of approval or a joint resolution of disapproval is received from the House of Representatives, and no companion joint resolution has been introduced in the Senate, the Senate procedures under this subsection shall apply to the House of Representatives joint resolution.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id69e4a6e800744d8faf13e5c013f26bf2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Application to revenue measures</header><text>The provisions of this paragraph shall not apply in the House of Representatives to a joint resolution of approval or joint resolution of disapproval that is a revenue measure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf36d16e3cf7c4523a8c4bae7f315977a"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rules of house of representatives and senate</header><text>This subsection is enacted by Congress—</text><subparagraph id="id17ec346787aa44a8956d11397b115422"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and the House of Representatives, respectively, and as such is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, and supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide9f4edc8eb0e4c28b41793ac5a408a8a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idBC5669DE7A634CAFB1DE4E255E300BF7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Democratic and economic development and prosperity initiatives</header><subsection id="idcc0aa42113b74934810d8f25cb017705"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Anti-Corruption initiative</header><text>The Secretary of State, through ongoing and new programs, shall—</text><paragraph id="id5f4e1f01b2924f51a14e377e0dc87ad1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>seek to expand technical assistance in each Western Balkans country to develop new national anti-corruption strategies, or to strengthen existing national anti-corruption strategies focused on priorities, including good governance, election administration, and transparent economic investments, taking into account local conditions and contingent on the agreement of the host country government;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id801806bff7c944d49d77783847f3a567"><enum>(2)</enum><text>seek to share best practices with, and provide training to, civilian law enforcement agencies and judicial institutions, and other relevant administrative bodies, of the Western Balkans countries, to improve the efficiency, transparency, and accountability of such agencies and institutions on priorities, including the promotion of human rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1d5c260a26164e4daf9df228bbf12f97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide to the Western Balkans countries support to combat corruption, particularly in the judiciary, independent election oversight bodies, and public procurement processes, and to strengthen regulatory and legislative oversight of critical governance areas, such as freedom of information and public procurement, including by strengthening cyber defenses and ICT infrastructure networks; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0c17f1ceb039494894640b8fe18f3610"><enum>(4)</enum><text>include the Western Balkans countries in the European Democratic Resilience Initiative of the Department of State, or any successor initiative, and considers the Western Balkans as a recipient of anti-corruption funding for such initiative.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id55d55f33996341f3864bc506800595ac"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prioritizing cyber resilience, regional trade, and economic competitiveness</header><paragraph id="idb7e1e5ff3b084879a079ef708f1d12b3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="idd6a0ce643eb04ff48bed3bd2677c77cb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promoting stronger economic, civic, and political relationships among Western Balkans countries will enable such countries to better utilize existing resources and maximize their economic security and democratic resilience by reinforcing cyber defenses and increasing trade in goods and services among other countries in the region; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1389a1baced845c0a737e1ff7a8371bb"><enum>(B)</enum><text>United States investments in and assistance toward creating a more integrated region ensures political stability and security for the region.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id08c733f95612489ba04f909e60e840a5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>5-year strategy for economic development and democratic resilience in western balkans</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Commerce, and the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a regional economic development and democratic resilience strategy for the Western Balkans that—</text><subparagraph id="idddc6144f581c413ca099679b4857f2da"><enum>(A)</enum><text>considers the full set of tools and resources available from the agencies overseen by such Federal officials;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5bf81ebf10bd4890ba586aaed4a14e7f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes efforts to ensure coordination with multilateral and bilateral partners, such as the European Union, the World Bank, and other relevant assistance frameworks;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id74f05d05fce04f4cbb19dfa429d55a31"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes an initial public assessment of—</text><clause id="id0647b3456c234698b7fb8bc8982b48e6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>economic opportunities for which United States businesses, or those of other like-minded partner countries, would be competitive;</text></clause><clause id="idbe5b59ee319a4923a214e0d5e3e9a93e"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>legal, economic, governance, infrastructural, or other barriers limiting United States trade and investment in the Western Balkans;</text></clause><clause id="id88a1d8ef8904445b91f3c0fc51366774"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the effectiveness of existing regional cooperation initiatives, such as the Open Balkan initiative and the Western Balkans Common Regional Market; and</text></clause><clause id="id318c700bc3aa4f05bf82635bc341b4d2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>ways to increase United States trade and investment in the Western Balkans;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id24bb82e779b746b780a31b92a32393fe"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develops human and institutional capacity and infrastructure across multiple sectors of economies, including clean energy, energy efficiency, agriculture, small and medium-sized enterprise development, health, and cyber security;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6e7b816a0d514e91b9b75984ed5d49a3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>assists with the development and implementation of regional and international trade agreements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb51ab72dc48f4407a7a0f571d5cf2285"><enum>(F)</enum><text>supports women-owned enterprises and gender equality;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbdccd13830e04a15af89fbef545f199a"><enum>(G)</enum><text>promotes government and civil society policies and programs that combat corruption and encourage transparency, free and fair competition, sound governance, judicial reform, environmental protection, and business environments conducive to sustainable and inclusive economic growth; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idad1bf917a307466ab88f6c6d239a1ffb"><enum>(H)</enum><text>includes a public diplomacy strategy that describes the actions that will be taken by relevant agencies to ensure that populations in the Western Balkans are aware of the development activities of the United States Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id221f578741024e7a8653a0b0a36c9931"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall provide a briefing to the appropriate congressional committees that describes the progress made towards developing the strategy required under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id1c8464bab3ff4aeabf1e23f71589d729"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regional trade and development initiative</header><paragraph id="ide3ba62d7ba6640e28aba2b6074c1cdbe"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>The Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in coordination with the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation and the Secretary of Commerce, shall coordinate a regional trade and development initiative for the region comprised of each Western Balkans country and any European Union member country that shares a border with a Western Balkans country (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>Western Balkans region</quote>) in accordance with this subsection. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idce01debac7e84af4ab8880c780ceac1b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initiative elements</header><text>The initiative authorized under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="id9d992ffc55ce4de0a4686da9ff7ac367"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote private sector growth and competitiveness and increase the capacity of businesses, particularly small and medium-sized enterprises, in the Western Balkans region;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id178974f1014b423eae3616b09297f71b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seek to increase intraregional exports to countries in the Balkans and European Union member states;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3fc1085db85e4e71aa2da92304ccbeb7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>advance opportunities to increase United States exports to, and investments in, countries in the Balkans; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd04c8022526a4ecf9462355c22859d77"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support startup companies in the Western Balkans region by—</text><clause id="id31157FE7CE2346389541B59CB4AD4418"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing training in business skills and leadership;</text></clause><clause id="idC6BB7851B227456195E4B33A8D395EF4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing opportunities to connect to sources of capital; and </text></clause><clause id="id46B02B8084AE40D4BCD573EC37F44B8E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>encouraging startup companies that are led by youth or women;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4a5376bf293d4d928418aa144dfc8a8e"><enum>(E)</enum><text>encourage and promote inward and outward trade and investment through engagement with the Western Balkans diaspora community in the United States and abroad;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0c18df15a11148a2823d5231bac73db1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>provide assistance to the governments and civil society organizations of Western Balkans countries, through an inclusive process incorporating the input of local private sector and civil society stakeholders, to develop—</text><clause id="idb1bfad41f4fa4dd2aaa63085a868b313"><enum>(i)</enum><text>regulations to ensure fair, transparent, and effective investment; and</text></clause><clause id="idf492dece9c734f14a5778ac726111ccd"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>economic security policies, such as foreign direct investment screening mechanisms and anti-coercion initiatives, to identify and counter corrosive and malign investments and use of economic coercion by foreign countries potentially in the areas of critical infrastructure, critical technologies, dual use items, media, supply of critical inputs, and access to sensitive information and data; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6a4a9d7185e74fa7bb8bffd32c2ec3f6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>review existing assistance programming relating to the Western Balkans across Federal agencies—</text><clause id="id4df2632716cc4d88a04de40275025afa"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to eliminate duplication; and</text></clause><clause id="idd046ac34e86242c184f0442afb215d5f"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to identify areas of coordination within the Western Balkans region;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6bc6da766ca04c30a8d8bc3c4ceb1488"><enum>(H)</enum><text>identify areas where application of additional resources could expand successful programs to 1 or more countries in the Western Balkans region by building on the existing experience and program architecture;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0b0fad62e6a548778ca56d22a0fd8f34"><enum>(I)</enum><text>compare existing single-country sector analyses to determine areas of focus that would benefit from a regional approach with respect to the Western Balkans region; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7009604c26e74de59da73f1135c3f7c4"><enum>(J)</enum><text>promote intraregional trade throughout the Western Balkans region through—</text><clause id="ide92217474013430ea48d39627847aefc"><enum>(i)</enum><text>programming, including grants, cooperative agreements, and other forms of assistance;</text></clause><clause id="id97d7820c9727406e954ec280132d7dc3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expanding awareness of the availability of loans and other financial instruments from the United States Government, including from the United States International Development Finance Corporation and the Export-Import Bank of the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="id313d098245144227b404f7e16d91056b"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>coordinating access to existing trade instruments available through allies and partners in the Western Balkans region, including the European Union and international financial institutions.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id587d9715005c4daeb0f97521fb65a34b"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Support for regional infrastructure projects</header><text>The initiative authorized under paragraph (1), consistent with the BUILD Act of 2018 (division F of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/254">Public Law 115–254</external-xref>) and the European Energy Security and Diversification Act of 2019 (title XX of division P of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/94">Public Law 116–94</external-xref>), should facilitate and prioritize support for regional infrastructure projects, including—</text><subparagraph id="idea51f6b43f2144c0adf18b65b7a2c734"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transportation projects that build roads, bridges, railways and other physical infrastructure to facilitate travel of goods and people throughout the Western Balkans region, particularly international travel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idba864f2c1ad74ec68c1376518b44eed0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>technical support and investments needed to meet United States and European Union standards for air travel, including screening and information sharing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id77b719298d1040e595461ca698695655"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the development of telecommunications networks from trusted providers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6b557b52bd11433c84859ef7413d07ba"><enum>(D)</enum><text>infrastructure projects that connect Western Balkan countries to each other and to countries with which they share a border;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc9953bd0621e4bdf9d3b5c0e6f38273e"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the effective analysis of tenders and transparent procurement processes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd64f5b0a33014d46a7aad5546d27c90b"><enum>(F)</enum><text>investment transparency programs that will help countries in the Western Balkans analyze gaps and establish institutional and regulatory reforms necessary—</text><clause id="id7662F425D9B948818103A394E2108C80"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to create an enabling environment for trade and investment; and </text></clause><clause id="id26A5600D3BAC49A0928F2A8C48E3C896"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to strengthen protections against suspect investments through public procurement and privatization and through foreign direct investments;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd4c6dba740d749dea1dd7fb83f150028"><enum>(G)</enum><text>sharing best practices learned from the United States and other international partners to ensure that institutional and regulatory mechanisms for addressing these issues are fair, nonarbitrary, effective, and free from corruption;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddfff0d7270714e728f34754683bffff4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>projects that reduce reliance on fossil fuels and facilitate the transition to clean sources of energy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id759205e05bef4efe969eef793306272d"><enum>(I)</enum><text>technical assistance and generating private investment in projects that promote connectivity and energy-sharing in the Western Balkans region; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7684343a1b544e359cb0bdaa3e92ce98"><enum>(J)</enum><text>technical assistance to support regional collaboration on environmental protection that includes governmental, political, civic, and business stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id02A7CA816F464C3A8293B6A30DA9F631"><enum>(K)</enum><text>technical assistance to develop financing options and help create linkages with potential financing institutions and investors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7d9d4094b7394baba04705e96ceb2ff0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Loans</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="iddef5c5dde7a1445d9b51586aea8a7940"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts appropriated under the headings <header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-small">economic support fund</header-in-text> and <header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-small">assistance for europe, eurasia and central asia</header-in-text> in any Act making appropriations for the Department of State, foreign operations, and related programs may be made available for the costs (as defined in section 502 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661a">2 U.S.C. 661a</external-xref>)), of loan guarantees, including the cost of modifying loans and loan guarantees, for programs, projects, or activities in any Western Balkans country, which are authorized to be provided.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idddb30c9b89184bcbac77d4c1cf4d4a25"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Classification of loans and loan guarantees</header><text>Amounts made available under subparagraph (A) for the costs of loans and loan guarantees, including the cost of modifying loans and loan guarantees, shall not be considered assistance for the purposes of any provisions of law limiting assistance to a country.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide29284c5d77c47f097000b8dcb59552c"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consultation and notification</header><text>Amounts made available under this subsection shall be subject to—</text><clause id="id463db11901fc43789858b0cad0641b7d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prior consultation with the appropriate congressional committees; and</text></clause><clause id="id0611c0122398439f9a97ad6f843d0d78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the regular notification procedures of the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id310a7ae990a5476983d3484bb25174a9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>All programming under the initiative authorized under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="idfa02a3587dab43fb8257668de00a6900"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be open to the participation of each Western Balkan country;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id97088eae4a994dd787487f7081693369"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be consistent with European Union accession requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idad2600865f7c4eafa5e072b8caeb80fe"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be focused on retaining talent within the Western Balkans;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id13ff0db4cd7643018ec1ed9fa5e4c295"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promote government policies in Western Balkan countries that encourage free and fair competition, sound governance, environmental protection, and business environments that are conducive to sustainable and inclusive economic growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8c11dc09f3a240e8b6db06d640389e1c"><enum>(E)</enum><text>include gender analysis and efforts to promote gender equity; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida95ebff6ce2a45eaab297d4a9b099cd4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>include a public diplomacy strategy to inform local and regional audiences in the Western Balkans region about the initiative, including specific programs and projects; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id178065224c0d43228f3cf42643dbc277"><enum>(G)</enum><text>support the Western Balkans countries in meeting international commitments agreed to by the European Union on clean energy and energy security goals. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id3cbc91d171094423a14b3a010f17611b"><enum>(d)</enum><header>United States International Development Finance Corporation</header><paragraph id="idbfb0425fd3704f7c895302e0cf26eb14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointments</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, subject to the availability of appropriations, the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation, in collaboration with the Secretary of State, should take steps to ensure that—</text><subparagraph id="id5520f171798b429b9171eb98652bbed6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a regional office of the United States International Development Finance Corporation with responsibilities for the Western Balkans is established and operational in the Western Balkans region; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcc28f66623b842aa8c79d7c2b5b92e14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>sufficient full-time employees of the United States International Development Finance Corporation, including at least 1 permanent hire from the United States, are stationed in the regional office to serve United States interests in the Western Balkans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id10d00c0ac8b0404da1e6aaeb30ea26f1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that includes—</text><subparagraph id="id6dad348ce8d1476baca826898d73af1b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of the steps that have been taken to fulfill the requirements under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfcb1fbfe3a364b15831f846ec9e05084"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an account of any additional resources and authorities needed to complete the requirements under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6d3f6586b1d1418fb0423e98ff0541b4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the initial outreach plan for the new regional office of the United States International Development Finance Corporation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id87e483bd5c6c463a9aca4f75758e5807"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Joint report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation, the Secretary of State, and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall submit a joint report to the appropriate congressional committees that includes—</text><subparagraph id="id89aa4ddf9d254707b4d1c207d4c3a227"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the benefits of providing sovereign loan guarantees to countries in the Western Balkans to support infrastructure and energy diversification projects; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida3c9922839f340239c833a58639b1c78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an outline of additional resources, such as tools, funding, and personnel, which may be required to offer sovereign loan guarantees; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id63599221cb6645a3b4dd3237732b0546"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment of how the United States International Development Finance Corporation can deploy its insurance products in support of bonds or other instruments issued to raise capital through United States financial markets.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idde1305c6d5054559aa4d02532e6e273d"><enum>8.</enum><header>Countering malign influence and promoting cross-cultural engagement</header><subsection id="idc768fb162d044f22a0b0181ac96440df"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="idfe15aa7b1d31403b888c9499b90761eb"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promoting university partnerships in the Western Balkans, particularly in traditionally under-served communities, advances United States foreign policy goals and requires a whole of government approach, including the utilization of public-private partnerships;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id78a613d184714b34b3a1b8d4a71adc07"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such university partnerships would provide opportunities for exchanging academic ideas, technical expertise, research, and cultural understanding for the benefit of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id958a5f8d4b444f66b24bd482ca2d9db4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the 6 countries in the Western Balkans meet the requirements under section 105(c)(4) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151c">22 U.S.C. 2151c(c)(4)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6672157b1b7b4029950e3c5b3b1ed46f"><enum>(b)</enum><header>University partnerships</header><text>The President, working through the Secretary of State, is authorized to provide assistance, consistent with section 105 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151c">22 U.S.C. 2151c</external-xref>), to promote the establishment of university partnerships between the United States and the Western Balkans, including—</text><paragraph id="id29fc69dacf2849d6b2dc411147e3c2cd"><enum>(1)</enum><text>supporting research and analysis on foreign policy, cyber resilience, economic resilience, and disinformation; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb948cd04583d4a47b7618391d45f325f"><enum>(2)</enum><text>working with partner governments to reform policies, improve curricula, strengthen data systems, train teachers, and provide quality, inclusive learning materials;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id223a295e3b8142a6a2e702458343fa99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>providing individuals, particularly at-risk youth, women, people with disabilities, and other vulnerable, marginalized, or underserved communities, with relevant education, training, and skills for meaningful employment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id83e37e22b2ca45619177470bc4753448"><enum>(4)</enum><text>removing barriers to entering formal education for out-of-school individuals, assisting such individuals to stay in school, and providing an opportunity for any individuals left behind to catch up on schooling; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc4df2c51069543d8a33d9ce5054f7e66"><enum>(5)</enum><text>promoting teaching and research exchanges between institutions of higher education in the Western Balkans and in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc639929a3ecd4fc3aab65854e6cc8a2a"><enum>(6)</enum><text>encouraging alliances and exchanges with like-minded institutions of education within the Western Balkans and the larger European continent. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9df96f63c63b45cba5e9485ebfa34e5d"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="id25e66cc11ad44196a202f2724912d73c"><enum>9.</enum><header>Peace Corps in the Western Balkans</header><subsection id="id140c05bd9b8c4d93892dfb4e90b7dec3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="idf3112b9606774c0f8a3afff7d429ba19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Peace Corps should be reinstated in the Western Balkans by reopening Peace Corps programs in as many Western Balkans countries as safely possible, including where the Peace Corps had previously operated, or has suspended operations due to the COVID–19 pandemic;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id95b5f4852d544d4bbd13b4f65e8f024c"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Peace Corps should reopen its programs in as many of the Western Balkans countries as possible, including where the Peace Corps operated previously, but later suspended operations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd5a5d3f6262344d58bea6aa05eb16525"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Peace Corps, whose mission is to promote world peace and friendship, in part by helping the people of interested countries in meeting their need for trained men and women, provides an invaluable opportunity to connect the people of the United States with the people of the Western Balkans.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id115b0a97b3164c3ca8f4c593c01b56f8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Peace Corps shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that includes—</text><paragraph id="id1e4cdf5852e64ec791975d1f97e860f9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of current opportunities for Peace Corps expansion in the Western Balkans region; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id24bc85ac5c5a4e4d8ea7a859ecee6cec"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan and timeline for implementing the outcomes described in subsection (a) to facilitate expansion of Peace Corps presence in the Western Balkans region, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id56ca8f8e3e7e4f55a068d4ebf1876d3f"><enum>10.</enum><header>Balkans Youth Leadership Initiative</header><subsection id="id95c1c37a50f64bdeb1d04601b340224b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that regular people-to-people exchange programs that bring religious leaders, journalists, civil society members, politicians, and other individuals from the Western Balkans to the United States will strengthen existing relationships and advance United States interests and shared values in the Western Balkans region.</text></subsection><subsection id="idbaaa1156f048492d842961ba023068ca"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>The Secretary of State shall further develop and implement a program, which shall be known as the <quote>Balkans Youth Leadership Initiative</quote> (referred to in this section as <quote>BOLD</quote>) that promotes educational and professional development for young adult leaders and professionals in the Western Balkans who have demonstrated a passion to contribute to the continued development of the Western Balkans region.</text></subsection><subsection id="id806c0bf1ba6b42d7b8d0b97bd27d59df"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conduct of initiative</header><text>The goals of BOLD shall be—</text><paragraph id="id276ac0c1448b422dabb207cf470281e4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to build the capacity of young Balkan leaders in the Western Balkans in the areas of business and information technology, cyber security and digitization, agriculture, civic engagement, and public administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf8c171610f49474c9d011a954228f745"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to support young Balkan leaders by offering professional development, training, and networking opportunities, particularly in the areas of leadership, innovation, civic engagement, elections, human rights, entrepreneurship, good governance, and public administration; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd0e94a9d3b9b438dafeb22a00cbfb8ad"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to support young political, parliamentary, and civic Balkan leaders in collaboration on regional initiatives related to good governance, environmental protection, government ethics, and minority inclusion; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id83138f063144495590fcc252f328fd9a"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to provide increased economic and technical assistance to young Balkan leaders to promote economic growth and strengthen ties between businesses in the United States and in the Western Balkans.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idc643c882b3e64ce5a882d8901398ff43"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Fellowships</header><text>Under BOLD, the Secretary of State shall award fellowships to young leaders from the Western Balkans who—</text><paragraph id="id19b94708882c4db7846cc9ae6f2d83d7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are between 25 and 35 years of age;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id77dd214d0acc4f858a5d70cbb421cb13"><enum>(2)</enum><text>have demonstrated strong capabilities in entrepreneurship, innovation, public service, and leadership;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idec2e0343e1d44396a6b62311f30f6218"><enum>(3)</enum><text>have had a positive impact in their communities, organizations, or institutions, including by promoting cross-regional and multiethnic cooperation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1583fa631d8e4451858d9a212308ed89"><enum>(4)</enum><text>represent a cross-section of gender, regional, and ethnic diversity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6a5628b84fe84232b1a944aa61ca1097"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public engagement center</header><text>Under BOLD, the Secretary of State may seek to procure space, hire staff, and develop programming for the establishment of a flagship public engagement and leadership center in the Western Balkans that seeks—</text><paragraph id="id82EFDE78F7B7491085B836223BD5985D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to counter disinformation and malign influence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4F4315BD87174DE7B345AE9376F32334"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to promote cross-cultural engagement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idF2AF147F7C414394BD3D8C62A2BE8612"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to provide training for young leaders from the Western Balkans described in subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1E8F1FBCFAE5403FA49F45200056EB14"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to harmonize the efforts of existing venues throughout the Western Balkans established by the Office of American Spaces.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idaddf7cfbf28247c39a50662b00ff05da"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Briefing on certain exchange programs</header><paragraph id="id750631d131a4448fac56e63f3c80efbe"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, acting through the Assistant Secretary of State for Educational and Cultural Affairs, shall provide a briefing to the appropriate congressional committees that describes the status of exchange programs involving the Western Balkans region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0bce51b6e6b94f18b74f6229fcb2dc76"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The briefing required under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="id7390eb0f5c2f4b6585f9944d38e6d492"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the factors constraining the number and frequency of participants from Western Balkans countries in the International Visitor Leadership Program of the Department of State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5d8e3ace14344f20bf839c6c9b9348e3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify the resources that are necessary to address the factors described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2d529f53cf8d46b9a7240485c83f87c7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describe a strategy for connecting alumni and participants of professional development exchange programs of the Department of State in the Western Balkans with alumni and participants from other countries in Europe, to enhance inter-region and intra-region people-to-people ties.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id1a99e62a38294b7ea08d7091a24ca096"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="idaeae170d11b94ba080afb80db249c4bc"><enum>11.</enum><header>Supporting cybersecurity and cyber resilience in the Western Balkans</header><subsection id="id363bbe2a027149d7800a928d91b61a19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="id673758e2ab994b7ab209f57d793a5c94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>United States support for cyber security, cyber resilience, and secure ICT infrastructure in Western Balkans countries will strengthen the region’s ability to defend itself from and respond to malicious cyber activity conducted by nonstate actors and foreign actors, including foreign governments that seek to influence the region;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc94be5b498e04ca7b0f29bf33b246ecf"><enum>(2)</enum><text>insecure ICT networks that are vulnerable to manipulation can increase opportunities for—</text><subparagraph id="id766d75956dfa4405a4fd268f9a6bae74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the spread of disinformation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide53d777ff3eb442b96ad272800b32410"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disrupting or disabling critical infrastructure, including energy, telecommunications, water, health, finance, and other infrastructure that provides essential services to citizens;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5f6201589d3e4cd6b048286203b1d2a3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the spread of disinformation is a transnational threat; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id451bf539da504ef4aea66376ea9fbd16"><enum>(4)</enum><text>it is in the national security interest of the United States to support the cyber security and cyber resilience of Western Balkans countries.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide0018954867f48eea18e66862715fd1f"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on digital ecosystems</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a Digital Ecosystem Country Assessment for each Western Balkans country that did not undergo a Digital Ecosystem Country Assessment before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="id9e359fecce6540258395e5049709ab2c"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interagency report on cyber security and cyber resilience in Western Balkans countries</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and other relevant Federal Government agencies, shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that contains—</text><paragraph id="idf6d6d229fe094f6394622b3433260510"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an overview of interagency efforts to strengthen cyber security and cyber resilience efforts in Western Balkans countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide8bf7a70e88541848b4b1810468b8699"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a strategy to better strengthen the cyber security and cyber resilience of each Western Balkans country;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc64159e7fbb94d43bb61518f54304c67"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a review of existing United States Government cyber security initiatives that—</text><subparagraph id="id102dc6fe4d12446e8523b97de5fda98c"><enum>(A)</enum><text>counter disinformation in Western Balkans countries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id355cabe855ab4efd94382ed14c2e3466"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strengthen ICT infrastructure and cyber security capacity in the Western Balkans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1d828b3fd5d1428a8a3b4bc202b1e036"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support democracy and internet freedom in Western Balkans countries;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id376c62f84cd145ecb23f7ef85346bceb"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assessment of cyber threat information sharing between the United States and Western Balkans countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id39df120b548e46dc950b3284c4d9a270"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment of options for the United States to better support cyber security and cyber resilience in Western Balkans countries, including the posting of cyber professionals to United States diplomatic posts in Western Balkans countries and providing relevant training, such as technical capacity building and response and recovery efforts to Foreign Service Officers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4ac62a0c9ce24675bdb7c7391b3ceff7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a determination of United States additional support needed for the cyber security and cyber resilience Albania, Montenegro, North Macedonia, and Croatia, which are NATO allies. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id87486a0b37fd40a2b2f67a7136265174"><enum>12.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding an interim agreement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="id4660213174254de3b072db556a431547"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Agreement on the Path to Normalization of Relations, which was agreed to by Kosovo and Serbia on February 27, 2023, with the facilitation of the European Union, is a positive step forward in advancing normalization between the 2 countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc6b33124a35d41c49614733d53d54b80"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Serbia and Kosovo should seek to make immediate progress on the Implementation Annex to the agreement referred to in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide1c0d47be23646cd871ab122cca7d224"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Department of State shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees an evaluation of each country’s progress on the Implementation Annex referred to in paragraph (2);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd696087e514943fb96f59e329b322d5a"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States should not consider advancing the initiatives referred to in this Act to such country until sufficient progress has been made on the Implementation Annex;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcaffcaca4906435daf3bab8f2553bc03"><enum>(5)</enum><text>once sufficient progress has been made on the Implementation Annex, the United States should consider advancing additional initiatives to strengthen bilateral relations with both countries, which could include— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id64a769887276421da519224501a99fc3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing bilateral strategic dialogues; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5e0c228eb6604afd882b1133df7e19a3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advancing concrete initiatives to deepen trade and investment with both countries; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id12efd2fa28284aaebe4b8382f0b39f3c"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the United States should continue to support a comprehensive final agreement between Kosovo and Serbia based on mutual recognition. </text></paragraph></section><section id="id5D8EAB28F6F54BB6B3E71AA89D34AC3A"><enum>13.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Sections 5 and 6 of this Act shall cease to be effective on the date that is 10 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

